<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tei-to-html.xsl" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Grammar of Tamil (<foreign xml:lang="ta">cen tamiḻ</foreign>), by Beschi</title>
            
         <editor><persName>Cristina Muru</persName><orgName>DISTU Department, University of Tuscia</orgName></editor></titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TST Project</publisher>
            <date>2025</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>
                     <orgName>Bibliothèque nationale de France. Département des Manuscrits</orgName>
                  </repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Indien 192</idno>
                  <idno type="alternate"><idno>n. 282</idno><idno>Tamoul 192</idno></idno>
               <idno type="URI">https://archivesetmanuscrits.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cc103711q</idno></msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#STM">
                  <summary><p>This manuscript reproduces the Latin grammar of the High Tamil (<emph>centamiḻ</emph>) composed by the Italian Jesuit Giuseppe Costantino Beschi (1680-1740). </p></summary>
                  
               <msItem synch="#U1" xml:id="T1" defective="false" class="#illakkanam"><title xml:lang="la">Grammatica Latino Tamulica ubi De Elegantiori Linguæ Tamulica Dialecto செநதமிழ  dictâ cui adduntur tamulica poësos rudimenta ad usum Missionariorum Societatii Jesu</title><author xml:lang="la">Giuseppe Costantino Beschi (1680-1747)</author><textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="tam"/><incipit xml:lang="la"><p>†</p> <p>Pars prima</p> <p>Caput primum</p> <p>§us primus</p> <p>De Litteris</p> 
<p>I° ominis quo in lingua vulgari Grammaticâ de litteris fusé scripsimus</p></incipit><explicit xml:lang="la">sed nullâ aliâ arte quam ut (delectunt popolum, sue visum excisunt, ade[...] inutile fit in 117 artem inter[...])</explicit></msItem><msItem synch="#U1a" xml:id="T1" defective="false" class="#illakkanam"><title xml:lang="la">Religiosi et missionarijs C.J.B. salutem in domino plurinam</title><author xml:lang="la">Giuseppe Costantino Beschi (1680-1747)</author><textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="tam"/><incipit xml:lang="la">Cum anno clapso vulgaris Tamulica lingua Grammaticam Apostolico vestro desiderio famulatum prostiturus obsularium, brevi me nonnulla de Elegantioni hujus lingua dialecto daturum promoseram</incipit><explicit xml:lang="la"><ellipsis>...</ellipsis>quæ de elegantioni hâc Dialecto tradere constitui valete.</explicit></msItem></msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  
                  
                  
                  
                  
               <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="paper industrial">
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        
                     <support>
                           
                           
                        <p>There is watermark that is also found in other manuscripts (i.e. Indien 189, Indien 190, and Indien 634 – see Colas and Colas-Chauhan 1995: 67). It is represented by the letter T surmounted by a crown and placed on a base, itself surmounting a <emph>cartouche</emph> which contains a J followed by a fleur-de-lis and the name CUSSON (cf. nos. 3292 and 3293, pl. 424 and no. 694, pl 109 in  Heawood 1969 [1950]).</p></support><extent>
                           <measure unit="page" quantity="89">1 (bifolio) front guard leaf + 81 pages + 3 pages blank + 1 (folio) back guard leaf.</measure>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              
                              
                           </dimensions>
                        <dimensions type="object" unit="mm"/><dimensions type="written" unit="mm"/></extent><foliation>Original numeration on the right and left upper side of each page in Arabic numbers.</foliation><collation><desc xml:id="stiff-cover">CCMBR number: n. 282 (= <emph>Ancient fond</emph>, n° CCLXXXII, p. 448).</desc><desc xml:id="cover">the front cover. Shelfmark on recto. </desc><desc xml:id="u1">1 bifolio = front guard leaf. No foliation. Shelfmark on recto. Verso blank. </desc><desc xml:id="U1">84 pages = Grammar of the Tamil language (81 pages) + blank pages (3 pages).</desc><desc xml:id="U1a">5 folios = Title and preface</desc><desc xml:id="u2">1 folio = back guard leaf</desc><desc xml:id="cover">the back cover</desc></collation><condition>Very good state of preservation.</condition></supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        
                     <layout columns="1"><p>There are approx. 33-37 lines per page.</p>
<p>Brown ink.</p></layout></layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc><handDesc><handNote synch="#U1" scope="sole" script="latin tamil" scriptRef="#tamilPulliSporadic"><desc><p>Filliozat (1937: 283, fn. 1) states that this is a copy made by Abraham-Hyacinthe Anquetil-Duperron (1731-1805) (see Fr. Nouv. Acq. 22436 for an example of his handwriting). However, the handwriting in this manuscript seems to be similar to Jean Calmette's (1692-1739 or 1740) one. As he declares in a letter  sent from Ballabaram in 1732, he was among those Jesuits who copied some of the manuscripts sent to the Royal Library (fond Brotier 89, fol. 37a, 37b cited in Colas and Chauhan 1995: 11).</p>
<p><emph>puḷḷi</emph> is marked only on <emph>cinna ra</emph> otherwise is not regularly used.</p>
<p>Double-curled <emph>kompu</emph> is not used. The differentiation between <emph>o/ō</emph>, <emph>e/ē</emph> is marked by a stroke placed above the letter in order to mark the short C.</p><p>Differentiation between <emph>ra/ā</emph> is marked by a stroke palced above it. The <emph>periya ra</emph> is transrcibed with a double loop.</p></desc></handNote></handDesc><decoDesc>
                  <decoNote synch="#U1" corresp="#T1" type="drawing" subtype="top"><desc>At the beginning of each page there is a cross to mark that it is a Christian manuscript. The cross is placed in the upper side of the page in a centered position. </desc></decoNote></decoDesc><additions>
                  <desc><p>Grammatica</p><p>Latino-Tamulica</p><p>ubi</p><p>De Elegantiori Linguæ Tamulica Dialecto</p><p>செநதமிழ  dictâ</p><p> cui adduntur tamulica poësos rudimenta</p><p> ad usum</p><p>Missionariorum Societatii Jesu</p></desc><desc synch="#stiff-cover" type="shelfmark" subtype="cover top">CCMBR number: n. 282 (= <emph>Ancient fond</emph>, n° CCLXXXII, p. 448).</desc><desc synch="#cover" type="shelfmark" subtype="spine">BnF shelfmark sticker: "INDIEN 192"</desc><desc synch="#cover" type="shelfmark" subtype="beginning cover">BnF shelfmark sticker: "INDIEN 192"</desc><desc synch="#u1" type="shelfmark" subtype="beginning top">BnF shelfmark: "Tamoul 192"</desc><desc synch="#U1 #U1a" corresp="#T1" type="stamp">It is found at the beginning of the manuscript, on f. 1r, and at the end, on f. 81r. The stamp used is a red circle with a double line containing 3 fleurs-de-lil summounted by a crown with the inscription <emph>Bibliotheque Royal</emph>. This stamp is a variant of the stamp n. 21 in Josserand and Bruno (1960: 281) in use during the Restauration (July 1830 to half January 1831).</desc></additions><bindingDesc>
                     <binding><p><p>Apparently, the stiff covers (boards) at the front and back of the book are attached to the quires by the cords which are secured by means of channeling. </p><p>The boards and spine are covered with paper which is folded over the edges of the boards forming a turn-ins and glued down. Pastedowns of an initial and a final bifolios onto the inside of the board partially conceal these mechanism of the binding and also the channeling. The manuscript is made of 33 queris of six or three bifolios.</p> </p><decoNote type="stringhole"><measure unit="stringhole"/></decoNote></binding>
                  </bindingDesc></physDesc>
               <history>
                  
                  
                  
               <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="gregorian" notBefore="1730" notAfter="1739">In Vinson (1867: 49 and 1867-1868: 46) and Vinson and Feer (1866-: 46) the date is 1760 however being mentioned in the CCMBR (1739: 448) the date must be anticipated. Indeed, in Cabaton (1912: 32) the same date has been corrected with an annotation in 1739. However, the possibility of considering this manuscript as copied by Calmette allows to move the date further back up to 1730, even though it is not listed among the manuscripts that  Jesuits sent to France in order to enrich the Royal Library (see Omont 1902; Colas 1997).</origDate>
                     
                  </origin></history>
               <additional>
                  <listBibl>
                     
                  <bibl><p><emph>Anciens catalogues de la Bibliothèque du Roi et de différentes collections qui sont venues l'accroître aux XVIIe, XVIIIe et XIXe siècles. « Notices sur des manuscrits en langue européenne, relatifs à l'Inde : grammaires, dictionnaires, relations, etc., par M. Fauriel».</emph>Bibliothèque nationale de France. Département des Manuscrits. NAF 5445. Notice n° 12, f. 23r-v.</p> 
<p>Cabaton, Antoine. 1912. <emph>Catalogue sommaire des manuscrits indiens, indo-chinois et malayo-polynésiens.</emph> Paris: E. Leroux, p. 32.</p>
<p>CCMBR. 1739.<emph> Catalogus codicum manuscriptorum Bibliothecae regiae. Codices manuscriptos orientales, Tomus Primus.</emph>. MDCCXXXIX, p. 448.</p>
<p>Colas, Gérard. 1997. Les manuscrits envoyés de l’Inde par les jésuites français entre 1729 et 1735. In <emph>Scribes et manuscrits du Moyen-Orient</emph>, edited by Francis Déroche, François and Richard, Francis. Paris, France: Bibliothèque nationale de France, pp. 345-362.</p> 
<p>Colas, Gérard and Colas-Chauhan, U. 1995. <emph>Manuscrits telugu. Catalogue raisonné.</emph> Paris: Bibliothèque Nationale de France.  </p>
<p> Filliozat, Jean. 1937. Une Grammaire sanscrite du XVIIIe siècle et les débuts de l’indianisme en France. In <emph>Journal Asiatique</emph>, Tome CCXXIX. pp. 275-284.</p>
<p>Heawood, Edward 1969 [1950]. <emph>Watermarks mainly of the 17th and 18th centuries.</emph> Hilversum: The Paper Pubications Society.</p> 
<p>Feer, Léon. n.d.<emph> Tables du catalogue des manuscrits des manuscrits tamouls et télingas</emph>, Indien 578, f. 26r.</p>
<p><emph>Fragment de catalogue des manuscrits Tamouls, deuxieme partie, par Julien Vinson</emph>, c. 1869, Indien 1062,  f. 66bis.</p> 
<p> Josserand, Pierre and Jean Bruno. 1960. Les estampilles du Département des imprimés de la Bibliothèque nationale. In <emph> Mélanges d'histoire du livre et des bibliothèques offerts à Monsieur Frantz Calot</emph>. Paris: Librairie d’Argences, pp. 261-298.</p>
<p>Omont, Henri. 1902. XIV Missions en Chine et dans l’Inde. Fourmont aîné, les PP. Fouquet et de Prémare, Signard et le P. Le Gac (1684-1737). In <emph>Missions archéologiques françaises en Orient aux XVIIe et XVIIIe siècles. </emph>Seconde partie. Paris: Imprimerie nationale, pp. 806-851.</p>
<p>Vinson, Julien. 1867. <emph>Manuscrits tamouls</emph>. [Paris]. 49 p. Proof-readings. [Indien 1–204]</p> 
<p>Vinson, Julien. 1867-1868.<emph> Catalogue des manuscrits tamouls. Corrected proofreadings printed by the atelier oriental de l’Imprimerie nationale.</emph> Access No. 4-IMPROR-77 (B), p. 46.</p>
 <p>Vinson, Julien and Léon Feer and s.n. 1866–. <emph>Catalogue des manuscrits tamouls (1-574) et télingas (1-65)</emph>. Indien 577, f. 46</p></bibl></listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         
      <p><emph rend="bold">Transliteration conventions</emph> ― Conservative. Hence, <emph>puḷḷi, ō,</emph> and <emph>ē</emph> are used only if they are found in the manuscript. ― <emph rend="bold">Abbreviations</emph> ―
C = consonant, cf. = compare, f. = folio, ff. = folios, fn. = footnote, r. = recto.
</p></encodingDesc>
      
   <revisionDesc>
         
      <change when="2022-04">Record created by <persName>Cristina MURU</persName>. Version 1, April 2022.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
   </facsimile>
</TEI>