<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tei-to-html.xsl" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            
            
         <title><q>Illustrations of Hindoo Mythologies</q></title><editor><persName>Daniele CUNEO</persName><orgName>Sorbonne Nouvelle</orgName></editor></titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TST Project</publisher>
            <date>2022</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>
                     <orgName>Bibliothèque nationale de France. Département des Manuscrits</orgName>
                  </repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Indien 735</idno>
                  <idno type="alternate"/>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#STM">
                  
                  
               <summary>This beautiful lithograph collection of drawings contains 21 illustrations ranging  from numerous scenes from the <title xml:lang="sa"> Mahābhārata</title> storyline to some images of Hindu deities. Captions in Marathi help to identify the represented characters and sometimes the details of the action. The book was obtained in Bombay by Charles d'Ochoa in 1843 during a mission in search of manuscripts and printed sources.</summary><msItem defective="false"><title xml:lang="mar"><q>Illustrations of Hindoo Mythologies</q></title><textLang mainLang="mar"/></msItem></msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="paper industrial">
                        <support>
                           <measure unit="stringhole"/>
                           <p>The last three illustrations are on folded folios of larger size (485 x305 mm). Folios 16 through 18 are in blue paper.</p>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure unit="folio" quantity="24">1 guard, 21 numbered folios and 2 blank folios</measure>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <width quantity="295"/>
                              <height quantity="195"/>
                           </dimensions>
                        <dimensions type="object" unit="mm"/><dimensions type="written" unit="mm"/></extent>
                        <collation/>
                        
                        
                     <foliation>Numerals, upper-right corner</foliation><condition>Very good (only folio 19 has a small tear)</condition></supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc><handNote scope="major" script="devanagari"/></handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                  <decoNote type="drawing"><desc><locus facs="4">Folio 1</locus>: Kuntī and the 5 gods, fathers of her children, Yama, Vāyu, Indra and the Āśvins</desc></decoNote><decoNote type="drawing"><desc><locus facs="5">Folio 2</locus>: The churning of the ocean of milk. Śrīhari sits on top of Mount Mandara, mounted on its turn on the back of Kūrma, while the gods on one side (Mahādeva, Viṣṇu and Brahmadeva) and the demons on the other (Bāḻi, Rāhu and Ketu) are pulling on the serpent Vāsukī</desc></decoNote><decoNote type="drawing"><desc><locus facs="6">Folio 3</locus>: Duṣyanta, attended by two servants (rājabhṛtya) meets Śakuntalā and their son Bharata in front of the assembly</desc></decoNote><decoNote type="drawing"><desc><locus facs="7">Folio 4</locus>: Dharma and Nārada meet at the centre of a well-manned assembly (sabhā).</desc></decoNote><decoNote type="drawing"><desc><locus facs="8">Folio 5</locus>: Vasiṣṭha offers the Rāmāyaṇa to Rāma and Sītā, surrounded by Hanumān (Māruti) and his monkey army as well as Lakṣmaṇa, Bharata and Śatrughna.</desc></decoNote><decoNote type="drawing"><desc><locus facs="9">Folio 6</locus>: Arjuna and Śrīkṛṣṇa watch the gruesome scene of Bhīma splitting open the evil king Jarāsandha.</desc></decoNote><decoNote type="drawing"><desc><locus facs="10">Folio 7</locus>: Draupadī is represented three times, performing various actions in front of Kṛṣṇa and in the middle of a feast offered to Brahmins. </desc></decoNote><decoNote type="drawing"><desc><locus facs="11">Folio 8</locus>: Arjuna and Kṛṣṇa in their battle chariot, which carries on its banner Hanūmān (Māruti), rush towards the Khāṇḍava Forest already in flames. </desc></decoNote><decoNote type="drawing"><desc><locus facs="12">Folio 9</locus>: The forest exile of the Pāṇḍava (Pāṃḍavavanavāsagamana): Dharma, Bhīma, Arjuna, Nakula, Sahadeva, Draupadī and Dhaumya</desc></decoNote><decoNote type="drawing"><desc><locus facs="13">Folio 10</locus>: Duḥśāsana disrobes Draupadī in front of the assembly of Kauravas, on one side, and the five Pāṇḍava brothers and Śrīkṛṣṇa, on the other</desc></decoNote><decoNote type="drawing"><desc><locus facs="14">Folio 11</locus>:  Śrīśuka performs a recitation, in a Mandira erected on the Lokastambha, in front of Parīkṣit (<q>parikṣitī</q>), and surrounded by Brāhamaṇas on one side, and servants (bhṛtyagaṇa) on the other.</desc></decoNote><decoNote type="drawing"><desc><locus facs="15">Folio 12</locus>:  In the higher register, Draupadī and the five Pāṇḍava borthers give homage to Śrīkṛṣṇa. In the lower register, Draupadī offers food to a group of sages (ṛṣipaṅktī)</desc></decoNote><decoNote type="drawing"><desc><locus facs="18">Folio 13</locus>: Gaṅgā presents her son Bhīṣma to Śantanu, his father.</desc></decoNote><decoNote type="drawing"><desc><locus facs="19">Folio 14</locus>: Yayāti helps Devayāni out of the well.</desc></decoNote><decoNote type="drawing"><desc><locus facs="20">Folio 15</locus>: The game of dice between the Pāṇḍavas and Kauravas, the former represented on one side (Dharmarāja, Bhīma and Nakula), the latter on the other (Śakunī, Karṇa, Duryodhana and Duḥśāsana)</desc></decoNote><decoNote type="drawing"><desc><locus facs="21">Folio 16</locus>: The young Pāṇḍavas and Kauravas are wrestling, training and playing [?]. Duryodhana and Bhīma in the center, Arjuna, Dharma, Nakula and Sahadeva on one side, and Duḥśāsana, Śakunī, Karṇa and Śailya on the other</desc></decoNote><decoNote type="drawing"><desc><locus facs="22">Folio 17</locus>: Arjuna brings Drupada in ropes to king Droṇa</desc></decoNote><decoNote type="drawing"><desc><locus facs="23">Folio 18</locus>: Bhīṣma, accompanied by Arjuna and Dharma, offers worship to Droṇācārya (<q>bhīṣma droṇācāryā cī pūjā karitāta</q>)</desc></decoNote><decoNote type="drawing"><desc><locus facs="24">Folio 19</locus>: Śiva and Umā on Nandin on one side and Skanda embracing her spouse on the other</desc></decoNote><decoNote type="drawing"><desc><locus facs="24">Folio 20</locus>: The ṛṣi Atri (<q>Atrirusī</q>) and his father Dattātreya (<q>Dattātrī</q>)</desc></decoNote><decoNote type="drawing"><desc><locus facs="26">Folio 21</locus>: Kṛṣṇa (or Śiva) surrounded by female attendants and musicians</desc></decoNote></decoDesc>
                  <additions>
                  <desc type="shelfmark documenting-note" subtype="beginning flyleaf"><locus facs="2">Initial flyleaf, verso</locus>: <q rend="block"><lg>
  <l>N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 7</l>
  <l>Bombay 1943</l>
  <l>Charles d’Ochoa</l>
  </lg></q></desc></additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding/>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="gregorian" notBefore="1800" notAfter="1843"/>
                     
                  <origPlace>Maharashtra</origPlace></origin>
                  <provenance/>
                  <acquisition><p>Acquired by <persName role="collector">Charles d'Ochoa</persName>.</p></acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <listBibl>
                     
                  <bibl>Cabaton, Antoine. (1912). <title xml:lang="fr">Catalogue sommaire des manuscrits indiens, indo-chinois &amp; malayo-polynésiens. Bibliothèque nationale. Département des manuscrits.</title> Paris: E. Leroux. — See <ref target="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10329763p/f126">p. 107</ref>.</bibl><bibl>Kulkarni, A. R. (1988). <title type="article"><ref target="http://www.jstor.org/stable/44148429">Charles d’Ochoa : A French Orientalist of the Mid-19th Century</ref></title>. <title>Proceedings of the Indian History Congress</title>, 49, 447–455. </bibl></listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         
      <p>Names transcribed in IAST.</p></encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         
      <change when="2022-03">First version.</change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
   <graphic url="https://gallica.bnf.fr/iiif/ark:/12148/btv1b100911524/manifest.json"/></facsimile>
</TEI>