<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tei-to-html.xsl" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Catéchisme chrétien</title>
            
         <editor><persName>Cristina Muru</persName><orgName>DISTU Department, University of Tuscia</orgName></editor></titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TST Project</publisher>
            <date>2025</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>
                     <orgName>Bibliothèque nationale de France. Département des Manuscrits</orgName>
                  </repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Indien 564</idno>
                  <idno type="alternate"><idno>Tamoul 564</idno></idno>
               <idno type="URI">https://archivesetmanuscrits.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cc104092n</idno><idno type="URI">https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b52514303h</idno></msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#STM">
                  <summary>Christian religious text containing a Catechism written in Tamil.</summary>
                  
               <msItem xml:id="T1" defective="false"><title xml:lang="ta">Catéchisme chrétien</title><textLang mainLang="tam"/><incipit xml:lang="ta"><pb n="f1r" facs="9"/>
<lb n="1"/>Aṉāti ~ nama<seg rend="grantha">stu</seg>
<lb n="2-3"/>cātāraṇamāṉa cattiya-vēta-t·-tiru-capaiyil· paṭippikkiṟa ~ tiru-mantiraṅkaḷ  ~
<lb n="4"/>ciluvai-mantiram·</incipit><explicit xml:lang="ta"><pb n="f139r" facs="285"/>
<lb n="7-8"/>
Atukaḷukaku nāmum· paṅkāḷikaḷ āy-irukka caṟuvēcuraṉai vēṇṭi-k koḷḷukiṟatu</explicit><colophon xml:lang="ta"><pb n="f139r" facs="285"/>
<lb n="9-10"/>tiṟīttuvattukku tō<seg rend="grantha">sti</seg>ram ñāṉa Upatēcam· muṟṟum</colophon></msItem></msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  
                  
                  
                  
                  
               <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="paper industrial">
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        
                     <support>
                           
                           <p><p>Three different types of papers are used.</p><p>The first and third type is thin and transparent, yellowish in colour.</p><p>The third type has a recurring <watermark>watermark</watermark> represented by a bell and a symbol made of two wings and different initials i.e. D, G, C.<note> not found in Heawood 1969[1950])</note></p><p>The second type of paper is placed in the middle of the manuscript and it is bluish in colour. The recurrent <watermark>watermarks</watermark> here are a lion or a woman with a spier and a shield, both within a rounded framework which is surmounted by a crown with a cross above. Both are variants of <watermark>watermarks</watermark> in pl. 31-35 and 400-402, Heawood 1969 [1950]). A second <watermark>watermark</watermark> found in this kind of paper is represented by names and dates, i.e. <emph>1832 Clements</emph>; <emph>1833 J Rump</emph>; <emph>PC</emph> with an irregular alternation between even and odd pages.</p><p>The <watermark>watermarks</watermark> in type two and three of paper are so distributed:</p><p><emph>Paper Type 1</emph>
No <watermark>watermarks</watermark>: this kind of paper  runs from ff. 1r-59v, f. 68r-v.</p>
<p><emph>Paper type 2</emph>: <watermark><emph> watermark 1</emph></watermark> = woman with spier and shield within a crown with a cross above (130 mm height  x 80 mm width). It is found at ff.: 61–63, 66, 70.</p><p><watermark><emph>watermark 2</emph></watermark> = lion with spier within a crown with a cross above (150 mm height x 78 mm width). It is found at ff.: 77–79, 83–85, 87–88, 91, 95, 97.</p><p><watermark> <emph>watermark 3</emph></watermark> = Clements 1832. It is found at ff.: 64–65, 67, 69.</p><p><watermark>variant of <emph>watermark 3</emph></watermark> = B CLEMEN[ts] found at f. 71.</p><p><watermark><emph>watermark 4</emph></watermark> = PC (250 mm height  x 410 mm width). Found at f. 73.</p><p><watermark><emph>watermark 5</emph></watermark> = J Rump – 1833. Found at ff.: 74– 76, 80–82, 86, 89–90, 92, 94.</p>
<p><emph>Paper Type 3</emph></p><p><watermark><emph>watermark 6</emph></watermark> = bell (300 mm height  x 300/200). Found at: 1st front guard leaf, 3rd front guard/protective leaf, last protective leaf, and ff. 96, 98, 101–102, 106, 108–109, 111, 113, 115, 118, 120–121, 123, 125, 127–128, 131–132, 134–136.</p><p><watermark><emph>watermark 7</emph></watermark> = wings and letters (400 mm height x 540 mm width). It is found at: 2nd front guard leaf, and ff. 93, 99–100, 103–105, 107, 110, 114, 116–117, 119, 122, 124, 126, 129–130, 133, 137–139.</p></p>
                        </support><extent>
                           <measure unit="folio" quantity="143">3 front guard leaves + 139 folios + 1 back guard leaf </measure>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <width quantity="150"/>
                              <height quantity="220"/>
                           </dimensions>
                        <dimensions type="object" unit="mm"><width quantity="160"/><height quantity="220"/></dimensions><dimensions type="written" unit="mm"/></extent><foliation>Foliation is on the right upper side of the recto of each folio, no foliation on guard leaves. It is the library foliation in Arabic numbers. </foliation><collation><desc xml:id="cover">the front cover. Shelfmark on recto. </desc><desc xml:id="u1">3 folios = front guard leaf. No foliation. Shelfmark and watermark information on recto. Verso blank.</desc><desc xml:id="U1">139 folios = Christian paryers and Catechism. Library Arabic foliation on recto. </desc><desc xml:id="u2">1 folio = back guard leaf. No foliation. Blank recto verso.  </desc><desc xml:id="cover">the back cover</desc></collation><condition>Apart for the card-board which is loosing, the manuscript is in very good conditions and very legible.</condition></supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        
                     <layout><p>The layout of the page is marked with light pencil rows.</p><p>There are from a minimum of 21 lines per page to a maximum of 29. The most recurrent number of lines is 22, 24, or 26 lines per pages <note>other numbers are 25 and 27</note></p> </layout></layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc><handDesc><handNote synch="#U1" scope="sole" script="grantha tamil" scriptRef="#tamilPulliSporadic #tamilOE" medium="ink black brown"><desc><emph>Scriptio continua</emph>. Only in titles words are separated by hyphen. <emph>puḷḷi-s</emph>: not regularly used. <emph>C+ā</emph>, as well as <emph>ra</emph> are written with a diacritic represented by an horizontal stroke above. <emph>ra/ā</emph> are differentiated. <emph>Periya Ra</emph> ற is written with doouble loop. Modern writing. Experienced hand.</desc></handNote></handDesc><decoDesc>
                  <decoNote synch="#U1" corresp="#T1"><desc>Usage of single or double horizontal lines for marking the passage from one 'text' to another (e.g. at f. 3v two sets of thin double lines separate pāvaṅkīrattaṉam paṇṇukiṟatukku añcukariyam from t</desc></decoNote></decoDesc><additions>
                  <desc synch="#u1" type="shelfmark"><p>BnF shlefmark in black pencil: "Tamoul n. 564".</p><p>Notes: 1. Manuscrit Tamoul (139 feuilles); 2. filigrane du papier (Clements 1832).</p></desc><desc synch="#U1" type="stamp" subtype="beginning bottom">The stamp is in the recto of the first folio and in the blank verso of the last folio of the main text. Its size is 200 mm. It contains: <emph>Bibliothèque Nationale. MSS. R. F.</emph>. It is the stamp in use during the <emph>Second Republique</emph> (see n° 27 in Josserand and Bruno 1960:  282). It suggests that the manuscript was stamped between 1848 and 1852.</desc><desc synch="#U1" corresp="#T1" type="register" subtype="beginning bottom">R.D. 8996</desc><desc synch="#U1" type="shelfmark" subtype="beginning top">BnF shlefmark in black pencil: "Tamoul n. 564"</desc></additions><bindingDesc>
                     <binding><p><p>Original card-board covered with animal skin <note>probably goat.</note> The stiff covers (boards) at the front and back of the manuscript are attached to the quires by the cords which are secured by means of channeling. The boards and spine are covered with card-board, probably  covered with damp leather that is folded over the edges of the boards forming a turn-ins and glued down. Pastedowns of an initial and a final bifolios onto the inside of the board conceal theses mechanisms of the binding and also the channeling. One initial and one final guard leaf (2 bifolios+1 bifolio not numbered).</p><p> 21 quires in total: 1st, 2nd, 4th, 7th, 9th quires = quaternion; 3rd, 5th, 8th quires = ternio; from 10th to 12th quires = ternio; front guard leaf = 2 bifolios; back guard leaf = 1 bifolio.</p></p><decoNote type="stringhole"><measure unit="stringhole"/></decoNote></binding>
                  </bindingDesc></physDesc>
               <history>
                  
                  
                  
               <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="gregorian">1832/1833 (Cabaton 1912). The date is found in the watermarks of some folios (ff. 64–65, 67, 69, 71 – Clements 1832, and 74– 76, 80–82, 86, 89–90, 92, 94 – J Rump 1833). </origDate>
                     
                  </origin><provenance><p>M. Paul Sier controleur au ministéres as Finances, 42. Rue Pelet à Alfortville. Manuscrits en Tamouls: Tirittrayattukkutan rumajña upadisam XIX seicle, papier. 10 franchi. n°89986.</p></provenance><acquisition><p>Registre des acquisitions 1894-1950 n°8878 à 17571. </p></acquisition></history>
               <additional>
                  <listBibl>
                     
                  <bibl><p>Cabaton, Antoine. 1912. <emph>Catalogue sommaire des manuscrits indiens, indo-chinois et malayo-polynésiens.</emph> Paris: E. Leroux.</p>
<p>Heawood, Edward 1969 [1950]. <emph>Watermarks mainly of the 17th and 18th centuries.</emph> Hilversum: The Paper Pubications Society.</p> 
<p> Josserand, Pierre and Jean Bruno. 1960. Les estampilles du Département des imprimés de la Bibliothèque nationale. In <emph> Mélanges d'histoire du livre et des bibliothèques offerts à Monsieur Frantz Calot</emph>. Paris: Librairie d’Argences, pp. 261-298.</p></bibl></listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         
      <p><emph rend="bold">Transliteration conventions</emph> ― Conservative. <emph>puḷḷi, ē, ō</emph> are marked only if found in the manuscritp. ― <emph rend="bold">Abbreviations</emph> ― f. = folio, ff. = folios, r = recto, U/u = unit (codicological and/or textual), v = verso.</p></encodingDesc>
      
   <revisionDesc>
         
      <change when="2022-04">Record created by <persName>Cristina MURU</persName>. Version 1, April 2022.</change><change when="2024-06">Revised by <persName>Emmanuel FRANCIS</persName>. Version 2, June 2024.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
   <graphic url="https://gallica.bnf.fr/iiif/ark:/12148/btv1b52514303h/manifest.json"/></facsimile>
</TEI>