<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tei-to-html.xsl" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><title xml:lang="ta">Taṇṭiyalaṅkāram</title> (text &amp; commentary)</title>
            
         <editor><persName>Victor D'Avella</persName><orgName>University of Oxford</orgName></editor></titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TST Project</publisher>
            <date>2025</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>
                     <orgName>Bibliothèque nationale de France. Département des Manuscrits</orgName>
                  </repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Indien 206</idno>
                  <idno type="alternate"><idno>Tamoul 206</idno><idno>Ariel ?</idno></idno>
               <idno type="URI">https://archivesetmanuscrits.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cc103719x</idno><idno type="URI">http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b52510480g</idno><idno type="URI">https://didomena.ehess.fr/concern/data_sets/5999nc38f</idno></msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#STM">
                  
                  
               <summary><p>The manuscript contains the <title xml:lang="ta">Taṇṭiyalaṅkāram</title> along with its commentary. The text is very neatly written and accurate. Each chapter (<foreign xml:lang="ta">atikāram</foreign>) is started on a new folio with the chapter heading written in the left margin. Noteworthy are the diagrams for the <foreign xml:lang="ta">cittirakavi </foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="sa">citrakāvya</foreign>) figures and the list of abbreviations on the antepenultimate folio. The text of the commentary differs at times from what we find in printed editions (which also differ amongst themselves). The example verses, however, show much less variation.</p>

<p>Dimensions assessed by E. Francis (March 2023).</p>      
</summary><msItem synch="#U1" xml:id="T1" defective="false" class="#illakkanam"><title xml:lang="ta">Taṇṭiyalaṅkāram: Mūlam &amp; Urai</title><author xml:lang="ta">Taṇṭi</author><textLang mainLang="tam"/><finalRubric xml:lang="ta"><term xml:lang="en">Chapter end titles are found.</term>
</finalRubric></msItem><msItem synch="#U2" xml:id="T2" defective="false"><title xml:lang="ta">Taṇṭiyalaṅkāram: <term xml:lang="en">Register</term></title><textLang mainLang="tam"/></msItem></msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  
                  
                  
                  
                  
               <objectDesc form="pothi" rend="manuscript">
                     <supportDesc material="palm-leaf palmyra">
                        
                        
                        
                        
                     <support>
                           
                           
                        <p>Rounded edges.</p></support><extent>
                           <measure unit="folio" quantity="204">202 + {1} + {1} (U1 + U2 + U3). ― There are two guard leaves at the end which lack any numbering. The first of these (U2) has an index on the recto and verso; the latter (U3) is blank.</measure>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              
                              
                           <width quantity="380"/><height quantity="30"/></dimensions>
                        <dimensions type="object" unit="mm"><width quantity="380"/><height quantity="30"/><depth quantity="130"/></dimensions><dimensions type="written" unit="mm"/></extent><foliation>The manuscript has two sets of numerals. Bottom left recto, incised Tamil numerals up to <locus facs="405">199</locus> for U1.  The final two folios (U2 and U3) have no Tamil numerals. Upper right recto, library Arabic numerals in pencil up to <locus facs="409">201</locus>, including the final two folios, which do not bear Tamil numerals.  The Tamil numerals 47, 61 and 62 are used twice. The second such numbered folio has the Arabic numeral 47-bis, 61-bis and 62-bis. </foliation><collation><desc xml:id="CoverFront">the <emph rend="bold">front cover</emph>.</desc><desc xml:id="U1">202 folios = <emph rend="bold"><title xml:lang="ta">Taṇṭiyalaṅkāram</title>: Text &amp; Commentary</emph>. Tamil foliation 1-47, 47.2, 48-61.1, 61.2, 62.1, 62.2-199. Foliation sometimes unblackened. 2 folios foliated 47 by oversight. f61.2, f62.2 = folios inserted by the original copyist for additions. f61v, f62.2v, f165v, f199v blank. 380 x 30 mm.</desc><desc xml:id="U2">1 folio = <emph rend="bold"><title xml:lang="ta">Taṇṭiyalaṅkāram</title>: Table of Contents </emph>. No original foliation. Library foliation 200. 380 x 30 mm.</desc><desc xml:id="U3">1 folio = <emph rend="bold">guard leaf</emph>. No original foliation. Library foliation 201. Blank recto verso. 380 x 30 mm.</desc><desc xml:id="BackCover">the <emph rend="bold">back cover</emph>.</desc></collation><condition>Relatively good state of preservation, despite boreholes. ― The palm leaves are for the most part in excellent condition throughout. There is, however, sporadic damage from worms, occasionally becoming moderate especially in the latter half of the manuscript.</condition></supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        
                     <layout writtenLines="6">The manuscript is written in scriptio continua with moderate margins and space left around the string holes in the usual fashion. Two diagrams are incorporated into the left portion of a page with text written to the right of the left string hole (ff. <locus facs="355">174r</locus>, <locus facs="365">179r</locus>). A line of text at the top accompanies the long diagram on <locus facs="322">f. 157v</locus>.  Two diagrams occupy the left and center sections of <locus facs="352">f. 172v</locus>, and a single snake diagram takes up all of <locus facs="337">f. 165r</locus>. </layout></layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc><handDesc><handNote synch="#U1 #U2" scope="sole" script="tamil" scriptRef="#tamilPulliNone #tamilRa" medium="incised"><desc>The hand is very neat and regular with no peculiar features. There are occasionally interlinear and marginal corrections/additions, e.g., ff. <locus facs="68">33v</locus>, <locus facs="156">74v</locus>, etc.</desc></handNote></handDesc><decoDesc>
                  <decoNote synch="#U1" type="diagram"><desc><locus facs="322">f. 157v</locus>: a diagram for the poetic figure (<foreign xml:lang="ta">alaṅkāram/aṇi</foreign>) <foreign xml:lang="ta">kōmūttiri</foreign> (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="sa">gōmūtrikā</foreign>) ''cow-urine''. This is an example verse for TA 3.7. The verse is written in two lines and each <foreign xml:lang="ta">eḻuttu</foreign> is placed within a box forming a 24x2 grid. The same verse is also written in scriptio continua as part of the main textual body in lines <locus facs="321">f. 157r</locus>6 and <locus facs="322">f. 157v</locus>1. The point of the diagram is so that the reader can easily see that when the <foreign xml:lang="ta">eḻuttu</foreign>s are so arranged, the verse can be read from left to right or in a zig-zag. Cf. <title xml:lang="ta">Kāvyādarśa</title> 3.78f.   </desc></decoNote><decoNote synch="#U1" type="diagram"><desc><locus facs="337">f. 165r</locus>: a diagram for the poetic figure  <foreign xml:lang="ta">nākapantam</foreign> (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="sa">nāgabandha</foreign>). These are example verses for TA 3.7. The diagram is made up of two intertwined snakes each with four coils and running from left to riht with their heads facing one another at the left end. The <foreign xml:lang="ta">eḻuttu</foreign>s have been mostly written within the snakes but several lie outide their bodies because the diagram is incorrect. The correct diagram can be foud on p. 57 of <persName xml:lang="ta">Kōpālakiruṭṭiṇamācāryar</persName>'s edition, 1962. The <foreign xml:lang="ta">nākapantam</foreign> consists of two verses which must have the same <foreign xml:lang="ta">eḻuttu</foreign> in certain places. When the <foreign xml:lang="ta">eḻuttu</foreign>s are written in the snakes bodies, the repeated <foreign xml:lang="ta">eḻuttu</foreign>s are where the snake coils back on itself or the two snakes overlap.  Cf. <title xml:lang="sa">Pratāparudrīya</title> of <persName xml:lang="sa">Vidyānātha</persName>, pp. 348f. </desc></decoNote><decoNote synch="#U1" type="diagram"><desc><locus facs="352">f. 172v</locus>: two diagrams for the poetic figure <foreign xml:lang="ta">cuḻikuḷam</foreign> "whirl pool" (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="sa">ardhabhrama</foreign>).  The verses are examples ad TA 3.7. As in the diagram on <locus facs="321">f. 157v,</locus> the <foreign xml:lang="ta">eḻuttu</foreign>s have been arranged in boxes so as to better display the possibilities for reading the verses, which are written out as part of the main textual body in lines <locus facs="351">f. 172r</locus>2f. and <locus facs="353">173r</locus>1f. Each grid measures 9x4 although the 9th column in both cases is empty. The addition of the extra column was likely to fill out space. One grid is placed to the left of the left string hole and the second is between the two string holes. The label, <foreign xml:lang="ta">itu cuḻikuḷam</foreign>, sits to the left of the second grid.  We can read the poem from left to right and then down as well as in a "whirl", i.e., one starts in the upper left-hand corner reads down the left column, up the right most column, then down the second column, up the 7th column, and so forth.  Cf. <title xml:lang="sa">Kāvyādarśa</title> 3.80f. </desc></decoNote><decoNote synch="#U1" type="diagram"><desc><locus facs="355">f. 174r</locus>: a diagram for the poetic figure <foreign xml:lang="ta">caruppatōpattiram</foreign> (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="sa">sarvatobhadra</foreign>) and an example ad TA 3.7. Much like the previous diagrams, the <foreign xml:lang="ta">eḻuttu</foreign>s have been written in a grid so as to better present the various ways one can read the poem. The same verse is also written in scriptio continua as part of the main textual body in lines <locus facs="354">173v</locus>3ff. In this instance the grid is an 8x8 square and contains the 4 line poem written twice: once in its original order and then again mirrored over the x-axis, i.e., the 4th and 5th lines are identical as are the 3rd and 6th and so forth. The lower mirrored part  demonstrates that each column, when read top to bottom and then again bottom to top will be identical to the first line. Similarly each line reads the same backwards and forwards. Cf. <title xml:lang="sa">Kāvyādarśa</title> 3.80 and 82.</desc></decoNote><decoNote synch="#U1" type="diagram"><desc><locus facs="365">f. 179r</locus>: a diagram for the poetic figure <foreign xml:lang="ta">muracapantam</foreign> (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="sa">murajabandha</foreign>) and another example ad TA 3.7. The verse is written out as part of the 12x4 grid of <foreign xml:lang="ta">eḻuttu</foreign>s in the same manner as the others and placed to the left of the first string hole. The same verse is also written in scriptio continua as part of the main textual body in lines <locus facs="364">f. 178v</locus>2f.  As before, the grid helps the reader better identify the various paths along which one can read the verse. In the <foreign xml:lang="ta">muracapantam</foreign>, same line can be read left to right then down or along a zigzag in the manner of the strings that bind down the heads of drum. Cf. <title xml:lang="sa">Kāvyālaṅkāra</title> of <persName xml:lang="ta">Rudraṭa</persName> 5.19.</desc></decoNote></decoDesc><additions>
                  <desc synch="#CoverFront" type="shelfmark" subtype="cover front">BnF current shelfmark sticker, covering an older sticker: <quote>INDIEN 206</quote> (<locus facs="1">front cover, recto</locus>).</desc><desc synch="#CoverFront" type="documenting-note" subtype="cover front">BnF donation sticker <quote>DON N° <space type="vacat"/></quote> (<locus facs="1">front cover, recto</locus>).</desc><desc synch="#CoverFront" subtype="cover front right">Number <quote xml:lang="ta"><num rend="traditional">360</num></quote> engraved (<locus facs="2">front cover, verso</locus>).</desc><desc synch="#U1" type="register" subtype="end">List of abbreviations, the divisions of consonants (<foreign xml:lang="ta">iṉam</foreign>), and examples of the cases (<locus facs="405">f199r</locus>).
</desc><desc synch="#U1" type="intertitle" subtype="marginal left">Chapter/section headings are given in the margin. See below.
</desc><desc synch="#U1" type="verse-beginning">Left-marginal <foreign xml:lang="sa">pratīka</foreign>s.</desc><desc synch="#U1" type="correction">f61.2, f62.2 = folios inserted by the original copyist. Both start with the sign “+” and the page is not entirely written.
</desc><desc synch="#U2" corresp="#T2" type="table-of-contents">List of <foreign xml:lang="ta">cūttiram</foreign>s (no title; 5 + 2 columns): <foreign xml:lang="ta">cūttiram</foreign>'s beginning, followed by its serial number. ― List of the beginning of the <foreign xml:lang="ta">cūttiram</foreign>s in the first two <foreign xml:lang="ta">atikāram</foreign>s ("chapters") (<locus facs="407">f[1]r = lf200r</locus>). The serial number occurs as the end of each line. The text is written in 5 columns on the recto and continues onto the verso in two columns. The list is not entirely accurate.</desc></additions><bindingDesc>
                     <binding><p>The palm leaves are cased in two original <material>wood</material> covers. 376 x 31 x 12 mm. Polished, varnished on the exterior sides. </p><decoNote type="stringhole"><measure unit="stringhole" quantity="2"/></decoNote></binding>
                  </bindingDesc></physDesc>
               <history>
                  
                  
                  
               <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="gregorian" notBefore="1800" notAfter="1854">The manuscript was part of Ariel's collection and may well have been comissioned by him based on the good condition of the leaves.</origDate>
                     
                  <origPlace>Tamilnadu (Pondicherry?)</origPlace></origin><provenance><p>Owned by <persName role="collector" key="Ariel, Édouard">Édouard Ariel</persName> (1818-1854). Bequeathed by Édouard Ariel to Société Asiatique (Rosny 1868, p. 177).</p></provenance><acquisition><p>Received, August 1st, 1866, from the Société Asiatique. —  See BnF, Département des Manuscrits, Inventaire 7 = dons : manuscrits et imprimés documentaires, 1848-1895, n° 1 à 3306: <ref target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b104635317/f78">no. 1192</ref>.</p></acquisition></history>
               <additional>
                  <listBibl>
                     
                  <bibl><title xml:lang="sa">Kāyvādarśa </title> of <persName xml:lang="sa">Daṇḍin</persName>.  <title xml:lang="de">Śabdālaṃkāradoṣavibhāga, die Unterscheidung der Lautfiguren und der Fehler: kritische Ausgabe des dritten Kapitels von Daṇḍins Poetik "Kāvyādarśa" und der tibetischen Übertragung "Sñan ṅag loṅ" samt dem Sanskrit-Kommentar des Ratnaśrījñāna, dem tibetischen Kommentar des Dpaṅ Blo gros brtan pa und einer deutschen Übersetzung des Sanskrit-Grundtextes</title>. Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz, 2011. </bibl><bibl><title xml:lang="sa">Pratāparudrīya</title> of <persName xml:lang="sa">Vidyānātha</persName>. <title>The Pratāparudrayaśobhūshaṇa of Vidyānātha with the commentary, Ratnāpaṇa, of Kumārasvāmin, Son of Mallinātha.</title> Ed. <persName xml:lang="sa">Kamalāśaṅkara Prāṇaśaṅkara Trivedī</persName>. Bombay Sanskrit and Prakrit Series, No. LXV. Bombay: Government Central Press, 1914.</bibl><bibl><title xml:lang="ta">Taṇṭiyalaṅkāram</title> of <persName xml:lang="ta">Taṇṭi. </persName> <title xml:lang="ta">Taṇṭiyāciriyar iyaṟṟa Taṇṭiyalaṅkāram mūlamum paḻaivuraiyum ... Vai. Mu. Caṭakōparāmānujācārya Svāmikaḷ iyaṟṟa kuṟippuraiyuṭaṉ.</title> Ed. <persName xml:lang="ta">Vai. Mu. Kōpālakiruṭṭiṇamācaryar</persName>. <placeName xml:lang="ta">Ceṉṉai</placeName>: <orgName xml:lang="ta">Āṉantāpārvati Accakam and Śrīrāmaliṅkam Accakam</orgName>, 1956.</bibl><bibl>Cabaton, Antoine. 1912. <title xml:lang="fr">Catalogue sommaire des manuscrits ind  iens, indo-chinois et malayo-polynésiens</title>. Bibliothèque nationale. Département des man  uscrits. Paris: E. Leroux. — See <ref target="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10329763p/f52">p. 34, no. 206</ref>.</bibl><bibl>Rosny, Léon de. 1868. <title type="article">La bibliothèque tamoule de M. Ariel, de Pondichéry</title>. In <title>Variétés orientales</title>, 177‒224. Paris: Maisonneuve. </bibl></listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         
      <p>The Tamil text has been given twice. Once in Tamil script approximating as closely as possible the text as it appears in the manuscript. The transliterated text, however, is interpretative in that it follows how the text would be printed in a modern edition with <foreign xml:lang="ta">puḷḷi</foreign>s long <foreign>ē</foreign>/<foreign>ō</foreign>, etc. </p></encodingDesc>
      
   <xenoData type="webannotation"><![CDATA[[]]]></xenoData><revisionDesc>
         
      <change when="2022-04">First version.</change><change when="2022-06">Revised by <persName>Emmanuel FRANCIS</persName>. Version 1, June 2022.</change><change when="2023-04">Revised and updated by <persName>Emmanuel FRANCIS</persName>. Version 2, April 2023.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
   <graphic url="https://gallica.bnf.fr/iiif/ark:/12148/btv1b52510480g/manifest.json"/></facsimile>
<text synch="#U1" corresp="#T1" xml:lang="ta"><body>
  <ab>
    <pb facs="3" n="1r"/>
<fw place="left-margin">
    <lb n="1"/>சொலலின
  <lb n="2-3"/>திருசசிறறமபலம
  <lb n="4-5"/>தெணடியலஙகாாம    
   <lb n="6"/>முதலாவது
   <lb n="7"/>பொதுவணி
   <lb n="8"/>இயல
   </fw>
    
     <lb n="1"/>சொலலின கிழததி மெலலியவிணையடி சிநதைவைததியமபுவல செயயுடகணி<g ref="#kompu"/><supplied>ய</supplied> ~ <supplied>எ</supplied>னின ~ இவவதிகாாமணியினதிலகக
  <lb n="2"/>ணமுணாததினமையினணியதிகாாமெனனுமபெயாதது ~
    
  <pb facs="46" n="22v"/>
  <lb n="1"/><gap reason="ellipsis"/> முதலதுபொதுவணியினமுறறும ~ திருசசிறறமபலம ~ <g ref="#pcl"/> இனியிரணடாவது பொருளணியியல <g ref="#pcl"/>
    
<pb facs="47" n="23r"/>
<fw place="left-margin">
  <lb n="1"/>இரணடாவது
  <lb n="2"/>பொருளணி
  <lb n="3"/>யியல
    </fw>
    
    <pb facs="247" n="120r"/>
  <lb n="5"/><gap reason="ellipsis"/> பொருளணியியன முறறும ~ <g ref="#pcl"/> <gap reason="ellipsis"/>
    
     <pb facs="248" n="120v"/><app><note xml:lang="en">blank page</note></app>
    
<pb facs="249" n="121r"/>
<fw place="left-margin">
  <lb n="1"/>
  <lb n="2"/>மூ<supplied>ன</supplied>றா<supplied>வ</supplied>து
  <lb n="3"/>சொலலணி
  <lb n="4"/>யி<supplied>ய</supplied>ல
  </fw>
    
    <pb facs="404" n="198v"/>
  <lb n="1"/>துவிகறபமபடவுரைததலிலககணமெனபது ~ எனனை ~ முனறொன முடிபெருஙகொததுபபினனொனவெணடும   துவிகறபஙகூறியழியா
  <lb n="2"/>மாபினது ~ வழிநூலாகும ~  எனறாாாகலின ~ வழுவணியியனமுறறும ~ அணியதிகாாமுடிநதது முறறும ~
    
    <pb facs="405" n="199r"/><app><note xml:lang="en">The following bit of text is written in the same hand across the leaf in three columns divided by the string holes. It contains a list of abbreviations, the divisions of consonants (<foreign xml:lang="ta">iṉam</foreign>), and examples of the cases.</note>
</app>
  <cb n="1"/>
  <lb n="1"/>இள இதனுள ~ இதன பொருள ~ 
  <lb n="2"/>எம ~ எனவும ~
  <lb n="3"/>உம ~ உதாரணம ~
  <lb n="4"/>வம ~ வரும ~
  <lb n="5"/>வறு ~ வரலாறு ~

    <cb n="2"/>
  <lb n="1"/>எனனின ~ எனபதெனனெனின
  <lb n="2"/>எனபதெனனுதலிறறொவெனின
  <lb n="3"/>உணா~றறு ~ உணாததுதனுதலிறறு
  <lb n="4"/>வலலினமெனப ~ ககடதபற
  <lb n="5"/>மெனலினமெனப ~ யாலவழல
  <lb n="6"/>இடையினமெனப ~ ஙஞணநமன

    <cb n="3"/>
  <lb n="1"/>வெறறுமைசசூததிரம
  <lb n="2"/>ஐ ஒடு கு இன ~ அது கணணெனனுமவவாறெனப
  <lb n="3"/>வெறறுமையுருபெ ~ ஐ அவனவளது ~ ஒடு
  <lb n="4"/>அவனொடு அவளொடு ~ அதொது ~ கு அவ
  <lb n="5"/>னுககு ~ அவளுககு ~ அதுககு ~ இன ~ அவனின
  <lb n="6"/>அவரின ~ அதின ~ அது ~ அவனது ~ அவளது ~
  <lb n="7"/>அதுனது ~ கண ~ அவனகண ~ <g ref="#pcl"/>
    
         <pb facs="406" n="199v"/><app><note xml:lang="en">blank page</note></app>
  
  </ab>
  
  <ab>
    
    <pb facs="3" n="1r"/>
    <fw place="left-margin">
<seg function="verse-beginning">
      <lb n="1"/>colliṉ</seg>
     <seg function="blessing"><lb n="2-3"/>tirucciṟṟampalam</seg>
    <seg function="title"><lb n="4-5"/>teṇṭiyalaṅkāram<app><note xml:lang="en">Note the alternate spelling for <foreign xml:lang="ta">taṇṭiyalaṅkāram</foreign> with <foreign xml:lang="ta">te</foreign>°.</note></app></seg>
     <seg function="intertitle"><lb n="6"/>mutalāvatu
  <lb n="7"/>potuvaṇi
  <lb n="8"/>Iyal</seg>
      </fw>
    
    <seg function="incipit">  
<lb n="1"/>colliṉ kiḻatti melliya viṇaiyaṭi cintaivait tiyampuval ceyyuṭ kaṇiyē <supplied>e</supplied>ṉiṉ ~ Ivvatikāram eṉṉa peyarttō veṉiṉ aṇiyiṉat<pc>’</pc> ilakka
<lb n="2" break="no"/>ṇam uṇarttiṉamaiyiṉ aṇiyatikāram eṉṉum peyarttu ~</seg>
    
    <pb facs="46" n="22v"/>
<lb n="1"/><gap reason="ellipsis"/> <seg function="completion-statement"><sic>mutalatu</sic> potuvaṇiyiyaṉ muṟṟum ~</seg> <seg function="blessing">tirucciṟṟampalam ~ <g ref="#pcl"/></seg> <seg function="intertitle">Iṉi yiraṇṭāvatu poruḷ aṇiyiyal <g ref="#pcl"/></seg>
    
    <pb facs="47" n="23r"/>
    <fw place="left-margin">
<seg function="intertitle"> 
      <lb n="1"/>Iraṇṭāvatu
      <lb n="2"/>poruḷaṇi
      <lb n="3" break="no"/>yiyal</seg>
      </fw>

    <pb facs="125" n="61.2r"/>
    <fw place="left-margin">
      <lb n="1"/>+
      </fw>
    <lb n="1-4"/><gap reason="ellipsis"/>
    
        <pb facs="126" n="61.2v"/><app><note xml:lang="en">blank page</note></app>
             
     <pb facs="131" n="62.2r"/>
    <fw place="left-margin">
      <lb n="1"/>+
      </fw>
    <lb n="1-"/><gap reason="ellipsis"/>
                    
        <pb facs="132" n="62.2v"/><app><note xml:lang="en">blank page</note></app>
    
    <pb facs="247" n="120r"/>
    <lb n="5"/><gap reason="ellipsis"/> poruḷ aṇiyaṉ muṟṟum ~<g ref="#pcl"/> <gap reason="ellipsis"/>
    
        <pb facs="248" n="120v"/><app><note xml:lang="en">blank page</note></app>
    
<pb facs="249" n="121r"/>
    <fw place="left-margin">
<seg function="verse-beginning">
  <lb n="1"/>Eḻuttiṉ</seg>
 <seg function="intertitle"><lb n="2"/>mū<supplied>ṉ</supplied>ṟā<supplied>va</supplied>tu
      <lb n="3"/>collaṇi
      <lb n="4" break="no"/>yi<supplied>ya</supplied>l</seg>
      </fw>
    
    <pb facs="404" n="198v"/>
<seg function="explicit"><lb n="1"/>tu vikaṟ pampaṭa vuraittal ilakkaṇam eṉpatu ~ Eṉṉai ~ muṉṉōraṉ  muṭiperuṅkottup piṉṉōṉ vēṇṭum vikaṟpaṅ kūṟi vaḻiyā
<lb n="2"/>marapiṉatu ~ vaḻinūl ākum Eṉṟār ākaliṉ</seg> ~ <seg function="completion-statement">vaḻuvaṇiyiyaṉ muṟṟum ~ Aṇiyatikāra muṭintatu muṟṟum ~</seg> 
    
     <pb facs="405" n="199r"/><app><note xml:lang="en">The following bit of text is written in the same hand across the leaf in three columns divided by the string holes. It contains a list of abbreviations, the divisions of consonants (<foreign xml:lang="ta">iṉam</foreign>), and examples of the cases.</note></app>

  <cb n="1"/>
    <lb n="1"/>Iḷ ~ Itaṉuḷ ~ Itaṉporuḷ ~
<lb n="2"/>Em ~ Eṉavum ~
  <lb n="3"/>Um ~ Utāraṇam
  <lb n="4"/>vam ~ varum
  <lb n="5"/>vaṟu ~ varanāṟu
  
    <cb n="2"/>  
  <lb n="1"/>Eṉṉiṉ ~ Eṉpat<pc>’</pc> eṉṉ eṉiṉ
  <lb n="2"/>Eṉpat<pc>’</pc> eṉ ṉutaliṟṟō veṉiṉ
<lb n="3"/>Uṇar~ṟṟu ~ Eṇarttuta ṉutaliṟṟu
  <lb n="4"/>valliṉam eṉpa ~ ka ca ṭa ta pa ṟa
  <lb n="5"/>melliṉam eṉpa ~ ya ra la va ḻa la
  <lb n="6"/>Iṭaiyiṉam eṉpa ~ ṅa ña ṇa na ma ṉa
  
    <cb n="3"/>

  <lb n="1"/>vēṟṟumaiccūttiram<app><note xml:lang="en">TE 113n/4.11</note></app>
  <lb n="2"/>Ai Oṭu ku iṉatu kaṇṇ eṉṉum avvār<pc>’</pc> eṉpa
  <lb n="3"/>vēṟṟumai yurupē ~ Ai Avaṉ avaḷatu ~ Oṭu
  <lb n="4"/>Avaṉoṭu Avaḷoṭu ~ Atoṭy ~ ku ~ Ava
  <lb n="5"/>ṉukku ~ Avaḷukku ~ Atukku ~ Iṉ ~ Avaṉiṉ
  <lb n="6"/>Ataṉatu ~ kaṇ ~ Avaṉkaṇ ~
             
    <pb facs="406" n="199v"/><app><note xml:lang="en">blank page</note></app>    
   
  </ab>
</body></text><text synch="#U2" corresp="#T2" xml:lang="ta"><body>
  <ab>
    
    <pb facs="407" n="[1]r"/>
    <seg function="table-of-contents"><cb n="1"/>
    <lb n="1"/>colliṉ ~ 1 ~
    <lb n="2"/>ceyyuḷ eṉpavai ~ 2 ~
    <lb n="3ff."/><gap reason="ellipsis"/>
    
     <cb n="2"/>
    <cb n="3"/>
    <cb n="4"/>
    <cb n="5"/>

     <pb facs="408" n="[1]v"/>
    <cb n="1"/>
       <cb n="2"/>
    <lb n="1"/><gap reason="ellipsis"/>
    <lb n="2"/>muḻuvatu 22</seg>    
    
  </ab>
</body></text></TEI>