<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tei-to-html.xsl" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tamil Grammar (in French) by La Lane</title>
            
         <editor><persName>Cristina Muru</persName><orgName>University of Tuscia</orgName></editor></titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TST Project</publisher>
            <date>2023</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>
                     <orgName>Bibliothèque nationale de France. Département des Manuscrits</orgName>
                  </repository>
                  
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Indien 189</idno>
                  <idno type="alternate"><idno>Tamoul 189</idno><idno>Ancien fonds 207</idno></idno>
               <idno type="URI">https://archivesetmanuscrits.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cc103708d</idno><idno type="URI">https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b531609463</idno><idno type="URI">https://didomena.ehess.fr/concern/data_sets/hd76s748g</idno></msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#STM">
                  <summary><p>BnF Indien 189 (ex- Tamoul 189), entitled <title xml:lang="fr">Grammaire Pour apprendre la Langue Tamoul Ditte Vulgairement le Malabar</title> on its title page (U1, <locus facs="3">p. 1</locus>) consists in 28 paper leaves (U2, that is, 56 pages) bound in one volume (260 x 200 mm). An unfoliated folio comes first, bearing the title-page on the recto (U1, <locus facs="3">p. 1</locus>) and a preface (“Préface”) on the verso (U1, <locus facs="4">p. 2</locus>). 26 folios follow (U2), all paginated except for <locus facs="56">p. 52</locus>.</p>

<p> The original pagination appears on the upper left corner of the page on the versos of folio and on the upper right corner on the rectos. Finally, there is a back guard leaf (u1).</p>

<p>This manuscript is a grammar of Tamil written in French organized into three sections, each one with a different number of chapters. The first section includes 2 chapters, the second 5 chapters, and 1 chapter.</p>

<p>The first section, <quote xml:lang="fr"><emph rend="bold">Premiere Partie. Des Lettres de l’Alphabet Tamoul</emph></quote> [First part. On the letters of the Tamil Alphabet] (U2, <locus facs="5">p. 1</locus>–<locus facs="13">p. 9</locus>) includes 2 chapters, which describe Tamil vowels and consonants, while a short preface (U1, <locus facs="4">p. 2</locus>), describing the extension of the geographical area where the Tamil language is spoken, precedes it on the verso of the front unfoliated folio. The two chapters are:</p>

<list>
	<item><quote xml:lang="fr">Chapitre 1er. Des Voyelles des Tamouls</quote> [1st Chapter. On the vowels of the Tamils] (U2, <locus facs="5">p. 1</locus>).</item>
	<item><quote xml:lang="fr">Chapitre 2e Des Consonnes des Tamouls</quote> [2nd Chapter. On the consonants of the Tamils] (U2, <locus facs="6">p. 2</locus>-<locus facs="13">p. 9</locus>).</item>
</list>

<p>The second section, <quote xml:lang="fr"><emph rend="bold">Seconde Partie</emph></quote> (U2, <locus facs="13">p. 9</locus>–<locus facs="43">p. 39</locus>) is divided into five chapters, as follows:</p>

<list>
	<item><quote xml:lang="fr">Chapitre 1er. Des Noms Tamouls</quote> [1st Chapter. On Tamil nouns] (U2, <locus facs="14">p. 10</locus>–<locus facs="18">p. 14</locus>).</item> 
</list>

 <p>Nouns are classified into five different declensions: the first one for nouns ending in <foreign xml:lang="ta">–am</foreign>; the second for masculine nouns ending in <foreign xml:lang="ta"> –an</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="ta">–en</foreign>; the third for nouns ending in <foreign xml:lang="ta">–ṭu</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="ta">–ṟu</foreign>; the fourth for non-masculine nouns ending in <foreign xml:lang="ta">ṉ, l, ḷ, r</foreign>; and the fifth for nouns ending in vowel with the exception of those already included in the third class.</p>

<list>
	<item><quote xml:lang="fr">Chapitre 2e. Des Pronoms</quote> [2nd Chapter. On pronouns] (U2, <locus facs="19">p. 15</locus>–<locus facs="22">p. 18</locus>).</item> 
</list>

 <p>It differentiates between personal, interrogative, demonstrative, and some other types of pronouns.</p>

<list>
  	<item><quote xml:lang="fr">Chapitre 3e. Des Numeraux</quote> [3rd Chapter. On numerals] (U2, <locus facs="22">p. 18</locus>–<locus facs="24">p. 20</locus>).</item>
	<item><emph rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Chapitre 4e. Des adverbes Tamouls</emph> [4th Chapter. On Tamil adverbs] (U2, <locus facs="25">p. 21</locus>).</item>
	<item><quote xml:lang="fr">Chapitre 5e. Des Verbes Tamouls</quote> [5th Chapter. On Tamil Verbs] (U2, <locus facs="25">p. 21</locus>–<locus facs="43">p. 39</locus>).</item>
</list>

<p>In the first paragraph (U2, <locus facs="26">p. 22</locus>–<locus facs="31">p. 27</locus>) the verb is conjugated into four modes (indicative, imperative, optative and subjunctive) and four tenses (present, imperfect preterite, perfect preterite, future). It also discusses conditional, infinitive, gerund, preterite verbal participle, and passive. The second paragraph (U2, <locus facs="32">p. 28</locus>–<locus facs="41">p. 37</locus>) groups verbs into seven classes, on the base of the formation of the past and future tenses. It further discusses impersonal and the verbal infinitive, as well as the defective verbs (U2, <locus facs="41">p. 37</locus>–<locus facs="43">p. 39</locus>).</p>

<p>The third and final section, <quote xml:lang="fr"><emph rend="bold">Troisième Partie</emph></quote> (U2, <locus facs="44">p. 40</locus>–<locus facs="56">p. 52</locus>) consists in only one chapter which focuses on syntax: <quote xml:lang="fr">Chapitre 1er. De quelques Regles de Concordance et de Syntaxe absolument necessaires pour entrer dans la Genie de la langue Tamoul</quote> [On a few rules about the concordance and the syntax, which are absolutely necessary for accessing the genius of the Tamil language].</p>

<p>Cabaton in his <title xml:lang="fr">Catalogue sommaire</title> (1912, <ref target="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10329763p/f49">p. 31</ref>) describes the manuscript as follows:
  
<quote xml:lang="fr" rend="block">Grammaire tamoule, par le P. de La Lave, S. J. 1728. Papier. 92 pages, 240 x 180 mm. (Ancien fonds, n° CCVII).<app><note xml:lang="en">A later hand corrected this information (the author's name and the number of pages, in blue ink.</note></app></quote>
  
Indeed, the manuscript is mentioned in the “ancient fonds” under n° CCVII (cf. <title xml:lang="la">Catalogus codicum manuscriptorum bibliothecae regiae. Tomus primus. Pars prima, complectens codices manuscriptos orientales</title>, 1739, <ref target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k140995x/f447">p. 444, no. CCVII</ref>), which states:
	<quote xml:lang="la" rend="block">Codex chartaceus. Ibi continetur liber Grammaticus inscriptus <hi rend="italic">Grammaire pour apprendre la language Tamoul</hi>, dite vulgairement <hi rend="italic">le Malabar</hi>, ou <hi rend="italic">la langue Malabare</hi>. Lingua est peninsulæ Indicæ à promontorio Comorino usque ad gradum latitudinis septentrionalis decimum quartum. Alia tamen in regno Maissour, sed parùm diversa, usurpatur. Hujusce operis auctor unus è Missionariis Gallis Societatis Jesu. Anno 1728.</quote></p>
  
<p>This grammar appears to be the work of Father Pierre de La Lane (1699-1746), who was posted in Tarkolam probably between 1705 and 1708, without remaining for a long time in India (Colas and Colas-Chauhan 1992; Colas and Colas-Chauhan 1995: 9). The of Father Pierre de La Lane also authored a Telugu Grammar in 1729, of very similar layout and structure. See <ref target="https://archivesetmanuscrits.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cc104160k">BnF Indien 634</ref>.</p>

<p>Like Cabaton, Vinson wrongly writes the name of Father La Lane as La Lave, in the proofreadings of his unpublished catalogue (1868, <ref target="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b105333021/f101">p. 46</ref>) and in his handwritten catalogue (BnF INDIEN 1062, <ref target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b105363346/f40">folio 66r</ref>), which states:
  
<quote xml:lang="fr" rend="block"> “Grammaire pour apprendre la langue tamoul, ditte vulgairement le Malabar”. à la fin: “faitte à Pondichéry et achevée le 18 novembre 1728, par un missionaire de la compagnie de Jésus de la mission du Carnat". Papier. Pet. In-4° – 92 p. – ancien fonds, n° CCVII. Une note d’Anquetil dit que l’auteur de cette grammaire est le père de la Lave.
</quote>

The note by Anquetil-Duperron, referred to above by Vinson, is found in the manuscript BnF Indien 219, <ref target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10029587q/f440">page 432, lines 1-3</ref>.  Anquetil-Duperron (1808, p. 669) mentions La Lane’s manuscript – along with others, such as the Tamil-Portuguese and the Portuguese-Tamil dictionaries, and Beschi’s Grammar, in his letter to Cœurdoux sent from Paris on the 28th July 1768.</p></summary>
                  
               <msItem synch="#U1" defective="false"><title xml:lang="fr">Title Page &amp; Preface</title><author xml:lang="fr">Father Pierre Lalane, Carnatic Mission</author><textLang mainLang="fra"/></msItem><msItem synch="#U2" defective="false"><title xml:lang="fr">Grammaire pour apprendre la langue Tamoul Ditte Vulgairement le Malabar.</title><author xml:lang="fr">Father Pierre Lalane, Carnatic Mission</author><textLang mainLang="fra" otherLangs="tam"/><colophon xml:lang="fr"><pb n="[52]" facs="56"/>

<lb n="26"/>Fin de la Grammaire.
<lb n="27"/>A la Plus Grande Gloire
<lb n="28"/>de Dieu.
  <lb n="29"/>Faite a <placeName xml:lang="fr" key="Pondicherry">Pontichery</placeName> et achevée le 18<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> 9<hi rend="superscript">bre</hi> 1728
  <lb n="30"/>Par un Missionaire de la Comp<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> de Jesus de la Mission du
  <lb n="31"/>Carnat</colophon></msItem></msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  
                  
                  
                  
                  
               <objectDesc form="codex" rend="manuscript">
                     <supportDesc material="paper laid">
                        
                        
                        
                        
                         <support>
                           <p>The type of paper is “laid” paper. It is thin, and the pulp touches the wires, making a latticework pattern easily seen when the leaf is held against a light. The paper has a watermark. See Muru (2019, <ref target="https://tst.hypotheses.org/560#identifier_0_560">fig. 6 </ref>). Unlike in this back guard leaf, it is found, throughout the manuscript, in the centre at the place of the binding.</p>
                        </support><extent>
                           <measure unit="page" quantity="54">{2} + 52 (U1 + U2).</measure>
                           <dimensions type="object" unit="mm"><width quantity="190"/><height quantity="250"/><depth quantity="15"/></dimensions><dimensions type="written" unit="mm"/><dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm"><width quantity="185"/><height quantity="245"/></dimensions></extent><foliation>Arabic pagination for U2, right or left upper side of each page, except page 52.</foliation><collation><desc xml:id="CoverFront">the <emph rend="bold">front cover</emph>.</desc><desc xml:id="U1">1 folio = 2 pages = <emph rend="bold">Title Page &amp; Preface</emph>. No pagination.</desc><desc xml:id="U2">26 folios = 52 pages = <emph rend="bold">Text</emph>. Pagination 1-51, <q><supplied reason="omitted">52</supplied></q>. 13 bifolios. No missing folios.</desc><desc xml:id="u1">1 folio = 2 pages = back <emph rend="bold">guard leaf</emph>. Blank recto verso.</desc><desc xml:id="CoverBack">the <emph rend="bold">back cover</emph>.</desc></collation><condition>Very good state of preservation and very legible.</condition></supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout writtenLines="36 43">Number of lines per folio/page: from a minimum of 13 text lines + 8 title lines per page (where titles written in different font sizes) up to 43 lines per page. The most recurrent number of lines per page/folio is 36/37. Only the first and the second chapters of the second section are layed-out into two columns marked in red ink. The formatting of the text reveals that the grammar was composed for the public rather than for personal use. In fact, the page layout delimits a writing surface between the right (25 mm), left (20 mm), upper (25 mm), and bottom margins (15 mm). Any mistake is corrected by posting a piece of paper bearing the correct version. Muru (2019, <ref target="https://tst.hypotheses.org/560#identifier_0_560">fig. 5</ref>).</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc><handDesc><handNote synch="#U1 #U2" scope="sole" script="latin tamil" scriptRef="#tamilPulliNone #tamilRa" medium="ink black red"><desc>Black ink for the main text, red ink for marking the layout of the page (margins), rows, and columns in the chart.</desc></handNote></handDesc><decoDesc>
                  <decoNote synch="#U2" type="table" subtype="intertextual"><desc>There are no illustrations, no diagrams, but different sizes for fonts for marking title, subtitles, paragraphs, beginning and ending of text. There is one chart for Tamil letters spread on several pages (<locus facs="6">p. 2</locus>, <locus facs="9">p. 5</locus>-<locus facs="12">p. 8</locus>).</desc></decoNote></decoDesc><additions>
                  <desc type="shelfmark" subtype="spine bottom">BnF current shelfmark sticker: <quote>INDIEN 189</quote> (<locus facs="1">spine</locus>).</desc><desc synch="#CoverFront" type="shelfmark" subtype="cover front top">Shelfmark incised on the leather cover: <quote>n. 207</quote> (<locus facs="1">front cover, recto</locus>).</desc><desc synch="#CoverFront" type="title" subtype="cover front">Shelfmark written in black ink on the leather cover (<locus facs="1">front cover, recto</locus>): 
<quote xml:lang="fr" rend="block">
  <lb n="1"/>Grammaire
<lb n="2"/>Tamoul.
</quote></desc><desc synch="#CoverFront" type="shelfmark" subtype="cover front">BnF current shelfmark sticker: <quote>INDIEN 189</quote> (<locus facs="2">front cover, verso</locus>).</desc></additions><bindingDesc>
                     <binding><p>The volume is made of 3 quires: the first is a quinternion (V), the second and the third are quaternion (IV): 1 V (ff. 20) + 2 IV (ff. 16). The stiff covers (boards) at the front and back of the book are attached to the quires by the cords which are secured by means of channelling. Damp leather, which is folded over the edges of the boards forming a turn-ins and glued down, covers the boards and the spine. Pastedowns of the initial and final bifolio onto the inside of the board conceal this configuration (binding and channelling).</p><decoNote type="stringhole"><measure unit="stringhole" quantity="4"/></decoNote></binding>
                  </bindingDesc></physDesc>
               <history>
                  
                  
                  
               <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="gregorian" when="1728">The copying of the grammar was completed on the 18th November 1728 in Pondicherry. See colophon (U2, <locus facs="56">p. [52]</locus>.</origDate>
                     <origPlace>South India, Pondicherry.</origPlace>
                  </origin><provenance><p>Autograph manuscript by Father Pierre de La Lane (1699-1746), copied in 1728 in Pondicherry.</p></provenance><acquisition><p>This is the <ref target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b105278700/f17">grammaire en Tamoul</ref> and the <ref target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b105278700/f31">grammaire Tamoul</ref> sent by the Jesuits of the Mission du Carnate in 1729 for the library of the king of France and mentioned in ancien lists (BnF NAF 5442, f5r and f9r).
It appears in the list provided in Omont (1902, p. 1188). ― The stamp on the first and on the last page of the document (see Josserand and Bruno, 1960) seems to suggest that the manuscript entered in the Library not earlier than July 1830 or January 1831.</p></acquisition></history>
               <additional>
                  <listBibl>
                     
                  <bibl>Anquetil-Duperron. 1808. <title xml:lang="fr">Supplément au Mémoire qui précède</title>. In <title xml:lang="fr">Mémoire de littérature, tirés des registres de l’Académie Royale des inscriptions et belles-Lettres, depuis l’année M.DCCLXXXIV, jusques et compris l’année M.DCCXCIII</title>. Tome Quarante-Neuvième, pp. 647-712. Paris: De L’imprimerie impériale. M.DCCCVIII.</bibl><bibl>Cabaton, Antoine. 1912. <title>Catalogue sommaire des manuscrits indiens, indo-chinois &amp; malayo-polynésiens. Bibliothèque nationale. Département des manuscrits</title>. Paris: E. Leroux. — See <ref target="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10329763p/f49">p. 31, no. 189</ref>.
</bibl><bibl><title xml:lang="fr" type="article">Catalogue des mss. indiens de la Bibliothèque du Roi.</title> Manuscript BnF NAF 5441. — See f327r, f352r, f353r.</bibl><bibl><title xml:lang="fr" type="article">Catalogue général des livres qui ont été envoyez de Chandernagor dans le Royaume de Bengale pour la Bibliothèque du Roi.</title> 14 f. [Envoi des jésuites, 1729–1735]. Manuscript BnF NAF 5442. — See f9r.</bibl><bibl>Colas, G. and Colas-Chauhan, U. 1992. <title type="article">Five dictionaries in the Telugu manuscript collection of the Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris</title>. <title>The Journal of Oriental Research, Madras</title> LVI-LXII: 379-392. </bibl><bibl>Colas, G. and Colas-Chauhan, U. 1995. <title>Manuscrits telugu. Catalogue raisonné</title>. Paris: Bibliothèque Nationale de France. </bibl><bibl>Josserand, Pierre and et Jean Bruno. 1906., <title xml:lang="fr" type="article">Les estampilles du Département des imprimés de la Bibliothèque nationale</title>, in <title xml:lang="fr">Mélanges d'histoire du livre et des bibliothèques offerts à Monsieur Frantz Calot</title>, p. 261-298. Paris, Librairie d’Argences.</bibl><bibl>Muru, Cristina. 2019-10-31. <title type="article">BnF INDIEN 189: Grammar of Tamil by P. de La Lane</title>. Blogpost. <ref target="https://tst.hypotheses.org/560#identifier_0_560">https://tst.hypotheses.org/560#identifier_0_560</ref>.
</bibl><bibl>Omont, Henri. 1902. <title xml:lang="fr" type="article">XXIX Liste de manuscrits envoyés de l’Inde par les Jésuites (1729-1735).</title> In: <title xml:lang="fr">Missions archéologiques françaises en Orient aux XVIIe et XVIIIe siècles. Seconde partie.</title> Paris: Imprimerie nationale. — See p. 840 and p. 1188.</bibl><bibl>S.n. 1739. <title>Catalogus codicum manuscriptorum Bibliothecae regiae. Tomus primus. Pars prima, complectens codices manuscriptos orientales.</title> Paris: Typographia Regia. — See <ref target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k140995x/f447">p. 444, no. CCVII</ref>.</bibl><bibl>Vinson, Julien &amp; Feer, Léon &amp; s.n. 1866-. <title>Catalogue des manuscrits tamoul et télinga</title>. Manuscript, BnF Indien 577. — See <ref target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b105375868/f107">f. 46r, no. 189</ref>. </bibl><bibl>Vinson, Julien. 1868. <title>Manuscrits tamouls</title>. Proofreadings of the catalogue for Tamoul 1-204 (old shelfmark). Printed by the atelier oriental de l’Imprimerie nationale. BnF “4-IMPROR-77 (B)”. — The same proofreadings with black ink handwritten corrections are found in Vinson et al. (1866-, f1-f49). — See <ref target="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b105333021/f101">p. 46, no. 189</ref>. </bibl></listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   <revisionDesc>
         
      <change when="2019-10">This catalogue entry has been redacted by <persName xml:id="cMURU">Cristina Muru</persName> (DISTU, University of Tuscia) for the research program <ref target="https://tst.hypotheses.org/88">Text Surrounding Texts</ref> (TST, FRAL 2018, ANR/DFG). Version 1, October 2019.</change><change when="2022-05">Revised by <persName>Emmanuel FRANCIS</persName>. Version 2, May 2022.</change><change when="2023-04">Revised and enlarged by <persName>Emmanuel FRANCIS</persName>. Version 3, April 2023.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
   <graphic url="https://gallica.bnf.fr/iiif/ark:/12148/btv1b531609463/manifest.json"/></facsimile>
</TEI>