<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tei-to-html.xsl" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><emph rend="bold">Grammaire Tamoul.</emph> <emph rend="italic">Grammaire pour apprendre la langue Tamoul Ditte Vulgaireiment le Malabar</emph></title>
            
         <editor><persName>Cristina Muru</persName><orgName>University of Tuscia</orgName></editor></titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TST Project</publisher>
            <date>2021</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>
                     <orgName>Bibliothèque nationale de France. Département des Manuscrits</orgName>
                  </repository>
                  <idno type="URI">https://archivesetmanuscrits.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cc103708d</idno>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Indien 189</idno>
                  <idno type="alternate"><idno>Tamoul 189</idno></idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#STM">
                  <summary><p>BnF INDIEN 189 (ex- Tamoul 189) consists in 28 paper leaves bound in one volume (260 x 200 mm). An unfoliated folio comes first, bearing the title-page on the recto and a preface (“Préface”) on the verso, p. <locus facs="4">2</locus>. 26 folios follow, all paginated except for p. <locus facs="56">52</locus>. The original pagination appears on the upper left corner of the page on the verso of folio and on the upper right corner on the recto. Finally, there is a back guard leaf. </p>
<p>This manuscript is a grammar of Tamil written in French organized into three sections,  each one with a different number of chapters. The first section includes 2 chapters, the second section includes 5 chapters, and the third section is made of 1 chapter.</p>
<p>The first section, <emph rend="bold" xml:lang="fr">Premiere Partie. Des Lettres de l’Alphabet Tamoul</emph> [First part. On the letters of the Tamil Alphabet] (pp. <locus facs="5">1</locus>–<locus facs="13">9</locus>) includes 2 chapters, which describe Tamil vowels and consonants, while a short preface (p. <locus facs="4">2</locus>), describing the extension of the geographical area where the Tamil language is spoken, precedes it on the verso of the front unfoliated folio:</p> 
<list>
	<item><emph rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Chapitre 1er Des Voyelles des Tamouls</emph> [1st Chapter 1st. On the vowels of the Tamils], p. <locus facs="6">2</locus>.</item>
	<item><emph rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Chapitre 2e Des Consonnes des Tamouls</emph> [2nd Chapter 2nd. On the consonants of the Tamils], pp. <locus facs="6">2</locus>-<locus facs="13">9</locus>.</item>
</list>
<p>The second section (pp. <locus facs="13">9</locus>–<locus facs="43">39</locus>) is divided into five chapters:</p>
<list>
	<item><emph rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Chapitre 1er Des Noms Tamouls</emph> [1st Chapter. On Tamil nouns], pp. <locus facs="13">9</locus>–<locus facs="18">14</locus>.</item> 
</list>
 <p>Nouns are classified into five different declensions: the first one for nouns ending in <foreign xml:lang="ta">–am</foreign>; the second for masculine nouns ending in <foreign xml:lang="ta"> –an</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="ta">–en</foreign>; the third for nouns ending in <foreign xml:lang="ta">–ṭu</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="ta">–ṟu</foreign>; the fourth for non-masculine nouns ending in <foreign xml:lang="ta">ṉ, l, ḷ, r</foreign>; and the fifth for nouns ending in vowel with the exception of those already included in the third class.</p>
<list>
	<item><emph rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Chapitre 2e. Des Pronoms</emph> [2nd Chapter. On pronouns], pp. <locus facs="19">15</locus>–<locus facs="22">18</locus>.</item> 
</list>
 <p>It differentiates between personal, interrogative, demonstrative, and some other types of pronouns.</p>
<list>
  	<item><emph rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Chapitre 3e. Des Numeraux</emph> [3rd Chapter. On numerals], pp. <locus facs="22">18</locus>–<locus facs="24">20</locus>.</item>
	<item><emph rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Chapitre 4e. Des adverbes Tamouls</emph> [4th Chapter. On Tamil adverbs], p. <locus facs="25">21</locus>.</item>
	<item><emph rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Chapitre 5e. Des Verbes Tamouls</emph> [5th Chapter. On Tamil Verbs], pp. <locus facs="25">21</locus>–<locus facs="43">39</locus>.</item>
</list>
<p>In the first paragraph (pp. <locus facs="26">22</locus>–<locus facs="31">27</locus>) the verb is conjugated into four modes (<emph rend="italic">Indicative, Imperative, Optative,</emph> and <emph rend="italic">Subjunctive</emph>) and four tenses (<emph rend="italic">present, imperfect preterite, perfect preterite, future</emph>). It also discusses conditional, infinitive, gerund, preterite verbal participle, and passive. The second paragraph (pp. <locus facs="32">28</locus>–<locus facs="41">37</locus>) groups verbs into seven classes, on the base of the formation of the past and future tenses. It further discusses impersonal and the verbal infinitive, as well as the defective verbs.(pp. <locus facs="41">37</locus>–<locus facs="43">39</locus>)</p>
<p>The third and final section (pp. <locus facs="44">40</locus>–<locus facs="56">52</locus>) consists in only one chapter which focuses on syntax: <emph rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Chapitre 1er. De quelques Regles de Concordance et de syntaxe absolument necessaires pour entrer dans la Genie de la langue Tamoul</emph> [On a few rules about the concordance and the syntax which are absolutely necessary for entering in the genius of the Tamil language]. </p></summary>
                  
               <msItem xml:id="T1" defective="false"><title xml:lang="fr">o  <emph rend="bold">Grammaire pour apprendre la langue Tamoul Ditte Vulgairement le Malabar. </emph></title><author xml:lang="en">Father Lalane Pierre, Carnatic Mission</author><textLang mainLang="fra" otherLangs="tam"/><filiation><p>Cabaton in his <emph rend="italic">Catalogue sommaire</emph> (1912, p. 31) describes the manuscript as follows:
<list>
	<item>Grammaire tamoule, par le P. de La Lave, S. J. 1728. Papier. 92 pages, 240 x 180 mm. (Ancien fonds, n° CCVII).</item>
</list>
 Indeed, the manuscript is mentioned in the “ancient fonds” under n° CCVII (cf. <emph rend="italic">Catalogus codicum manuscriptorum bibliothecae regiae. Tomus primus. Pars prima, complectens codices manuscriptos orientales</emph>, 1739, p. 444):
<list>
	<item><emph rend="italic">Codex chartaceus. Ibi coninetur liber Grammaticus inscriptus Grammaire pour apprendre la language Tamoul, dite vulgairement le Malabar, ou la langue Malabare. Lingua est peninsulæ Indicæ à promontorio Comorino usque ad gradum latitudinis septentrionalis decimum quartum. Alia tamen in regno Maissour, sed parùm diversa, usurpatur. Hujusce operis auctor unus è Missionariis Gallis Societatis Jesu. Anno 1728.</emph></item>
</list>
Like Cabaton, Vinson wrongly writes, in the proofreadings of his unpublished catalogue, the name of Father La Lane as La Lave (1867, p. 46). Vinson was however aware of the correct name of the author, as attested in his handwritten catalogue (BnF INDIEN 1062, <locus>folio 66r</locus>):
<list>
	<item><emph rend="italic">"Grammaire pour apprendre la langue tamoul, ditte vulgairement le Malabar”. A la fin: “Faitte à Pondichéry et achevée le 18 novembre 1728, par un missionaire de la Compagnie de Jésus de la mission du Carnat".
Une note d’Anquetil dit que l’auteur de cette grammaire est le Père de La Lave.
Papier. Pet. In-4° – 92 pages – (Ancien fonds, n° CCVII.).</emph> This note, to which Vinson refers to is found in the manuscript BnF INDIEN 192, <locus>folio 143v</locus>.</item>
</list></p></filiation><colophon xml:lang="fr"><milestone n="52" unit="page" facs="56"/>Fin de la Grammaire - A la Plus Grande Gloire de Dieu. Faite a Pondichery et achevèe le 18es 9bre 1728 Par un Missionaire de la Comp.e de Jesus de la Mission du Carnat</colophon></msItem></msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="paper laid">
                        <support>
                           <measure unit="stringhole"/>
                           <p>The type of paper is “laid” paper. It is thin, and the pulp touches the wires, making a latticework pattern easily seen when the leaf is held against a light. The paper has a watermark (cf. fig. 6 in <ref target="https://tst.hypotheses.org/560#identifier_0_560">Blogpost TST</ref>). Unlike in this back guard leaf, it is found, throughout the manuscript, in the centre at the place of the binding.</p>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure unit="page" quantity="52">13 bifolios. 
No missing folios.</measure>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              
                              
                           </dimensions>
                        <dimensions type="object" unit="mm"><width quantity="200"/><height quantity="260"/></dimensions><dimensions type="written" unit="mm"/></extent>
                        <collation><desc xml:id="U1">Number of lines per folio/page: from a minimum of 13 text lines + 8 title lines per page (where titles written in different font sizes) up to 43 lines per page. 
The most recurrent number of lines per page/folio: 36/37.</desc></collation>
                        
                        
                     <foliation>Arabic numerals, right and left upper side of each page</foliation><condition>Very good state of preservation and very legible.</condition></supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="43">only for the first and the second chapters of the second section that are layed-out into two columns marked in red ink. The formatting of the text reveals that the grammar was composed for a public rather than personal use. In fact, the page layout delimits a writing surface between the right (25 mm), left (20 mm), upper (25 mm), and bottom margins (15 mm). Any mistake is corrected by posting a piece of paper bearing the correct version (cf. Image n. 5 in <ref target="https://tst.hypotheses.org/560#identifier_0_560">Blogpost TST</ref>).
</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc><handNote synch="#U1" scope="sole" script="latin tamil" scriptRef="#tamilPulliNone #tamilRa" medium="ink black red"><desc>Black ink for the main text, red ink for marking the layout of the page (margins), rows, and columns in the chart.</desc></handNote></handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                  <decoNote synch="#U1" type="table" subtype="intertextual"><desc>no pictures, no diagrams, but different sizes for fonts for marking title, subtitles, paragraphs, beginning and ending of text/ms. 
One chart for Tamil letters, pp. <locus facs="6">2</locus>, <locus facs="9">5</locus>-<locus facs="12">8</locus>.</desc></decoNote></decoDesc>
                  <additions>
                  </additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding><p>3 quires of which, the first quire is a quinternion (V), the second and the third quires are quaternion (IV):
1 V (ff. 20) + 2 IV (ff. 16). The stiff covers (boards) at the front and back of the book are attached to the quires by the cords which are secured by means of channelling. Damp leather, which is folded over the edges of the boards forming a turn-ins and glued down, covers the boards and the spine. Pastedowns of the initial and final bifolio onto the inside of the board conceal this mechanism (binding and channelling). Not numbered guard leaves. On the recto of the first guard leaf, the title of the Grammar appears, while on the verso there is the Preface.</p></binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="gregorian" when="1728">The grammar was ended on the 18th November 1728 in Pondicherry.</origDate>
                     <origPlace>South India, Tamilnadu, Pondicherry</origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance><p>The manuscript was sent in 1729 to the <emph rend="italic">Bibliothèque du Roy</emph> from the Jesuit Fathers of the Carnatic mission. It appears in the list provided in H. Omont (1902), <emph rend="italic">Missions archéologiques françaises en Orient aux XVIIe et XVIIIe siècles. Partie 2</emph>, p. 1188. </p></provenance>
                  <acquisition><p>The stamp on the first and on the last page of the document seems to suggest that the manuscript entered in the Library not earlier than July 1830 or January 1831 (cfr. Pierre Josserand et Jean Bruno, « Les estampilles du Département des imprimés de la Bibliothèque nationale », dans <emph rend="italic">Mélanges d'histoire du livre et des bibliothèques offerts à Monsieur Frantz Calot</emph>, Paris, Librairie d’Argences 1960, p. 261-298.)</p></acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <listBibl>
                     
                  <bibl>Sn. CCMBR=Catalogus Codicum Manuscriptorum Bibliothecæ Regiæ. Tomus Primus. (1739). Parisiis, e Typographia Regia. p. 444.</bibl><bibl>Cabaton, Antoine (1912). <title xml:lang="fr">Catalogue sommaire des manuscrits indiens, indo-chinois and malayo-polynésiens.</title> Bibliothèque nationale. Département des manuscrits. Paris: E. Leroux. — See p. 31. </bibl><bibl><title xml:lang="fr" type="article">Catalogue des mss. indiens de la Bibliothèque du Roi.</title> (NAF 5441, f. 327r; ff. 352r; 353r).</bibl><bibl><title xml:lang="fr" type="article">Catalogue général des livres qui ont été envoyez de Chandernagor dans le Royaume de Bengale pour la Bibliothèque du Roi.</title> 14 f. [Envoi des jésuites, 1729–1735]. (NAF 5442, f. 9r)</bibl><bibl>Omont, Henri (1902). <title xml:lang="fr" type="article">XXIX Liste de manuscrits envoyés de l’Inde par les Jésuites (1729-1735).</title> In: <title xml:lang="fr">Missions archéologiques françaises en Orient aux XVIIe et XVIIIe siècles. Seconde partie.</title> Paris: Imprimerie nationale. p. 840 and p. 1188</bibl><bibl>Muru, Cristina (2019). INDIEN 189 BnF. Blogpost <ref target="https://tst.hypotheses.org/560#identifier_0_560">tst.hypotheses.org</ref></bibl><bibl>Vinson, Julien (1867‒1868). <title xml:lang="fr">Catalogue des manuscrits tamouls.</title> Corrected proofreadings printed by the atelier oriental de l’Imprimerie nationale. Access No. 4-IMPROR-77 (B). — See p. 46.</bibl></listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         
      <change when="2019-10">This catalogue entry has been redacted by <persName xml:id="cMURU">Cristina Muru</persName> (DISTU, University of Tuscia) for the research program <ref target="https://tst.hypotheses.org/88">Text Surrounding Texts</ref> (TST, FRAL 2018, ANR/DFG). Version 1, October 2019.</change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
   <graphic url="https://gallica.bnf.fr/iiif/ark:/12148/btv1b531609463/manifest.json"/></facsimile>
</TEI>
