<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tei-to-html.xsl" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Indian Syllabaries</title>
            
         <editor><persName>Emmanuel FRANCIS</persName><orgName>CNRS, CEIAS UMR 8564, EHESS/CNRS</orgName></editor></titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TST Project</publisher>
            <date>2022</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>
                     <orgName>Bibliothèque nationale de France. Département des Manuscrits</orgName>
                  </repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Indien 858</idno>
                  <idno type="alternate"><idno>Indien 219</idno></idno>
               <idno type="URI">https://archivesetmanuscrits.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cc104890r</idno><idno type="URI">https://didomena.ehess.fr/concern/data_sets/5138jp12b</idno></msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#CM">
                  <summary><p>Various Indic Syllabaries (Devanāgarī, Grantha, Tamoul, Telugu, Tibetan) collected in one bound volume.</p>
<p>18 folios or bifolios of various measurements hinged on tabs, with Arabic library foliation 1–5 and 7–23 (bifolios bear several foliations; folio 6 not foliated), which makes 23 folios, numbered in upper right corner in black pencil (U1). The folios are hinged (<term xml:lang="fr">montés sur onglet</term>), except f1, which is pasted on the page.</p>
<p>The volume contains, besides the cover and U1, 2 front guard leaves and 2 back guard leaves.</p>
<p>The volume contains 16 items, which are various Indic syllabaries:
<list>

  <item><emph rend="bold">Item 1 = Devanāgarī syllabary (<locus facs="3">f1r</locus>)</emph>, with transcription and French annotation. 1 folio pasted on the volume page = library foliation 1. Incomplete. A series of consonants with <foreign>a</foreign> vocalisation only.  With Roman transcription of each character.  With an annotation, bottom, upside down: <quote xml:lang="fr">Dhatu-pratyaya-pandjica par Dharmakirtti</quote> [i.e. Dhātu-pratyaya-pañcikā by Dharmakīrti].</item>
 
  <item><emph rend="bold">Item 2 = 2 Devanāgarī syllabaries (<locus facs="5">f2rv</locus>)</emph>. 1 folio hinged on a tab = library foliation 2. One syllabary on recto, the other on verso. f2r: numerals; vowels, initial and medial; consonants series with <foreign>a</foreign> vocalisation; conjunct letters, with some corrections in the left margin. f2v: vowels, initial and medial; consonants series with <foreign>a</foreign> vocalisation; selection of consonants with <foreign>u</foreign> vocalisation; conjunct letters.</item>
 
  <item><emph rend="bold">Item 3 = Devanāgarī syllabary (<locus facs="7">f3r</locus>)</emph>, with transcription. 1 folio hinged on a tab = library foliation 3. Selection of consonants and conjunct letters with various vocalisations. With Roman transcription of each character. </item>
 
  <item><emph rend="bold">Item 4 = Devanāgarī syllabary (<locus facs="8">f4r</locus>)</emph>, with transcription and French and Latin annotation. 1 folio hinged on a tab = library foliation 4. Consonants series with <foreign>a</foreign> vocalisation; initial vowels; selection of 4 letters, with the various possible vocalisations.</item>
 
  <item><emph rend="bold">Item 5 = Devanāgarī, Grantha and Telugu joint syllabary (<locus facs="11">f5r</locus>)</emph>, with transcription and French annotation. 1 folio, folded and hinged on a tab = library foliation 5. In the form of tables. For more details, see Colas and Colas-Chauhan (1995, p. 74, n° III), who suggest that the manuscript was sent from Pondicherry by Signard in 1729.</item>
   
  <item><emph rend="bold">Item 6 = selection of Grantha letters, Tamil numerals, and Tamil symbols for date elements (<locus facs="17">f7r</locus>)</emph>. 1 bifolio hinged on a tab like a 4-page quire = library foliation 7 only (on page [3]). With a French annotation: <quote xml:lang="fr">Caractères qui servent de chiffres.</quote></item>
  
  <item><emph rend="bold">Item 7 = Tamil syllabary (<locus facs="19">f8r</locus>)</emph>, with Latin annotation. 1 folio, folded and hinged on a tab = library foliation 8. In the form of a table.</item>
  
  <item><emph rend="bold">Item 8 = Tamil syllabary (<locus facs="24">f9</locus>)</emph>, with partial transcription and French annotation.  1 bifolio hinged on a tab like a 4-page quire = library foliation 9. In the form of tables. “Voyelles initiales” (p. [1]), that is, initial vowels, and consonants (pp. [2]‒[3]).</item>
  
 <item><emph rend="bold">Item 9 = "Arrangement des Dictionnaires Tamouls" (<locus facs="27">f10</locus>)</emph>. 1 bifolio hinged on a tab like a 4-page quire = library foliation 10. Notes in French about the alphabetic ordering in a Tamil Portuguese dictionary, that is, an attempt is made to adopt an order which is in agreement with that of the Latin aphabet.</item>
  
 <item><emph rend="bold">Item 10 = Tamil syllabary (<locus facs="30">f11r</locus>)</emph>, with Latin annotation. 1 folio hinged on a tab = library foliation 11.</item>
  
 <item><emph rend="bold">Item 11 = Tamil syllabary (<locus facs="32">f12rv</locus>)</emph>.  1 folio hinged on a tab = library foliation 12. Initial vowels series; full consonant series with <foreign>a</foreign> vocalisation; individual consonant series with various possible vocalisations.</item>
  
 <item><emph rend="bold">Item 12 = Tamil syllabary (<locus facs="34">f13</locus>) and Telugu syllabary (<locus facs="39">f14–f16</locus>)</emph>, with transcription (only for Telugu) and French annotations. 2 bifolios hinged on a tab, each like a 4-page quire = library foliation 13–16. In the form of tables. For more details, see Colas &amp; Colas-Chauhan (1995, p. 74–75, n° IX), who state that this was sent from Pondicherry by the Jesuits and identify the hand of Le Gac in one annotation.</item>
  
 <item><emph rend="bold">Item 13 = Marāṭhī, Grantha, Telugu and Nāgarī joint syllabary (<locus facs="47">f17rv</locus>)</emph>, with transcription and French annotation. 1 folio hinged on a tab = library foliation 17. In the form of a table. Incomplete: only the column for Telugu is filled-in (initial vowels [f17v] and first consonants [f17r]; thus verso in the volume is in fact the original recto, and vice versa). For more details, see Colas and Colas-Chauhan (1995, p. 75–76, n° X).</item>
  
 <item><emph rend="bold">Item 14 = Telugu syllabary (<locus facs="49">f18rv</locus>)</emph>, with transcription and French annotation. 1 folio and hinged on a tab = library foliation 18. For more details, see Colas and Colas-Chauhan (1995, p. 76, n° XI), who state that this was sent from Pondicherry by the Jesuits and copied by Father Gargam (18th c.).</item>
  
 <item><emph rend="bold">Item 15 = Telugu syllabary (<locus facs="51">f19r–f22r</locus>)</emph>, with transcription and French annotation. 2 bifolios hinged on tabs; library foliation 19‒22. Initial vowels (f19r), consonant series with <foreign>a</foreign> vocalisation (f19r), medial vowels system (f19v), consonants' forms in conjunct letters (f20rv), various conjunct letters (f21rv–f22r). For more details, see Colas and Colas-Chauhan (1995, p. 77–75, n° XII).</item>
  
 <item><emph rend="bold">Item 16 = Tibetan syllabary (<locus facs="60">f23r</locus>)</emph>, by Des Hautesrayes (?) with notes in French. 1 folio hinged on a tab = library foliation 23. 1 full page very neatly written, as if for a printed book.</item>
  </list>
</p>

<p>The volume is described in Colas and Colas-Chauhan (1995, pp. 74–77), with further details about the Telugu syllabaries.</p>

<p>Description based on the examination of the original manuscript (October 2019).</p>
<p>Dimensions assessed at the time of examination.</p></summary>
                  
               <msItem synch="#U1" xml:id="T1" defective="false"><title xml:lang="ta"><term xml:lang="en">Indian Syllabaries</term></title><textLang mainLang="tam"/></msItem></msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  
                  
                  
                  
                  
               <objectDesc form="codex" rend="manuscript">
                     <supportDesc material="paper">
                        <support>
                           
                           
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure unit="folio" quantity="23">23 (U1).</measure>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              
                              
                           </dimensions>
                        <dimensions type="object" unit="mm"><width quantity="250"/><height quantity="350"/><depth quantity="5"/></dimensions><dimensions type="written" unit="mm"/></extent>
                        
                        
                        
                     <collation><desc xml:id="U1">23 folios = <emph rend="bold">Indian Syllabaries</emph>. Library Arabic foliation 1-5, {6}, 7-23. f3v, f4v, f7v, f11v, f22r, f23v blank.</desc></collation><condition>Very good state of preservation.</condition></supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        
                     <layout columns="1"/></layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc><handDesc/><decoDesc>
                  </decoDesc><additions>
                  <desc type="title" subtype="cover spine">Title printed on the <locus facs="2">spine</locus>:
<quote xml:lang="fr" rend="block">
<lb n="1"/>DIVERS ALPHABETS: INDIEN, DEVANAGARI, GRANTHAM, TAMOUL, TELINGA, TIBÉTAIN.
</quote></desc></additions><bindingDesc>
                     <binding><decoNote type="stringhole"><measure unit="stringhole"/></decoNote><p>Hard paper cover, marbled.</p></binding>
                  </bindingDesc></physDesc>
               <history>
                  
                  
                  
                  
                  
                  
               <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1800">Dated to 18th c. by Cabaton (1912, p. 130). Confirmed by Colas and Colas-Chauhan (1995, p. 74ff.) for several of the documents in the volume.</origDate>                     
                  
                  <origPlace>India.</origPlace></origin><provenance>
                     
                  <p>Unknown.</p></provenance><acquisition>
                     
                  <p>Unknown.</p></acquisition></history>
               <additional>
                  <listBibl>
                     
                  <bibl>Cabaton, Antoine. 1912. <title>Catalogue sommaire des manuscrits indiens, indo-chinois &amp; malayo-polynésiens</title>. Bibliothèque nationale. Département des manuscrits. Paris: E. Leroux. — See <ref target="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10329763p/f149">p. 130, no. 858</ref>.</bibl><bibl>Colas, Gérard and Usha Colas-Chauhan. 1995. <title>Manuscrits Telugu. Catalogue raisonné</title>. Paris: Bibliothèque nationale de France. — See <ref target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k2557038/f73">p. 39ff., no. 39</ref>.</bibl></listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         
      <p><emph rend="bold">General</emph> ― Unmarked length of <foreign>ō</foreign> and <foreign>ē</foreign> supplied. Unmarked <foreign>puḷḷi</foreign> supplied. Conjectural reading (text unclear) between parentheses. Supplied reading (text lost) between square brackets. Alternative readings separated by slash. <emph rend="bold">In transliteration</emph> ― Unmarked elided overshort <foreign>u</foreign> supplied as an apostrophe. Uppercase for initial vowels. Symbols between curly brackets. <emph rend="bold">Abbreviations</emph> ― c = column; f = folio; lf = library foliation; lm = left margin; r = recto; rm = right margin; u / U followed by a number = unit (codicological and/or textual); v = verso.            </p></encodingDesc>
      
   <revisionDesc>
         
      <change when="2020-05">This catalogue entry has been redacted by Emmanuel FRANCIS (CNRS, CEIAS UMR 8564, EHESS/CNRS) for the research program Texts Surrounding Texts (TST, FRAL 2018, ANR/DFG). Version 1, May 2020.</change><change when="2022-07">Revised by <persName>Emmanuel FRANCIS</persName>. Version 2, July 2022.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
   <graphic url="https://didomena.ehess.fr/concern/data_sets/5138jp12b/manifest.json"/></facsimile>
<text synch="#U1" corresp="#T1" xml:lang="ta"><body>
  <ab>
    
    <pb facs="3" n="1r"/><note xml:lang="en">Item no. 1</note>
    
    <pb facs="5" n="2r"/><note xml:lang="en">Item no. 2</note>
    
    <pb facs="7" n="3r"/><note xml:lang="en">Item no. 3</note>
    
    <pb facs="8" n="4r"/><note xml:lang="en">Item no. 4</note>
    <lb n="1"/>Alphabet Nagrou/Nagri dont les caractères répondent <unclear>sous</unclear> le même son que ceux du Telougou
    <lb n="1-4"/>Je ferai en sorte (d’y) avoir <gap reason="illegible"/> mieux expliqué les plus gros caractères pour l’année prochaine.
            
    <pb facs="11" n="5r"/><note xml:lang="en">Item no. 5</note>
    <lb n="1-3"/>Cette table contient 3 alphabets. Dans les 1eres lignes sont les caracteres marates ou Guzurates; dans les 2es ceux du grandam; et les troisièmes contiennent l’alphabet Telongou. La grammaire Telongou apprendra la manière de prononcer ces lettres <note xml:lang="en">compare with item 13</note>
      
    <pb facs="16" n="6r"/><app><note xml:lang="en">blank page</note></app>
    
    <pb facs="17" n="7r"/><note xml:lang="en">Item no. 6</note>
    
    <pb facs="19" n="8r"/><note xml:lang="en">Item no. 7</note>
    <lb n="1-3"/>Modus quo vocales scribuntur cum consonantibus ad faciendas syllabas. Omnes consonantes pronuntiantur cum a brevi, et sic quand nullum apponitur signum, nec consona est quiescens, pronuntiatur semper cum <gap reason="illegible"/>
    <lb n="1"/><note xml:lang="en">bottom</note> <del>22 Se</del> 21 Septbre 1666    
                
    <pb facs="24" n="9r"/><note xml:lang="en">Item no. 8</note>
    
    <pb facs="27" n="10r"/><note xml:lang="en">Item no. 9</note>
    <lb n="1"/>Arrangement des dictionnaires tamouls.
    <lb n="2-4"/>On a tâché dans le Dictionnaire Tamoul portuguais de garder autant qu'il a été possible l'ordre de nos dictionnaires alphabétiques. Ainsi il commence par
    <lb n="5"/>A அ 
    <lb n="6"/>B. ப. Ch. ச. <gap reason="ellipsis"/>
    
    <pb facs="30" n="11r"/><note xml:lang="en">Item no. 10</note>
    <lb n="1-2"/>Forma Caracterum Tamulensium.
    <lb n="3ff."/>quos ita in sex classes distinctos scripsi: ut qui in 1â <note xml:lang="en">that is, prima</note> classe sunt <gap reason="ellipsis"/>
    
    <pb facs="32" n="12r"/><note xml:lang="en">Item no. 11</note>
    
    <pb facs="34" n="13r"/><note xml:lang="en">Item no. 12</note>
    <pb facs="36" n="13v"/>
    <pb facs="39" n="14r"/>
    <pb facs="40" n="14v"/>
    <pb facs="41" n="15r"/>
    <pb facs="42" n="15v"/>
    <pb facs="43" n="16r"/>
    <pb facs="44" n="16v"/>
    <pb facs="46" n="17r"/>
    
    <pb facs="47" n="17v"/><note xml:lang="en">Item no. 13</note>
      <lb n="1-4"/>Cette Table contient 4 Alphabets. Dans la première colonne sont les caractères Marates ou Guzurates; dans la 2de ceux du Grandan; La 3ème colonne contient l'alphabet Telongou. Enfin dans la 4e sont les caractères Nagrou, ou Nagri. <note xml:lang="en">compare with item 5</note>
                            
    <pb facs="49" n="18r"/><note xml:lang="en">Item no. 14</note>
   <lb n="-1"/><note xml:lang="en">bottom</note> Alphabeth Telongou. 
    <pb facs="50" n="18v"/>
            
    <pb facs="51" n="19r"/><note xml:lang="en">Item no. 15</note>
   <lb n="1"/>Alphabet Talinga.
    <pb facs="52" n="19v"/>
             
    <pb facs="54" n="20r"/>
    <pb facs="55" n="20v"/>
    <pb facs="56" n="21r"/>
    <pb facs="57" n="21v"/>
    <pb facs="59" n="22r"/>
    <pb facs="58" n="22v"/>
    
    <pb facs="60" n="23r"/><note xml:lang="en">Item no. 16</note>
    <lb n="1-2"/>Alphabet de la Langue Scavante des Lamas du Thibet ou Boutan.
    <lb n="-1"/><note xml:lang="en">bottom, left</note> <persName xml:lang="fr">Des Hautesrayes</persName> del.
    
    </ab>
  </body></text></TEI>