<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tei-to-html.xsl" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Pondicherry Copper Plate</title>
            
         <editor><persName>Emmanuel FRANCIS</persName><orgName>CNRS, CEIAS UMR 8564, EHESS/CNRS</orgName></editor></titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TST Project</publisher>
            <date>2022</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>
                     <orgName>Bibliothèque nationale de France. Département des Manuscrits</orgName>
                  </repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Indien 508</idno>
                  <idno type="alternate"><idno>Tamoul 508</idno></idno>
               <idno type="URI">https://archivesetmanuscrits.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cc1040351</idno><idno type="URI">https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b525092794</idno></msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#MTM">
                  <summary><p>A copper plate grant, furnished with partial printed translation into French.</p>

<p>The plate, engraved on recto (23 lines) and verso (26 lines) records five land transactions in connection with the upkeep of a <foreign xml:lang="sa">maṇḍapa</foreign>, i.e. a choultry or, in French, <foreign xml:lang="fr">chaudrie</foreign>.</p>
<p>It appears that a certain Tiruvampalanīlaṅkarai Nayiṉār founded a <foreign xml:lang="sa">maṇḍapa</foreign> in Muruṅkaippākkam for Tāṇṭavatampiṟāṉ / Tāṇṭavatampirāṉ / Tāṇṭavayyar, son of Nākaliṅkatampirāṉ (p1v2), and made an endowment (p1r12‒13) for him, who, as in charge of the <foreign xml:lang="sa">maṇḍapa</foreign>, was residing there (p1r14‒15).</p>
  <p>In the Śaka year 1616, Nallatampi Mutaliyār and Aḻakappa Mutaliyār of Muruṅkaippākkam donated land to Tāṇṭavatampiṟāṉ (land transaction n° 1, p1r1‒p1r10).</p>
    <p>In the same Śaka year 1616, the same Tiruvampalam Nallatampi and Aḻakappaṉ made a further hereditary land donation to Tāṇṭavatampirāṉ (land transaction n° 2, p1r11‒p1r23).</p>
<p>In the Śaka year 1618, Kūṉpāppureṭṭiyār, Paricareṭṭiyār and Kōṉērikavaṇṭaṉ of Ariyāṅkuppam made a further land donation to Tāṇṭavatampirāṉ (land transaction n° 3, p1v1‒p1v9).</p>
<p>In the Śaka year 1621, a Reṭṭi of Kiḷiñcikuppam made a further donation (land transaction n° 4, p1v10‒p1v16).</p>
<p>Finally, in the year Cupāṉu, four people (Tiruvampalam Nallatampi again, Tiruv<choice><unclear>e</unclear><unclear>ē</unclear></choice>ttakāmmacikappu Mutali, Ammaiyappaṉ Kuppaippiḷḷai, and Teṉṉavarāyaṉ Ciṉṉatampi) made a regulation of the donation (land transaction n° 5, p1v17‒p1v26).</p>
<p>The text is complete.</p>
<p>Description based on the examination of the original manuscript (May 2019).</p>  <p>Dimensions assessed at the time of examination.</p>      
</summary>
                  
               <msItem synch="#U1" xml:id="T1" defective="false"><title xml:lang="ta"><term xml:lang="en">5 Land Transactions</term></title><textLang mainLang="tam"/></msItem></msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="plate">
                     <supportDesc material="copper">
                        <support>
                           <measure unit="stringhole" quantity="0"/>
                           
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure unit="plate" quantity="1">1 (U1).</measure>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              
                              
                           </dimensions>
                        <dimensions type="object" unit="mm"><width quantity="305"/><height quantity="20"/></dimensions><dimensions type="written" unit="mm"/></extent>
                        <collation><desc xml:id="U1">1 plate = <emph rend="bold">5 Land Transactions</emph>. No foliation.

</desc></collation>
                        
                        
                     <condition>Fairly good state of preservation. Slight damages on the left side of plate and at one corner. Green oxydation, here and there, but excellent readability.</condition></supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        
                     <layout columns="1">The engraved surface is framed by two parallel lines at the edges of the plate. The lines 25‒26 on the verso are layed-out as 5 columns.</layout></layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc><handNote synch="#U1" scope="sole" script="tamil" medium="incised"/></handDesc>
                  <additions>
                  <desc subtype="inserted">The plate is accompanied by a folio (180 x 120 mm), printed recto-verso, in French. On the <locus facs="3">recto</locus> is an administrative decision dated to January 17th, 1791, which has no relation to our plate, in contradistinction with the <locus facs="4">verso</locus>, where are French translations/paraphrases of two of the land transactions (n° 1 and n° 3) recorded in the plate. These translations (<quote>Traduction des actes de donation qui se trouvent écrits sur une plaque de cuivre</quote>) are certified by Maridas, <quote>interprète en chef du roi au conseil supérieur et au tribunal de la Chaudrie</quote> and dated to May 30th, 1789, Pondichéry. There are further countersigned <quote>Pour copie</quote> by Léger. Maridas took the Śaka years rather than the Jovian cycle years as references for the date of the transactions in his translations. Note also that, as for land transaction n° 3, the given land has, according to Maridas, an area of <quote>30 cougis</quote> i.e. 30 <foreign xml:lang="ta">kuḻi</foreign>s, while the plate (p1v6) mentions an area of 50 <foreign xml:lang="ta">kuḻi</foreign>s. This folio is taken from a printed document entitled <title xml:lang="fr">Les habitants indiens de Pondichéry à la chambre de députés</title> (Nantes: Imprimerie Busseuil, 1846), which is in fact a petition, advocating for fiscal relief, addressed in 1845 to the French parliament by Nadour Sidam Barom, in the name of the Indian inhabitants of Pondicherry.</desc></additions>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1704" notBefore="1694">1704 at the earliest, since this is the internal date given for the last of the five land transactions recorded on the plate, dated respectively to the year Śaka 1616 (1694‒5 CE) and the year Tātu (1696‒7 CE) of the Jovian cycle for the first two, to the year Śaka 1618 (1696‒7 CE) and the year Vekutāṉiya (1698‒9 CE) of the Jovian cycle for the third, to the year Śaka 1621 (1699‒1700 CE) and the year Viṣa (i.e. Viṣu) (1701‒1702 CE) of the Jovian cycle for the fourth and to the year Cupāṉu (1703‒1704 CE) of the Jovian cycle for the fifth and last one. There is thus a discrepancy of two years between the Śaka and Jovian cycle years.</origDate>                     
                  <origPlace>Pondicherry.</origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  
                  <provenance>
                     
                  <p>Pondicherry area.</p></provenance>
                  
                  <acquisition>
                     <p>Bequeathed by Madame Goschler (1873).</p>
                  </acquisition>
                  
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <listBibl>
                     
                  <bibl>Cabaton, Antoine. 1912. <title>Catalogue sommaire des manuscrits indiens, indo-chinois &amp; malayo-polynésiens</title>. Bibliothèque nationale. Département des manuscrits. Paris: E. Leroux. — See <ref target="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10329763p/f90">p. 71, no. 508</ref>.</bibl><bibl>Francis, Emmanuel. 2019-05-13. INDIEN 508 BnF: Copper Plate from Pondicherry. <ref target="https://tst.hypotheses.org/479">https://tst.hypotheses.org/479</ref></bibl><bibl>Vinson, Julien &amp; Feer, Léon &amp; s.n. 1866-. <title> Catalogue des manuscrits tamoul et télinga</title>. Manuscript, BnF Indien 577. — See <ref target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b105375868/f247">f. 116r, no. 508</ref>.</bibl></listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         
      <p><emph rend="bold">General</emph> ― Unmarked length of <foreign>ō</foreign> and <foreign>ē</foreign> supplied. Unmarked <foreign>puḷḷi</foreign> supplied. Conjectural reading (text unclear) between parentheses. Supplied reading (text lost) between square brackets. Alternative readings separated by slash. <emph rend="bold">In transliteration</emph> ― Unmarked elided overshort <foreign>u</foreign> supplied as an apostrophe. Uppercase for initial vowels. Symbols between curly brackets. <emph rend="bold">Abbreviations</emph> ― c = column; f = folio; lf = library foliation; lm = left margin; r = recto; rm = right margin; u / U followed by a number = unit (codicological and/or textual); v = verso.            </p></encodingDesc>
      
   <xenoData type="webannotation"><![CDATA[[]]]></xenoData><revisionDesc>
         
      <change when="2020-05">This catalogue entry has been redacted by Emmanuel FRANCIS (CNRS, CEIAS UMR 8564, EHESS/CNRS) for the research program Texts Surrounding Texts (TST, FRAL 2018, ANR/DFG). Version 1, May 2020.</change><change when="2021-08">Updated to TST encoding conventions by <persName>Emmanuel FRANCIS</persName>.</change><change when="2022-05">Revised by <persName>Emmanuel FRANCIS</persName>. Version 1, May 2022.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
   <graphic url="https://gallica.bnf.fr/iiif/ark:/12148/btv1b525092794/manifest.json"/></facsimile>
<text synch="#U1" corresp="#T1" xml:lang="ta"><body>
  <ab>
    
  <pb facs="1" n="[1]r"/>
  
  <lb n="1"/><g ref="#pcs"/> cālivakaṉacakāṟtam 1616 <g ref="#varuṣam">varuṣam</g> cellā niṉṟa tātu <g ref="#varuṣam">varuṣam</g> citti
  <lb n="2" break="no"/>rai <g ref="#mācam">mācam</g> <g ref="#muthal">mutal</g> muruṅkaippākkam nallatampi mutaliyār Aḻakappa mutaliyār Ava
  <lb n="3" break="no"/>rkaḷ tiruvampalanīlaṅkarai nayiṉār Avarkaḷ kaṭṭukiṟa maṇṭapam kuḷam pū
  <lb n="4" break="no"/>ntōṭṭam tōppu turavu yitukaḷukkāka viṭṭa nilam puñcai {kuḻi} 150
  <lb n="5"/>yitu tāṇṭavatampiṟāṉukku kuṭuttōm yitukku yātām oruvaṟ
  <lb n="6"/>vikātam paṇṇiṉ atē Uṇṭāṉāl keṅkaikaraiyil kārāmpa
  <lb n="7" break="no"/>cuvai koṇṇa tōṣattil pōka kaṭavār ākavum yituvum mā
  <lb n="8" break="no"/>ṉiyam viṭṭatu maṇṭapattukku mēlaṇṭai puñcai {kuḻi} 50 kiḻakkē
  <lb n="9"/>maṇal veḷiyil {kuḻi} 32 yittai Apakariccavaṉ vīṭukulaṣṣeya
  <lb n="10" break="no"/>m <g ref="#pcs"/> tiruvampalam nallatampi Aḻakappaṉ <g ref="#pcs"/><app><note xml:lang="en"><emph rend="bold">Translation of lines 1-10</emph>: "Year 1616 of the Śaka Cālivākaṉa, [that is,] year Tātu current, month of Cittirai, day 1. (We) the honourable (<foreign xml:lang="ta">avarkaḷ</foreign>) Nallatampi Mutaliyār [and] Aḻakappa Mutaliyār [of] Muruṅkaippākkam, [for the upkeep of] the pillared hall (<foreign xml:lang="sa">maṇḍapa</foreign>), the pond (<foreign xml:lang="ta">kuḷam</foreign>), the flower-garden (<foreign xml:lang="ta">pūntōṭṭam</foreign>), the grove (<foreign xml:lang="ta">tōppu</foreign>), and the well (<foreign xml:lang="ta">turavu</foreign>) that the honourable Tiruvampalanīlaṅkarai Nayiṉār has built (<foreign xml:lang="ta">kaṭṭukiṟa</foreign>); for all of this (<foreign xml:lang="ta">yitukaḷukkāka</foreign>), the land given [by us] (<foreign xml:lang="ta">viṭṭa nilam</foreign>) [is] 150 <foreign xml:lang="ta">kuḻi</foreign>s of <foreign xml:lang="ta">puñcai</foreign>. This we have given to Tāṇṭavatampiṟāṉ. To this [gift], whoever makes obstruction/destruction, if that happens, let him be (<foreign xml:lang="ta">ākavum</foreign>) due (<foreign xml:lang="ta">kaṭavār</foreign>) to go into the sin of killing a black cow (<foreign xml:lang="ta">kārāmpacuvai</foreign>) on the bank of the Ganges. Furthermore, a <foreign xml:lang="ta">māṉiyam</foreign> that has been given [is] 50 <foreign xml:lang="ta">kuḻi</foreign>s of <foreign xml:lang="ta">puñcai</foreign> on the west side of the pillared hall [and] 32 <foreign xml:lang="ta">kuḻi</foreign>s at Maṇal Veḷi on the east side (of the pillared hall). [For] He who does wrong (<foreign xml:lang="ta">apakariccavaṉ</foreign>) to this (<foreign xml:lang="ta">ittai</foreign>), [there will be] the ruin of [his] house and family. Tiruvampalam Nallatampi [and] Aḻakappaṉ."</note></app>

  <lb n="11-23"/><gap reason="ellipsis"/>
  
  
  <pb facs="2" n="[1]v"/>
  <lb n="1-26"/><gap reason="ellipsis"/>
    
    </ab>
</body></text></TEI>
