<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tei-to-html.xsl" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Grammar of Tamil (<foreign xml:lang="ta">cen tamiḻ</foreign>), by Beschi</title>
            
         <editor><persName>Cristina MURU</persName><orgName>DISTU Department, University of Tuscia</orgName></editor><editor><persName>Emmanuel FRANCIS</persName><orgName>CESAH, CNRS-EHESS, Aubervilliers</orgName></editor></titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TST Project</publisher>
            <date>2025</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>
                     <orgName>Bibliothèque nationale de France. Département des Manuscrits</orgName>
                  </repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Indien 192</idno>
                  <idno type="alternate"><idno>282</idno></idno>
               <idno type="URI">https://archivesetmanuscrits.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cc103711q</idno><idno type="URI">https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10029452v</idno></msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#STM">
                  <summary><p>A copy of the grammar of the High Tamil (<foreign>centamiḻ</foreign>) composed in Latin by the Italian Jesuit Giuseppe Costantino Beschi (1680-1740).</p>
<p>By a Christian copyist as indicated by the cross in the header of each page.</p></summary>
                  
               <msItem synch="#U2" xml:id="T1" defective="false" class="#illakkanam"><title xml:lang="la"><title xml:lang="en">Grammar of Tamil</title></title><author xml:lang="la">Giuseppe Costantino Beschi (1680-1747)</author><textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="tam"/><incipit xml:lang="la"><pb n="1" facs="5"/>
<lb n="11-12"/>
Religiosis J. C. missionarijs C.J.B. salutem in do<ex>mi</ex>no plurimam
<lb n="13ff."/>Cum anno elapso vulgaris Tamulica lingua Grammaticam Apostolico vestro desiderio famulatum praestiturus obtulerim, brevi me nonnulla de Elegantioni hujus lingua dialecto daturum promoseram <gap reason="ellipsis"/>

<pb n="5" facs="9"/>
<lb n="31-33"/>
<gap reason="ellipsis"/> quibus praenotatis incipiam tandem praecepta quæ de elegantioni hâc Dialecto tradere constitui valete.

<pb n="6" facs="10"/>
<lb n="1"/>Pars prima
<lb n="2"/>Caput pri<ex>mu</ex>m
<lb n="3"/>§us p<ex>ri</ex>mus
<lb n="4"/>De Litteris
<lb n="5"/>I° omissis quae in lingua vulgaris Grammaticâ de litteris fusé scripsimus <gap reason="ellipsis"/>

</incipit><explicit xml:lang="la"><pb n="81" facs="85"/>
<lb n="6-8"/>sed nullâ aliâ arte quam ut delectent populum, ac risum excitent, adeo ut inutile fit in iis artem investigare.</explicit></msItem></msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  
                  
                  
                  
                  
               <objectDesc form="codex" rend="manuscript">
                     <supportDesc material="paper industrial">
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        
                     <support>
                           
                           
                        <p>Same <watermark>watermark</watermark> as found in manuscripts BnF Indien 189,  190, 617, and 634 (see Colas and Colas-Chauhan 1995: 51, 67). The watermark shows the letter T surmounted by a crown and placed on a base, itself surmounting a <emph>cartouche</emph> which contains a J followed by a fleur-de-lis and the name CUSSON (cf. nos. 3292 and 3293, pl. 424 and no. 694, pl. 109 in Heawood 1969 [1950]).
</p></support><extent>
                           <measure unit="folio" quantity="44">[1] + 44 + [2] (U1 + U2 + U3).</measure>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              
                              
                           </dimensions>
                        <dimensions type="object" unit="mm"/><dimensions type="written" unit="mm"/></extent><foliation>Pagination 1-81 (U2) on top (right or left) of page in Arabic numbers.</foliation><collation><desc xml:id="CoverFront">the <emph rend="bold">front cover</emph>. Shelfmark on recto. </desc><desc xml:id="U1">1 folio = <emph rend="bold">front guard leaf</emph>. No foliation. Shelfmark on recto. Verso blank. Shelfmark on recto. Verso blank.</desc><desc xml:id="U2">41 folios = <emph rend="bold"><title xml:lang="en">Grammar of Tamil (<foreign xml:lang="ta">cen tamiḻ</foreign>)</title></emph>. Roman pagination 1-81. f41v blank.</desc><desc xml:id="U3">2 folios = <emph rend="bold">back guard leaves</emph>. No foliation. Blank recto verso.</desc><desc xml:id="CoverBack">the <emph rend="bold">back cover</emph>.</desc></collation><condition>Very good state of preservation.</condition></supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        
                     <layout columns="1" writtenLines="33 37"/></layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc><handDesc><handNote synch="#U2" scope="sole" script="latin tamil" scriptRef="#tamilPulliSporadic" medium="ink brown"><desc><p>According to Filliozat (1937: 283, fn. 1) this is a copy made by Abraham-Hyacinthe Anquetil-Duperron (1731-1805) (see BnF NAF 22436 for an example of his handwriting). However, the handwriting in this manuscript seems to be similar to that of Jean Calmette (1692-1739 or 1740). As he declares in a letter  sent from Ballabaram in 1732, he was among those Jesuits who copied some of the manuscripts sent to the Royal Library (fonds Brotier 89, fol. 37a, 37b cited in Colas and Chauhan 1995: 11).</p>
<p>The <emph>puḷḷi</emph> is marked only on <emph>cinna ra</emph> and is otherwise not regularly used.</p>
<p>Double-curled <emph>kompu</emph> is not used. The differentiation between <emph>o/ō</emph>, <emph>e/ē</emph> is marked by a stroke placed above the letter in order to mark the short C.</p>
<p>Differentiation between <emph>ra/ā</emph> is marked by a stroke placed above it. The <emph>periya ra</emph> is has a double loop.</p></desc></handNote></handDesc><decoDesc>
                  </decoDesc><additions>
                  <desc type="shelfmark" subtype="spine">BnF shelfmark sticker <quote>INDIEN 192</quote> (<locus facs="93">spine</locus>).</desc><desc synch="#CoverFront" type="shelfmark" subtype="cover top">Shelfmark in black ink <quote>n. 282</quote> (<locus facs="1">front cover, recto</locus>), that is Ancien fonds 282, described in 1739 <title>Catalogus</title> (n° CCLXXXII, p. 448).</desc><desc synch="#CoverFront" type="shelfmark" subtype="beginning cover">BnF shelfmark sticker <quote>INDIEN 192</quote> (<locus facs="2">front cover, verso</locus>).</desc><desc synch="#U1" type="shelfmark" subtype="beginning top">BnF shelfmark <quote>Tamoul 192</quote> (<locus facs="3">f[1]r</locus>).</desc><desc synch="#U2" corresp="#T1" type="title">Title (<locus facs="5">p. 1</locus>)
<quote rend="block">
  <lb n="1"/>Grammatica
  <lb n="2"/>Latino-Tamulica
  <lb n="3"/>ubi
  <lb n="4"/>De Elegantiori Linguæ Tamulica Dialecto
  <lb n="5"/>செநதமிழ  dictâ
  <lb n="6"/>cui adduntur tamulica poësos rudimenta
  <lb n="7"/>ad usum
  <lb n="8"/>Missionariorum Societatis Jesu
  </quote></desc><desc synch="#U2" corresp="#T1" type="stamp">Stamps are found at the beginning of the manuscript, on <locus facs="5">p. 1</locus>, and at the end, on <locus facs="85">p. 81</locus>. The stamp used is a red circle with a double line containing 3 fleurs-de-lis surmounted by a crown with the inscription <quote>BIBLIOTHEQUE ROYALE</quote>. This stamp is a variant of the stamp n. 21 in Josserand and Bruno (1960: 281), in use during the Bourbon Restoration (July 1830 - January 1831).</desc></additions><bindingDesc>
                     <binding><p><p>The cover boards at the front and back of the book appear to be attached to the quires by the cords which are secured by means of channeling.</p>
<p>The boards and spine are covered with paper which is folded over the edges of the boards forming a turn-ins and glued down. Pastedowns of an initial and a final bifolios onto the inside of the board partially conceal these mechanism of the binding and also the channeling. The manuscript is made of 33 quires of six or three bifolios.</p> </p><decoNote type="stringhole"><measure unit="stringhole"/></decoNote></binding>
                  </bindingDesc></physDesc>
               <history>
                  
                  
                  
               <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="gregorian" notBefore="1730" notAfter="1739">No internal date. The <foreign>terminus ad quem</foreign> is 1739, the date of the <title>Catalogus</title> in which this manuscript is described.

1760 in Vinson (1867: 49 and 1867-1868: 46) and in Vinson and Feer (1866-: 46).
Indeed, in Cabaton (1912: 32) the same date has been corrected with an annotation in 1739.

If this manuscript was copied by Calmette the date woould be pushed further back up to 1730, even though the manuscript is not listed among those sent by the Jesuits to the Royal Library in the 1730's (see Omont 1902; Colas 1997).</origDate>
                     
                  <origPlace>Tamilnadu or Pondicherry</origPlace></origin></history>
               <additional>
                  <listBibl>
                     
                  <bibl><title>Notices sur des manuscrits en langue européenne, relatifs à l'Inde : grammaires, dictionnaires, relations, etc., par M. Fauriel</title>. In <title>Anciens catalogues de la Bibliothèque du Roi et de différentes collections qui sont venues l'accroître aux XVIIe, XVIIIe et XIXe siècles</title>. Bibliothèque nationale de France. Département des Manuscrits. NAF 5445. Notice n° 12, f. 23r-v.
</bibl><bibl>Cabaton, Antoine. 1912. <title>Catalogue sommaire des manuscrits indiens, indo-chinois and malayo-polynésiens</title>. Bibliothèque nationale. Département des manuscrits. Paris: E. Leroux, p. 32.
</bibl><bibl><title>Catalogus codicum manuscriptorum Bibliothecae regiae. Codices manuscriptos orientales, Tomus Primus.</title>. Parisiis, e Typographia Regia. 1739.</bibl><bibl>Colas, Gérard. 1997. <title type="article">Les manuscrits envoyés de l’Inde par les jésuites français entre 1729 et 1735</title>. In <title>Scribes et manuscrits du Moyen-Orient</title>, edited by Francis Déroche, François and Richard, Francis. Paris, France: Bibliothèque nationale de France, pp. 345-362.

</bibl><bibl>Colas, Gérard and Colas-Chauhan, U. 1995. <title>Manuscrits telugu. Catalogue raisonné.</title> Paris: Bibliothèque Nationale de France.  


</bibl><bibl>Filliozat, Jean. 1937.<title> Une Grammaire sanscrite du XVIIIe siècle et les débuts de l’indianisme en France</title>. In <title>Journal Asiatique</title>, Tome CCXXIX. pp. 275-284.</bibl><bibl>Feer, Léon. n.d. <title>Tables du catalogue des manuscrits des manuscrits tamouls et télingas</title>. BnF Indien 578, f. 26r.</bibl><bibl>Heawood, Edward. 1969 [1950]. <title>Watermarks mainly of the 17th and 18th centuries</title>. Hilversum: The Paper Publications Society.</bibl><bibl><title>Fragment de catalogue des manuscrits Tamouls, deuxieme partie, par Julien Vinson</title>, c. 1869. BnF Indien 1062,  f. 66bis. 
</bibl><bibl> Josserand, Pierre and Jean Bruno. 1960. <title type="article">Les estampilles du Département des imprimés de la Bibliothèque nationale</title>. In <title>Mélanges d'histoire du livre et des bibliothèques offerts à Monsieur Frantz Calot</title>. Paris: Librairie d’Argences, pp. 261-298.
</bibl><bibl>Omont, Henri. 1902. <title type="article">XIV Missions en Chine et dans l’Inde. Fourmont aîné, les PP. Fouquet et de Prémare, Signard et le P. Le Gac (1684-1737)</title>. In <title>Missions archéologiques françaises en Orient aux XVIIe et XVIIIe siècles. </title>Seconde partie. Paris: Imprimerie nationale, pp. 806-851.
</bibl><bibl>Vinson, Julien. 1867. <title>Manuscrits tamouls</title>. [Paris]. 49 p. Proof-readings. [Indien 1–204] 
</bibl><bibl>Vinson, Julien. 1867-1868. <title>Catalogue des manuscrits tamouls. Corrected proofreadings printed by the atelier oriental de l’Imprimerie nationale.</title> BnF, access No. 4-IMPROR-77 (B), p. 46.
</bibl><bibl>Vinson, Julien and Léon Feer and s.n. 1866–. <title>Catalogue des manuscrits tamouls (1-574) et télingas (1-65)</title>. BnF Indien 577, f. 46</bibl></listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         
      <p><emph rend="bold">Transliteration conventions</emph> ― <emph>puḷḷi</emph>, <emph>ō</emph>, and <emph>ē</emph> are used only if they are found in the manuscript. ― <emph rend="bold">Abbreviations</emph> ― C = consonant, cf. = compare, f. = folio, ff. = folios, fn. = footnote, r. = recto.
</p></encodingDesc>
      
   <revisionDesc>
         
      <change when="2022-04">Record created by <persName>Cristina MURU</persName>. Version 1, April 2022.</change><change when="2025-02">Revised by <persName>Emmanuel FRANCIS</persName>. Version 2, February 2025.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
   <graphic url="https://gallica.bnf.fr/iiif/ark:/12148/btv1b10029452v/manifest.json"/></facsimile>
</TEI>