<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tei-to-html.xsl" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Grammaire de la Langue Malabar</title>
            
         <editor><persName>Cristina Muru</persName><orgName>DISTU Department, University of Tuscia</orgName></editor></titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TST Project</publisher>
            <date>2022</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>
                     <orgName>Bibliothèque nationale de France. Département des Manuscrits</orgName>
                  </repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">NAF 9114</idno>
                  <idno type="alternate"><idno>Picot 123</idno></idno>
               <idno type="URI">https://archivesetmanuscrits.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cc41612d/cd0e4778</idno></msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#STM">
                  <summary><p>A syllabary and a grammar of the Malayalam language.</p> 

<p>It is not divided in numbered chapters, however nine sections can be identified on the basis of titles and arguments. They are listed below:</p>
<list rend="numbered">
  <item><emph> Regles Generalles pour les noms</emph>. Nouns are inflected into five declensions (pp. <locus facs="12">1</locus>-<locus facs="22">11</locus>).</item>
	<item><emph>Pronoms</emph>, i.e. personnels, Qual, possessifs, demonstatifs, relatifs, interrogatifs, indefinis, responsifs –affirmatifs et negatifs (pp. <locus facs="23">12</locus>-<locus facs="33">22</locus>).</item>
	<item><emph>Noms des nombre</emph>, i.e. cardinal, adverbe (pp. <locus facs="34">23</locus>-<locus facs="39">28</locus>). This section also includes: <emph>Grand Livret de Multiplication</emph> (pp. <locus facs="40">29</locus>-<locus facs="52">41</locus>); <emph>Quarré de Pythagore, en Chiffres Mallabars</emph> (p. <locus facs="53">42</locus>).</item>
	<item><emph>Adjectif</emph> (pp. <locus facs="54">43</locus>-<locus facs="57">46</locus>); <emph>Genre</emph> (pp. <locus facs="57">46</locus>-<locus facs="59">48</locus>); <emph>Comparatif</emph> (pp. <locus facs="59">48</locus>-<locus facs="60">49</locus>).</item>
	<item><emph>Conjugaison des Verbs</emph> (pp. <locus facs="60">49</locus>-<locus facs="102">91</locus>). Apart from moods and tenses (i.e. Indicatif, Subjonctif, Optatif, Infinitif, Gerundif, Participe, Conditionnel, Imperative, Supin, présent, imparfait, preterit parfait, passé eloigné, anterieur, plus que parfait, futuro, passé avenir), this section also includes <emph>Verbe Personnel</emph>, <emph>Verbs Effectifs et mandatifs</emph>, <emph>Verbs deffectifs affirmatif</emph> and <emph> negatifs</emph>, <emph>Particule qui rendent les verbes affirmatifs negatifs</emph>, <emph>Verbs de l'Elegance Mallabarre</emph>. The section on verbs and with <emph>Maniere d'use des Verbs, et quand on doit s'en servir</emph> (pp. <locus facs="103">92</locus>-<locus facs="107">96</locus>).</item>
	<item><emph>Propositions</emph> (i.e. de lieu, de temp, de maniere, qui governent le Genitif, le Datif, l'accusatif, etc.) (pp. <locus facs="107">96</locus>-<locus facs="113">102</locus>).</item>
	<item><emph>Conjonction</emph> (pp. <locus facs="113">102</locus>-<locus facs="115">104</locus>).</item>
	<item><emph>Interjection</emph> (pp. <locus facs="115">104</locus>-<locus facs="116">105</locus>).</item>
	<item><emph>Syntaxe ou maniere de connoitre toutes les parties d'un discour</emph> (pp. <locus facs="116">105</locus>-<locus facs="125">114</locus>).</item>
</list>
  <p>Description based on the online digitized version.</p></summary>
                  
               <msItem synch="#U1a" xml:id="T1" defective="false" class="#illakkanam"><title xml:lang="fr">Alphabet contenant tous les divers caractere Malabar, et leurs composés avec leur vraye prononciation en française</title><textLang mainLang="fra" otherLangs="mal"/><incipit xml:lang="fr">Les trente cinq Consonne Malabare</incipit><explicit xml:lang="fr">pour que la finalle ne s'en pronounce <gap reason="illegible"/>
                                      </explicit></msItem><msItem synch="#U1b" xml:id="T1" defective="false" class="#illakkanam"><title xml:lang="fr">Les Rudiments de la langue Malabare</title><textLang mainLang="fra" otherLangs="mal"/><incipit xml:lang="fr"><milestone n="1" unit="page" facs="12"/>
<lb n="1"/><emph>Regle Generalles pour <lb n="2"/>les noms</emph>
<lb n="3"/>Combien y a til de nombres? Il ya en a deux.</incipit><explicit xml:lang="fr"><milestone n="114" unit="page" facs="125"/>
<lb n="16"/>il vaut autant que la particule scilicet.</explicit></msItem></msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="paper">
                        <support>
                           <measure unit="stringhole"/>
                           <p>Yellowish paper. </p>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure unit="folio" quantity="65"> 1 bifolio front guard leaf + 61 + 1 bifolio back guard leaf (u1 + U1 + u2).</measure>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              
                              
                           </dimensions>
                        <dimensions type="object" unit="mm"/><dimensions type="written" unit="mm"/></extent>
                        <collation><desc xml:id="CoverFront">the front cover. Shelfmark on recto. </desc><desc xml:id="u1">1 bifolios = front guard leaf. No foliation. Shelfmark on recto. Verso blank.</desc><desc xml:id="U1">61 folios = <emph>Alphabet and Grammar of the Malayalam language</emph>. Original Arabic pagination.</desc><desc xml:id="U1a">2 folios = Syllabary page: table with Malayalam letters. No foliation.</desc><desc xml:id="U1b">57 folios = <emph>Les Rudiments de la langue Malabare</emph>. Original Arabic pagination 3-114. </desc><desc xml:id="u2">1 bifolio = back guard leaf. No foliation. </desc><desc xml:id="CoverBack>the back cover.</desc></collation>
                        
                        
                     <foliation>Arabic original numeration on the upper right side of each page. </foliation><condition>Quite good conditions apart for the cover board that is slightly damaged.</condition></supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        
                     <layout>The text occupies the whole page. ca. 28 lines per page. Layout is organised similarly to a table for noun and pronoun declensions,  verb paradigms, and numbers. </layout></layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc><handNote synch="#u1 #U1" scope="sole" script="latin malayalam" medium="ink black brown"/></handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                  <decoNote synch="#U1a" type="table" subtype="detached"><desc>The consonants of the Malayalam language. </desc></decoNote></decoDesc>
                  <additions>
                  <desc synch="#u1" type="title shelfmark" subtype="guard-folio">Title:<emph> Grammair de la langue Malabar</emph>.</desc><desc synch="#u1" type="shelfmark" subtype="guard-folio">Shelfmark: Picot 123.</desc><desc synch="#U1" corresp="#T1" subtype="beginning guard-folio"><stamp>stamp:</stamp> red circle containing an eagle and the writing <emph>Bibliothèque Impérial MSS</emph>. This is the stamp in use from 1852 to 1870 (cf. stamp n. 36 in Josserand and Bruno 1960: 282). It is placed in the middle of the page.</desc><desc synch="#U1a" corresp="#T1" type="title" subtype="beginning"><emph> Alphabet</emph>

</desc></additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding><p>The stiff boards and spine is covered with paper that is folded over the edges of the boards and glued down. Hence, pastedowns are applied to conceal this mechanism.
</p></binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="gregorian" notBefore="1750" notAfter="1782">No internal date. Vinson, who catalogued it as MS.IND.17 <title xml:lang="fr">Rudiment de la langue Malabar</title> described it in 1902 saying that it probably dates back to the beginning of the 19th century (in Petit 2014: 450). The proposed span of time is calculated on the basis of the permanence of  Bernard François Bertrand Picot <emph>marquis</emph> de la Motte (1734-1797) in India. Indeed, he reached the Malabar Coast in 1750 and he was named General Commander of the Malabar Coast and Governor of Mahé in 1751. He returned in France in 1782 (Courcelle 1823: 370-371). The linguistic feature of the variety of the Portuguese language used in the manuscript would allow to date it earlier, at the first half of the 17th century.</origDate>
                     <origPlace>probably, Mahé</origPlace>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance><p>Correspondance de Bernard Picot de la Motte (NAF 8992-9114).</p></provenance>
                  <acquisition><p>Cf. le n° 3659 des nouvelles acquisitions françaises.</p></acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <listBibl>
                     
                  <bibl>Courcelles, Jean Baptiste Pierre Jullien de. 1823. <title xml:lang="fr">Dictionnaire historique et biographique des Généraux Français, depuis le Onzième siècle jusqu'en 1823.</title> Tome Huitième. Montesq-Riva. Paris: Arthus Bertrand, Treuttel et Wurtz.</bibl><bibl><title xml:lang="fr">Correspondance de Bernard PICOT DE LA MOTTE, commandant général de la côte du Malabar et gouverneur de Mahé, avec divers agents français et étrangers dans les places et comptoirs des Indes et de la Chine (1760-1780).</title> NAF 8992-9114.</bibl><bibl> Josserand, Pierre and Jean Bruno. 1960. <title xml:lang="fr" type="article">Les estampilles du Département des imprimés de la Bibliothèque nationale</title>. In <title xml:lang="fr"> Mélanges d'histoire du livre et des bibliothèques offerts à Monsieur Frantz Calot</title>. Paris: Librairie d’Argences, pp. 261-298.</bibl><bibl>Petit, Jérôme. 2014. <title xml:lang="fr" type="article">Les Savants Occidentaux, Lecteurs et (Re)copists des Manuscrits Orientaux Eugene Burnof, Leon Feer, Julien Vinson</title>. In: Nalini Balbir and Maria Szuppe (eds.), <title xml:lang="fr">Lecteurs et copistes dans la traditions manuscrites Iraniennes, Indiennes et Centrasiatiques. Scribes and readers in Iranian, Indian and Central Asian manuscript traditions.</title> Vol. XII/1-2, pp. 437-459.</bibl></listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         
      <p><hi rend="bold">Abbreviations</hi> ― cf. = compare, f. = folio, ff. = folios, r = recto, v = verso, U/u = unit (codicological and/or textual), v = verso.</p></encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         
      </revisionDesc>
   <xenoData type="webannotation"><![CDATA[[]]]></xenoData></teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
   <graphic url="https://gallica.bnf.fr/iiif/ark:/12148/btv1b52515017x/manifest.json"/></facsimile>
</TEI>