<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tei-to-html.xsl" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><title xml:lang="sa">Pāṇinīyaśikṣā</title></title>
        
      <editor><persName>Charles LI</persName><orgName>CNRS, CEIAS, UMR 8564</orgName></editor></titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TST Project</publisher>
        <date>2023</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository>
              <orgName>Bibliothèque nationale de France. Département des Manuscrits.</orgName>
            </repository>
            
            <idno type="shelfmark">Sanscrit 1145</idno>
            <idno type="alternate"/>
          <idno type="URI">https://archivesetmanuscrits.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cc1000139</idno></msIdentifier>
          <msContents class="#STM">
            <summary>              <p>This manuscript of the <title xml:lang="sa">Pāṇinīyaśikṣā</title>, a Sanskrit grammatical work, was edited from printed editions by <persName>Umraosingh Sher-Gil</persName> and given by him to the <orgName xml:lang="fr">Bibliothèque nationale</orgName>. It is written in ink on watermarked, laid Ingres Canson &amp; Montgolfier paper, bound in book form, with a typewritten letter attached <locus facs="2">inside the front cover</locus>.</p>
              <p>The manuscript was produced in Paris, where the Sher-Gil family had moved in order to support the artistic career of Umraosingh's daughter, <persName>Amrita</persName>. The <locus facs="3">letter</locus>, addressed to <persName role="addressee">Edgar Blochet</persName>, is dated April 4th, 1930. A handwritten addendum at the <locus facs="19">end of the manuscript</locus> is dated to April 1st, 1930. The <locus facs="18">colophon</locus> of the manuscript, in English, dates its completion to March 17, 1930.</p>
              <p>In the letter to Blochet, Sher-Gil states that the <orgName xml:lang="fr">Bibliothèque nationale</orgName> contains a <ref target="Sanscrit_0568.xml">manuscript</ref> of the commentary of the <title xml:lang="sa">Pāṇinīyaśikṣā</title>, which omits the <term xml:lang="sa">mūla</term> text.</p>
              <p>Sher-Gil points out that the text is not likely to have been authored by <persName xml:lang="sa">Pāṇini</persName> himself, but is usually attributed to <persName xml:lang="sa">Piṅgalācārya</persName>. Accordingly, both his <locus facs="5">English</locus> and <locus facs="7">Sanskrit</locus> title pages attribute the text to <persName xml:lang="sa">Piṅgalācārya</persName>.</p>
              <p>Sher-Gil notes that the manuscript has been copied from an edition published in Benares in 1887. Although this edition has not yet been located, the text is very close to the Benares edition of 1877, by <persName xml:lang="sa">Becanarāma Tripāṭhin</persName>. However, it seems that the edition that Sher-Gil used included Vedic accent marks, which are not present in the 1877 edition. Moreover, it seems that Sher-Gil consulted more than one edition; the marginal notes use two different referencing systems, and, in his letter to Blochet, he mentions using <quote>printed copies published in India at Benares as well at Bombay</quote>.</p>
            </summary>
            
            
          <msItem xml:id="mūla" defective="false"><title xml:lang="sa">Pāṇinīyaśikṣā</title><author xml:lang="sa">Piṅgalācārya</author><textLang mainLang="san" otherLangs="eng"/><filiation><p>Sher-Gil notes that <ref target="Sanscrit_0568.xml">Sanscrit 568</ref> contains a commentary on the text, but not the <term xml:lang="sa">mūla</term> itself.</p></filiation><rubric xml:lang="sa"><milestone n="2" unit="page" facs="9"/> <lb n="1"/>śrīgaṇeśāya namaḥ ||</rubric><incipit xml:lang="sa">atha śikṣāṃ pravakṣyāmi pāṇinīyaṃ mataṃ yathā |</incipit><explicit xml:lang="sa"><milestone n="10" unit="page" facs="18"/>  <lb n="7"/>trinayanamukhaniḥsṛtām imāṃ ya iha paṭhet prayataḥ sadā dvi<lb n="8"/>jaḥ | sa bhavati dhanadhānya kīrtimān sukham atulaṃ ca samaśnute <lb n="9"/>divi iti || 60 ||</explicit><finalRubric xml:lang="sa">iti pāṇinīyamatānusāriṇī śrī<space/>piṅgalācā-<lb n="10"/>rya viracitā śikṣā samāptā ||</finalRubric><colophon xml:lang="sa"><seg function="copy-statement">Copy prepared from the Benares edition of 1887 C.E. <lb n="11"/>by Umraosingh Sher-Gil. in Paris. 17th March 1930.</seg> <term xml:lang="sa">oṁ śauṃ</term></colophon></msItem><msItem xml:id="letter" defective="false"><title xml:lang="en">Typewritten letter to Edgar Blochet</title><author xml:lang="en">Umraosingh Sher-Gil</author><textLang mainLang="eng" otherLangs="fra"/></msItem></msContents>
          <physDesc>
            
            
            
            
            
            
          <objectDesc form="codex">
              <supportDesc material="paper industrial">
                
                
              <support>
                  <p>Laid Ingres paper, Canson &amp; Montgolfier watermark.</p>
                </support><extent>
                  <measure unit="page" quantity="15">English title page, blank verso, Sanskrit title page, 1-10, addendum, blank verso.</measure>
                  <dimensions type="object" unit="mm">
                    <width quantity="245"/>
                    <height quantity="160"/>
                  </dimensions>
                  <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                    <width quantity="240"/>
                    <height quantity="155"/>
                  </dimensions>
                  <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                    <width quantity="190"/>
                    <height quantity="105"/>
                  </dimensions>
                </extent><foliation>
                    <desc>Devanāgarī numerals, top-right margin, recto and verso.</desc>
                </foliation><condition>Perfect condition.</condition></supportDesc>
              <layoutDesc>
                <layout columns="1" writtenLines="10"/>
              </layoutDesc>
            </objectDesc><handDesc>
            <handNote scope="sole" script="devanagari" medium="ink black"><desc>Writes in thicker ink for the text, and thinner ink for the notes. Hand of <persName role="scribe" key="Umraosingh Sher-Gil">Umraosingh Sher-Gil</persName>.</desc></handNote></handDesc><typeDesc><typeNote scope="sole" script="latin" medium="ink black"><desc>The typewritten letter contains a number of corrected typos, which indicate that it was typed on modern QWERTY or AZERTY keyboard. The typo of <q>V</q> for <q>C</q>, specifically, indicate that those two letters were placed side-by-side. In contrast, the <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:QWERTY_1878.png#/media/File:QWERTY_1878.png">original QWERTY layout</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sholes_and_Glidden_typewriter#/media/File:Sholes-Glidden_1874.jpg">Sholes-Glidden typewriter</ref> places the letter <q>X</q> between <q>C</q> and <q>V</q>.</desc></typeNote></typeDesc><decoDesc>
            <decoNote type="table" subtype="beginning"><desc><locus facs="8">Title page, verso</locus>: Table of Sanskrit phonemes, according to the text. Possibly copied from the edition.</desc></decoNote></decoDesc><additions>
              
              
              
              
              
              
              
              
            <desc type="title" subtype="cover">
                <locus facs="1">Cover</locus>
                <quote rend="block" xml:lang="sa">
                    <lb n="1"/>śrī
                    <lb n="2"/>pāṇinīyamatānusāriṇī
                    <lb n="3"/>śrīpiṅgalācāryaviracitāśikṣā ||
                </quote>
              </desc><desc type="stamp" subtype="beginning"><locus facs="5">English title page</locus>. Library stamp, as well as stamp stating <quote xml:lang="fr">DON No. 6023</quote>. The corresponding entry in the BnF registry of donations shows that the manuscript entered the library on 7 April 1930. It is described as <quote xml:lang="fr">Çiksha, Traité de phonétique sanskrite par Piñgalâtchârya de la main de Sirdar Umraosingh Shergil.</quote> It also lists Sher-Gil's address as <quote xml:lang="fr">6 Avenue Saint-Philibert</quote>, which was renamed <term xml:lang="fr">rue Alfred-Bruneau</term> in 1938.
                  </desc><desc type="title" subtype="beginning">
                <locus facs="5">English title page</locus>
                <quote rend="block">
                    <lb n="1"/>Çikshá
                    <lb n="2"/>Treatise on Sanskṛta Phonetics compiled
                    <lb n="3"/>by Pingala-áchárya, in accordance with
                    <lb n="4"/>the system of Pánini, but which has
                    <lb n="5"/>passed under the appellation of Paṇini Çiksha.
                </quote>
              </desc><desc type="title" subtype="beginning"><locus facs="7">Sanskrit title page</locus>.
                    <quote rend="block" xml:lang="sa"><lb n="1"/>śrī <lb n="2"/>pāṇinīyamatānusāriṇī <lb n="3"/>|| śrīpiṅgalācāryaviracitā śikṣā ||</quote></desc><desc type="commenting-note" subtype="marginal"><locus facs="16">Page 8</locus>, right margin, in pencil: <quote>? ? marks ?</quote>. Sher-Gil seems to have pencilled-in Vedic recitation marks, copied from an edition, which he did not understand. Accordingly, he has not inked the recitation marks.</desc><desc type="gloss" subtype="marginal">Variant readings copied from the edition in the bottom margin, numbered. Variant readings in the left and right margins, perhaps copied from a different edition, marked with symbols.</desc><desc type="commenting-note" subtype="marginal">Note in the left margin, <locus facs="17">page 9</locus>: <quote><term xml:lang="sa">māṃḍūkīya</term> reads <term xml:lang="sa">svāmnātaṃ</term></quote>. This is referring to the <title xml:lang="sa">Māṇḍūkīśikṣā</title>, verse 159, which reads <quote xml:lang="sa">svāmnātaṃ</quote> in place of <quote xml:lang="sa">svāmnāyyaṃ</quote> (see the edition of <persName xml:lang="sa">Pāṭhaka</persName> 1893, <ref target="https://archive.org/details/siksasangrahaofyagnavalkyaandothersyugalkisoravyasachowkambha1893_772_m/page/n471/mode/1up">473</ref>).</desc><desc type="postface" subtype="intertextual"><locus facs="19">Page 11</locus>: <quote rend="block"><lb n="1"/>This correct and collated copy is :- <lb n="2"/>Presented to the Bibliotheque Nationale, Paris, by <lb n="3"/>Sirdar Umraosingh Sher-Gil of Majitha (Amritsar district), Panjab. INDIA. <lb n="4"/>Paris. 1st April 1930. Umraosingh. Sher-Gil. <lb n="5"/>Note :- This is the text, of which a commentary only <lb n="6"/>exists in the Bibliotheque Nationale as <add place="above">Paniniya</add> Çiksha <lb n="7"/>No 568. MS. Sanscrit which contains, unfortunately many <lb n="8"/>errors.</quote></desc></additions><bindingDesc>
              <binding>
                <p>Cover made of thicker, brown paper.</p>
              <decoNote type="stringhole"><measure unit="stringhole" quantity="5"/></decoNote></binding>
            </bindingDesc></physDesc>
          <history>
            
            
          <origin>
              <origDate calendar="gregorian" when="1930"><persName>Umraosingh Sher-Gil</persName> dates the copying of the text to <q>17th March 1930</q>. An addendum is dated <q>1st April 1930</q>. The typewritten note is dated <q>4th.April.1930</q>.</origDate>
              <origPlace>Paris</origPlace>
            </origin><acquisition>
              <p>Presented to the <orgName xml:lang="fr">Bibliothèque nationale</orgName> by <persName xml:id="UmraosinghShergil">Umraosingh Sher-Gil</persName>.</p>
            </acquisition></history>
          <additional>
            <listBibl>
              
              
              
              
              
            <bibl>Cabaton, Antoine. 1907-1908. <title xml:lang="fr">Catalogue sommaire des manuscrits sanscrits avec supplément manuscrit.</title> Paris: E. Leroux. Supplemented by Jean Filliozat. <ref target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10536321f/f215.item">279</ref>.</bibl><bibl>Li, Charles. 2020. <title type="article">A glimpse of Umraosingh Sher-Gil in Sanscrit 1145.</title> <title>Texts Surrounding Texts: Satellite Stanzas, Prefaces and Colophons in South-Indian Manuscripts</title>. 29 November. <ref target="https://tst.hypotheses.org/1927">https://tst.hypotheses.org/1927</ref>.</bibl><bibl><persName xml:lang="sa">Trīpāṭhin, Bechanarāma</persName>, ed. 1877. <title xml:lang="sa">Pāṇinīyaśikṣā</title>. Benares: Vrajabhūṣaṇadās aur kampanī. Digitized by eGangotri from the Acharya Chakradhar Joshi Collection — <ref target="https://archive.org/details/PaniniyaShikshaBenares1877BrajBhushanDas/">https://archive.org/details/PaniniyaShikshaBenares1877BrajBhushanDas/</ref>. Black and white reproduction by Google from Harvard University Library — <ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=XOMoAAAAYAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover">https://books.google.com/books?id=XOMoAAAAYAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover</ref>.</bibl><bibl>Sher-Gil, Umraosingh. 1914. <title type="article">Umrao Singh Sher-Gil's letter to Ignaz Goldziher.</title> Collection of Manuscripts and Rare Books and the Oriental Collection, Hungarian Academy of Sciences Library. <ref target="http://real-ms.mtak.hu/3874/">http://real-ms.mtak.hu/3874/</ref>.</bibl><bibl><persName xml:lang="sa">Pāṭhaka, Yugalakiśora Vyāsa</persName>, ed. 1893. <title>A Collection of Śikshás by Yájñavalkya and others, with commentaries on some of them</title>. Benares: B. D. Das. <ref target="https://archive.org/details/siksasangrahaofyagnavalkyaandothersyugalkisoravyasachowkambha1893_772_m/">https://archive.org/details/siksasangrahaofyagnavalkyaandothersyugalkisoravyasachowkambha1893_772_m/</ref>.</bibl></listBibl>
          </additional>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      
      
    <p>Spaces in the manuscript are reproduced in the transcription.</p><p><emph rend="italic">oṁ</emph> represents the <term xml:lang="sa">oṃkāra</term> symbol.</p></encodingDesc>
    
  <xenoData type="webannotation"><![CDATA[[]]]></xenoData><revisionDesc>
      
      
    <change when="2020-11">Catalogue entry created by Charles LI (CNRS, CEIAS, UMR 8564).</change><change when="2021-04">Line breaks added by Charles LI.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
  
  <facsimile>
    <graphic url="https://tst-project.github.io/img/Sanscrit_1145/index.json"/>
  </facsimile>
<text corresp="#letter" xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <milestone facs="3" n="1" unit="page"/>
      <lg>
        <l><lb n="1"/>To</l>
        <l><lb n="2"/><persName role="addressee" key="Edgar Blochet">Mons Blochet</persName></l>
        <l><lb n="3"/>Librarian Manuscript Section</l>
        <l><lb n="4"/>Bibliotheque Nationale</l>
        <l><lb n="5"/>Paris.</l>
      </lg>
      <p><lb n="6"/>Dear Sir,</p>
      <p><lb n="7"/>I have much pleasure in presenting to your great <lb n="8"/>Library, a copy of the text of the Cikshá ,which I have <lb n="9"/>prepared .</p>
      <p><lb n="10"/>It is the text of the Panini Ciksha so called, <lb n="11"/>a manuscript copy of the <emph rend="underline">commentary</emph> of which your Library <lb n="12"/>possesses as No. 568, and which I found to be without the <lb n="13"/>original text of which it is the Sanskrit <subst><del>V</del><add>C</add></subst>ommentary.</p>
      <p><lb n="14"/>So I thought that your library should possess a <lb n="15"/>manuscript of the text also, which now I have made from <lb n="16"/>reliable printed copies published in India at Benares as <lb n="17"/>well at Bombay,giving the variations in readings which <lb n="18"/>these texts give.</p>
      <p><lb n="19"/>My Benares text has <add place="above">also</add> <emph rend="underline">the</emph> commentary which you pos-<lb n="20"/>sess, and which ha<subst><del>s</del><add>d</add></subst> been corrected besi<del>e</del>d<add>es,</add> by a learned Br-<lb n="21"/>ahmin of my acquaintance ,so far as the typographic errors <lb n="22"/>were concerned. And as your manuscript of this commentary <lb n="23"/>contains numerous errors, I shall be glad some day,when I have <del>time to</del> <pb facs="4" n="2"/>time to prepare a corrigenda on a seperate paper for it, <lb n="1"/>to be kept with your text for the use of any scholar who<del>a</del> <lb n="2"/>may wish to study it in the future.</p>
      <p><lb n="3"/>I will add that this Cikshá which is generally called <lb n="4"/>Panini Ciksha has been found to be composed by Pingala <lb n="5"/>or some one called by that name,according to the system <lb n="6"/>of Panini, as the note at the end of the Benares copy <lb n="7"/>says on the strength of the variation in reading of the <lb n="8"/>finale. Beside<subst><del>d</del><add>s</add></subst> that the very first verse of the text <lb n="9"/>which says that <emph rend="underline">"I expound the Ciksha according to the <lb n="10"/>views of Panini",</emph> make it sure that it is not by Panini at <lb n="11"/>least as generally alleged.</p>
      <p><lb n="12"/>I have the honour to be Dear Sir,</p>
      <p><lb n="13"/>Yours faithfully</p>
      <p><lb n="14"/>Umraosingh Shergil</p>
      <lg>
        <l><lb n="15"/><persName role="author" key="Umraosingh Sher-Gil">Sirdar Umraosingh Sher-Gil</persName> <lb n="16"/>of Majitha.</l>
        <l><lb n="17"/>Amritsar District .</l>
        <l><lb n="18"/>Punjab.</l>
        <l><lb n="19"/>4th.April.1930. British INDIA.</l>
      </lg>
    </body>
  </text></TEI>