<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tei-to-html.xsl" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><title xml:lang="sa">Sārasvatīprakriyā</title></title>
            
         <editor><persName>Charles LI</persName><orgName>CNRS, CEIAS, UMR 8564</orgName></editor></titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TST Project</publisher>
            <date>2021</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>
                     <orgName>Bibliothèque nationale de France. Département des Manuscrits</orgName>
                  </repository>
                  <idno type="URI">https://archivesetmanuscrits.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cc102170g/ca59800664994684</idno>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Sanscrit 1868</idno>
                  <idno type="alternate">14</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#STM">
                  <summary><p>The <title xml:lang="sa">Sārasvatīprakriyā</title> (<title xml:lang="sa">Sārasvataprakriyā</title>, <title xml:lang="sa">Sārasvatavyākaraṇa</title>, or <title xml:lang="sa">Sārasvata</title>)  is a grammar manual by <persName xml:lang="sa">Anubhūti Svarūpācārya</persName> (13th - 14th century). It  is the primary text of the non-Pāṇinian <term xml:lang="sa">Sārasvata</term> school of Sanskrit  grammar, which, according to Hartmut Scharfe, <q>enjoyed for some time  great popularity and was patronized by both Hindu and Muslim princes</q>  (1977, 189). According to S. K. Belvalkar, the majority of the  commentaries on the text were composed in the 16th and 17th centuries  (1915, 92). There are also multiple translations into Tibetan, as well  as Tibetan commentaries.</p>
<p>This manuscript begins with the <title xml:lang="sa">Kṛdantaprakriyā</title>, the last chapter of the text, which deals with <term xml:lang="sa">kṛdantas</term>, words formed by applying suffixes to verbal roots to produce nouns, adjectives, or indeclinables. Although the <title xml:lang="sa">Kṛdantaprakriyā</title> is only one section of the larger text, it may have been transmitted as a text on its own. Sanscrit 562, for example, is a manuscript of the <title xml:lang="sa">Kṛdantaprakriyā</title>, even though its <ref target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b100827851/f22.item">colophon</ref> calls it the <title xml:lang="sa">Sārasvatīprakriyā</title>. Similarly, here, the foliation begins with the number 1, and the first dozen folios includes the marginal title <q xml:lang="sa">kṛ</q>, abbreviating <title xml:lang="sa">Kṛdantaprakriyā</title>. This manuscript, Sanscrit 562, and <ref target="https://openn.library.upenn.edu/Data/0002/html/mscoll390_item2607.html">Ms. Coll. 390 Item 2607 (Kṛdantaprakriyā)</ref>  from the University of Pennsylvania Libraries seem to share the same,  abbreviated version of the text (compared to the printed editions of  <persName xml:lang="sa">Navakiśorakara Śāstrī</persName> or <persName xml:lang="sa">Śivadatta Kudāl</persName>).</p>
<p>This manuscript is missing a number of folios and is incomplete at  the end. Moreover, it also contains text from other sections of the <title xml:lang="sa">Sārasvatīprakriyā</title>; the verso side of the last folio is from the <title xml:lang="sa">Ākhyātapratyayāḥ</title>, the section on conjugating verbs, which precedes the <title xml:lang="sa">Kṛdantaprakriyā</title>.  Here again, the text seems to be abbreviated; it skips from the sūtra  <q xml:lang="sa">āyaḥ</q> (ed. Śivadatta Kudāl, <ref target="https://archive.org/details/sarasvatavyakarnathreevruttiofanubhutisvarupacharyasubodhikachandrakirtied.sivad/page/n250/mode/1up">237</ref>) to <q xml:lang="sa">saparokṣayor jergiḥ</q> (<ref target="https://archive.org/details/sarasvatavyakarnathreevruttiofanubhutisvarupacharyasubodhikachandrakirtied.sivad/page/n253/mode/1up">240</ref>).
</p>
<p>The manuscript is wrapped in a paper sleeve formed from a wedding inviation, dated 1841, which precedes the year the manuscript was acquired, in 1842.</p></summary>
                  
               <msItem defective="true"><title xml:lang="sa">Sārasvatīprakriyā</title><author xml:lang="sa">Anubhūtisvarūpācārya</author><textLang mainLang="san"/><filiation><p>Sanscrit 562, University of Pennsylvania <ref target="https://openn.library.upenn.edu/Data/0002/html/mscoll390_item2607.html">Ms. Coll. 390 Item 2607 (Kṛdantaprakriyā)</ref></p></filiation><incipit xml:lang="sa">atha kṛdantaprakriyā nirūpyate || kṛt karttari vakṣyamā<lb n="2"/>naḥ pratyayaḥ kṛtsaṃjñako bhavati sa ca karttari bhavati tṛvu<lb n="3"/>ṇai || dhātos tṛvuṇai pratyayau bhavataḥ paktṛ iti sthi<lb n="4"/>te</incipit><explicit xml:lang="sa"><milestone n="120v" unit="foio"/>pakṣe āyaḥ gupādibhyaḥ svārthe āyapratyayo bhavati <lb n="2"/>gopāyāṃ cakāra <add place="top margin">āyādayaḥ ārddhadhātuke  vā vaktavyāḥ</add> jugopaḥ || hrī lajjāyāṃ jihrayāṃ <lb n="3"/>cakāraṃ pakṣe jihrāya jihriyatuḥ jihriyuḥ || jijaye || <lb n="4"/>saparokṣayor jergiḥ cātoḥ sapratyayaparokṣayor jergi<lb n="5"/>r ādeśo bhavati jigāya jigyatuḥ jigyuḥ || la<unclear>p_ pa</unclear>ri<lb n="6"/>bhāṣaṇe lalāpa vaicityāpahlapayor alpakā<unclear>le</unclear> pi ṇabādir vaktavyaḥ <unclear>lupto haṃ kila</unclear> vilalāpa vilepa</explicit></msItem></msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="pothi">
                     <supportDesc material="paper handmade">
                        <support>
                           <measure unit="stringhole"/>
                           
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure unit="folio" quantity="34">1-4, 11-12, 30-31, 93-96, 98-103, 106, 108-116, 119-120</measure>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <width quantity="230"/>
                              <height quantity="110"/>
                           </dimensions>
                        <dimensions type="object" unit="mm"/><dimensions type="written" unit="mm"><width quantity="175"/><height quantity="70"/></dimensions></extent>
                     <foliation>Foliation in <term xml:lang="sa">Devanāgarī</term> numerals, left margin, verso. The folio numbering from 114 to 120 have been corrected, incremented by 1 (previously 113 to 119). </foliation><condition>Some damage due to wear around the edges. Some water damage.</condition></supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout writtenLines="7 8">20-25 akṣaras per line. Double margin lines framing the left and right margins.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc><handNote scope="sole" script="devanagari" scriptRef="#bengaliYa" medium="ink black"><desc>Nandināgarī-style ca and ra. Bengāli-style da. Distinctive kṣa ligature.</desc></handNote></handDesc>
                  <additions>
                  <desc type="documenting-note" subtype="detached">Paper formed by a blank piece of paper, ripped in half and folded in half, on which is written, in pencil, the extent of the manuscript. This paper seems to show the bleed-through of some writing in ink.</desc><desc type="shelfmark documenting-note" subtype="detached">Another paper sleeve is formed by an invitation to the wedding of <persName>Julie Petit</persName> and <persName>John Kelly Snowden</persName>, folded in half. On the verso side of this invitation is written in ink, centered, <q>14</q> (this manuscript is 14th within this acquisition), followed by <q xml:lang="fr">fragment d'un ouvrage grammatical.</q> and <q xml:lang="fr">Ecrit en dévanagari.</q> On the left hand-side, a reference to the registry of acquisitions, <q>R. B. 3096</q> and the date of acquisition, <q>1842</q>. The new shelfmark is given in pencil. The invitation reads: <q xml:lang="fr" rend="block"><lg>
  <l>Paris le 17 Mai, 1841</l>
  <l>M</l>
  </lg>
</q>
<q rend="block">Monsieur Petit, chef d'Institution, et Madame Petit, ont l'honneur de vous faire part du Mariage de Mademoiselle Julie Petit, leur fille, avec Monsieur John Kelly Snowden, Docteur en Médecine.</q>
<q rend="block">Et vous prient d'assister á la bénédiction nuptiale que leur sera donnée le lundi 24 Mai 1841, á 1<del>1</del><add>0</add> heures du matin, en l'Eglise St Gervais.</q></desc><desc type="title" subtype="marginal">Running marginal title, <q xml:lang="sa">kṛ</q>, in the left margin, verso, folios 1-8, 11-12. </desc></additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding><p>Two paper sleeves.</p></binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1842"/>
                     
                  </origin>
                  <provenance/>
                  <acquisition><p>Acquired as part of a group of paper manuscripts on grammatical subjects on 10 May 1842.</p></acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <listBibl>
                     
                  <bibl>Belvalkar, Shripad Krishna (1915). <title xml:lang="sa">An account of the different existing systems of Sanskrit grammar</title>. Poona: Aryabhushan Press.</bibl><bibl>Cabaton, Antoine. (1907-1908). <title xml:lang="fr">Catalogue sommaire des manuscrits sanscrits avec supplément manuscrit</title>. Paris: E. Leroux. Supplemented by Jean Filliozat. <ref target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10536321f/f324.item">388</ref>.</bibl><bibl>Ghose, Bhagagovinda (1970). <title type="article">Study of Sanskrit Grammar in Tibet</title>. <title>Bulletin of Tibetology</title> 7(2): 21-41.</bibl><bibl>Li, Charles (2020). "A wedding invitation around MS Sanscrit 1868". <title><ref target="https://tst.hypotheses.org/">Texts Surrounding Texts: Satellite Stanzas, Prefaces and Colophons in South-Indian Manuscripts (Paris BnF and Hamburg Stabi collections)</ref></title>. 10 October. <ref target="https://tst.hypotheses.org/1813">https://tst.hypotheses.org/1813</ref>.</bibl><bibl><persName xml:lang="sa">Navakiśorakara Śāstrī</persName> (1936). <title><ref target="https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.326647">The Sārasvata Vyākaraṇa of Anubhûti Svarûpãchãrya, edited with two commentaries, the Subodhikā commentary of Chandrakīrti, the Prasāda commentary, the Lingānuśāsana with commentary, notes (Manorama), index, etc. (Part II)</ref></title>. Benares: Jaya Krishna Das Haridas Gupta.</bibl><bibl>Scharfe, Hartmut (1977). <title>Grammatical literature</title>. Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz.</bibl><bibl><persName xml:lang="sa">Śivadatta Kudāl</persName> (1926). <title xml:lang="sa"><ref target="https://archive.org/details/sarasvatavyakarnathreevruttiofanubhutisvarupacharyasubodhikachandrakirtied.sivad">Sārasvatavyākaraṇam, Candrakīrrtivyākhyāsahitam</ref></title>. Bombay: <persName xml:lang="sa">Pāṇḍuraṅga Jāvajī</persName>.</bibl><bibl>Verhagen, Pieter C. (1993). <title>A History of Sanskrit Grammatical Literature in Tibet, Vol. 1: Transmission of the canonical literature</title>. Leiden: Brill.</bibl></listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         
      <p>Spaces added where possible. An underscore denotes an explicit virāma.</p></encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         
      <change when="2021-09">First version.</change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
</TEI>
