<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tei-to-html.xsl" ?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><title xml:lang="fr">Papiers d'Etienne Formont relatifs à un essai de traduction française d'un fragment tibétain</title></title>
            
         <editor><persName>Weiyu Lin</persName><orgName>University of California, Berkeley</orgName></editor><editor><persName>Jason Cannon-Silber</persName><orgName>Universität Hamburg</orgName></editor></titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TST Project</publisher>
            <date>2024</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>
                     <orgName>Bibliothèque nationale de France. Département des Manuscrits</orgName>
                  </repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Tibétain 470</idno>
                  <idno type="alternate"><idno>Ancien Tibétain 143</idno></idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#CM">
                  <summary>Tibétain 470 is a notebook containing a later copy of two translations of a Tibetan fragment, discovered in a ruined monastery in Siberia towards the end of the 17th century or the onset of the 18th. This fragment was subsequently presented to Emperor Peter the Great, who forwarded it to the French Academy in Paris, where it was translated into Latin by Michel Fourmont using a Latin-Tibetan dictionary from the Royal Library. However, Fourmont's translation was egregiously inaccurate, and subsequent renditions were not without flaws—a reality later underscored by H. H. Wilson in an 1832 article. In this same article, Wilson introduced a more refined English translation by the renowned Sándor Kőrösi Csoma (1784-1842). The Tibétain 470 manuscript includes the first page of Fourmont's interlineal Latin translation followed by a French translation of the Latin rendering, said to be the work of Fourmont together with his brother Étienne. The original Tibetan text, with interlineal transcription, is included on what seems to be a separate leaf inserted at the back of the notebook. Given the scarcity of Tibetan texts in Europe during that era, this fragment gained prominence among intellectuals from the early 18th to the 19th century, even serving as a seminal ‘textbook’ for Tibetan learners.</summary>
                  
               <msItem defective="false"><title xml:lang="fr"><term xml:lang="fr">Essai de Fourmont</term></title><textLang mainLang="fra"/><incipit xml:lang="fr">Premier feuilles du travail de Fourmont pour l'interprétation du fragment tibétain d'Abloü-Kit.</incipit><explicit xml:lang="fr">On n'a retrouvé du brouillon de Fourmont que a premier feuilles.</explicit></msItem><msItem defective="false"><title xml:lang="fr"><term xml:lang="fr">Traduction en Francais, faite par les frs Etienne et Michel de Fourmont freres, Professeurs au college Royal, De la Feuille Thibetienne Envoyée Par le Czar a Mr l[']Abbé Bignon.</term></title><textLang mainLang="fra"/><incipit xml:lang="fr">Cette Feuille a [é]té trouvée avec plusieurs autres libres, dans un palais abandonné et presque enseueli sous les sables au Novdatet(?) a dix journées de la mer Caspienne.</incipit><explicit xml:lang="fr">63. Insensé donc celuy, qui meurt sans ces Reflexions.</explicit></msItem></msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  
                  
                  
                  
                  
               <objectDesc form="codex" rend="manuscript">
                     <supportDesc material="paper">
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        
                     <support>
                           
                        </support><extent>
                           <measure unit="folio" quantity="9">1 fly leaf with the notebook's old shelfmark, followed by 3 numbered leaves with writing on the recto only, followed by 3 leaves with writing on both sides, followed by an inserted sheet(?) with the original Tibetan, followed by a fly leaf with another note to the translation pasted on the recto.</measure>
                           <dimensions type="object" unit="mm">
                              
                              
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              
                              
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              
                              
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent><foliation>Arabic numerals, recto, upper right corner</foliation></supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        
                     <layout>The inserted leaf with Tibetan text has been written in a "landscape" format.</layout></layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc><handDesc/><additions>
                  </additions><bindingDesc>
                     <binding>
                        
                        <decoNote type="stringhole">
                           <measure unit="stringhole"/>
                        </decoNote>
                    </binding>
                  </bindingDesc></physDesc>
               <history>
                  
                  
                  
               <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="gregorian"/>
                     
                  </origin></history>
               <additional>
                  <listBibl>
                     
                  <bibl>Li, Charles. 2022. <title type="article">The Foucaux Collection at the BnF: Forgotten Works of a Forgotten Scholar</title>. <title>Bulletin d’Études Indiennes</title> 35: 141-159.</bibl><bibl>Csoma de Kőrös, Alexander and H. H. Wilson. 1832. <title type="article">Translation of a Tibetan Fragment, by Mr. Csoma de Kőrös, with remarks by H. H. Wilson, Secy.</title> <title>Journal of the Asiatic Society of Bengal</title> 1 (1-12): 271-282.</bibl></listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc><p>Roman script</p></encodingDesc>
      
   <revisionDesc/></teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
   <graphic url="https://gallica.bnf.fr/iiif/ark:/12148/btv1b10888182p/manifest.json"/></facsimile>
</TEI>