<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tei-to-html.xsl" ?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> Ritual Manuals of the Cycle of the <title xml:lang="sa-Latn">Sarvadurgatipariśodhanatantra</title></title>
            
         <editor><persName>Weiyu Lin</persName><orgName>University of California, Berkeley</orgName></editor><editor><persName>Jason Cannon-Silber</persName><orgName>Universität Hamburg</orgName></editor></titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TST Project</publisher>
            <date>2024</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>
                     <orgName>Bibliothèque nationale de France. Département des Manuscrits</orgName>
                  </repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Tibétain 514</idno>
                  <idno type="alternate"><idno/></idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#MTM">
                  <summary>   Tibétain 514 comprises woodblock prints of eight ritual manuals related to the cycle of the Sarvadurgatipariśodhana tantra, also known as the 'Elimination of All Evil Destinies.' Within this collection, there are a total of 21 copies, with each text having varying numbers of copies. The works included are as follows:
<p>1. <title xml:lang="bo-Tibt">བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ངན་སོང་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡོང་སུ་སྦྱོང་བ་གཟི་བརྗིད་ཀྱི་རྒྱལ་བོའི་བདག་བསྐྱེད་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྒྱས་པ་བཞུགས་སོ</title> (five copies)  Tentative Translation: Extensive Teaching on the Self-Generation as the Brilliant King who Eliminated All Evil Destinies. Compare with the copy of the same text in BDRC: http://purl.bdrc.io/resource/WA1NLM874</p>

<p>The following is an English translation of the prayer that forms the second part of this text's colophon: Having been blessed by the prayer made in this way towards sentient beings as infinite as sky, without exception, may I be the lord over the enemies of two obscurations and soon achieve the level of Vairocana.</p>

<p>2. <title xml:lang="bo-Tibt">བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀུན་རིག་རྣམ་བར་སྣང་མཛད་ཀྱི་བུམ་ཆོག་བཞུགས་སོ།</title> (two copies) Tentative Translation: The Ritual Manual of the Treasure Vase (bumpa) of Sarvavid Vairocana  Notes: This appears to be a ritual manual on the ‘Treasure Vase ritual’ associated with <term xml:lang="sa-Latn">Sarvavid Vairocana,</term> Who is the central deity of the Sarvadurgatipariśodhana tantra. One copy has a slip of paper tucked in that reads: <term xml:lang="bo-Tibt">ཚེ་ལས་འདས་པ་དི་ཕྱི་བར་དོ་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཐར་པ་དང</term> (‘After the end of life, all sentient beings will be liberated’). Compare this text with <title xml:lang="bo">kun rig rnam par snang mdzad kyi bum chog sogs</title> ("[Manual] for the vase-ritual of <term xml:lang="sa-Latn">Sarvavid Mahāvairocana</term>, etc."):  https://archive.org/details/bdrc-W4CZ74499. </p>

<p>3. <title xml:lang="bo-Tibt">བཅོམ་ལྡན་བདས་ངན་སོང་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡོངས་སུ་སྦྱོང་བ་གཟི་བརྗིད་ཀྱི་རྒྱལ་བོའ་མདུན་བསྐྱེད་ཀྱི་ངག་འདོན་བཞུགས་སོ།</title> (three copies) Tentative Translation: Recitation for the Frontal Visualization of the Brilliant King</p>

<p>4. <title xml:lang="bo-Tibt">ཆ་གསུམ་གཏོར་མ་བཞུགས་སོ།</title> (two copies) Tentative Translation: Three-Part Torma Ritual     5.  <title xml:lang="bo-Tibt">བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀུན་རིག་རྣམ་བར་སྣང་མཇད་ཀྱི་བདག་འཇུག་བཞུགས་སྟོ།</title> (one copy) Tentative Translation: Manual on the Self-Initiation Ritual of <term xml:lang="sa-Latn">Sarvavid Vairocana</term></p>

<p>6. <title xml:lang="bo-Tibt">བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཐམས་ཅད་རིག་བའི་བུ་མཆོག་ལྷ་ལྔམ་བཤུགས་སོ།</title> (three copies, including one incomplete copy) Tentative Translation: The Fifth Deity: Vase Ritual of All-Seeing <term xml:lang="sa-Latn">Bhagavān (= Sarvavid Vairocana?)</term></p>

<p>7. <title xml:lang="bo-Tibt">བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀུན་རིག་རྣམ་པར་སྣང་མཛད་ཀྱི་སྒོ་ནས་གཤིན་པོ་རྗེས་འཛིན་ལྷོ་སྒོའི་ཆོ་གའི་ངག་འདོན་བཞུགས་སོ།</title> (four copies) Translation: Recitation For the Ritual of South Gate of the Funeral Ritual through <term xml:lang="sa-Latn">Sarvavid Vairocana</term></p>

<p>8. <title xml:lang="bo-Tibt">གཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀུན་རིག་རྣམ་པར་སྣང་མཛད་ཀྱི་གཏད་རག་སྨོན་ལམ་ཤིས་བརྗོད་བཞུགས་སྟོ།</title> (one incomplete copy) Translation: Recitation of the Auspicious Thanksgiving Prayer for <term xml:lang="sa-Latn">Sarvavid Vairocana</term></p></summary>
                  
               <msItem xml:id="bcumldan" defective="false"><title xml:lang="bo"><title xml:lang="bo-Tibt">བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ངན་སོང་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡོང་སུ་སྦྱོང་བ་གཟི་བརྗིད་ཀྱི་རྒྱལ་བོའི་བདག་བསྐྱེད་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྒྱས་པ་བཞུགས་སོ</title></title><textLang mainLang="bod" otherLangs="zho"/><incipit xml:lang="bo">སྐུ་གསུམ་ལྷུན་གྲུབ་རྣམ་སྣང་ཛེ་ཏ་རི</incipit><explicit xml:lang="bo">ཉི་ཟླའི་འོད་དང་མཉམ་པའི་འོད་འཕྲོ་ཞིང།</explicit><colophon xml:lang="bo">སྐུ་གསུམ་ལྷུན་གྲུབ་རྣམ་སྣང་ཛེ་ཏ་རི།
ཀུན་སྙིང་རབ་འབྱོར་བསྐྱངས་དད་ན་ཡ་ཀ།
མེ་ཏྲི་རྡོ་གདན་ནི་སྐ་ལམ་ཀའི་ཞབས།། 
གསོལ་བ་བདེ་བས་སོ་དངོས་གྲུབ་མ་ལུས་སྩོལ།
འདུལ་འཛིན་ཤེད་འབྱུང་མཁས་བཙུན་བློ་བཟངས་ཞབས།
དགེ་ལེགས་དཔལ་བཟད་མཁས་གྲུབ་ནམ་མཁའི་མཚན།
བཀའ་དྲིན་མཉམ་མེད་རྩ་བའི་བླ་མ་ལ།
གསོལ་བ་འདེ་བསསོ་དངོས་གྲུབ་མ་ལུས་སྩོལ།ཅེས།
དེ་ལྟར་གསོལ་བ་བཏབ་པའི་བྱིན་ན་བརླབས་ཀྱིས།
བདག་དད་མཁའ་མཉམ་འགྲོ་བ་མ་ལུས་པ།
སྒྲིབ་གཉིས་དགྲ་ལས་རྣ་མ་པར་རྒྱལ་གྱུར་ཏེ།
རྣམ་པར་སྣང་མཛད་གོ་འཕང་མྱུར་ཐོབ་ཤོག། 
</colophon></msItem></msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  
                  
                  
                  
                  
               <objectDesc form="pothi" rend="xylography">
                     <supportDesc material="paper">
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        
                     <support>
                           
                        </support><extent>
                           <measure unit="folio" quantity="100"/>
                           <dimensions type="object" unit="mm">
                              
                              
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              
                              <height quantity="100"/>
                           <width min="420" max="450"/></dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              
                              
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent><condition>The print's first four copies have endured considerable wear and tear, betraying extensive use and marked by numerous highlights and annotations (in the <term xml:lang="bo">dbu can</term> script). The rest of the copies are in a better state of preservation.</condition></supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        
                     <layout>Among the various copies, there appear to be copies that originated from the same print, exhibiting uniform folio size, similar preservation conditions, and each featuring Chinese notations indicating their sequence (for instance, ‘Text One’ 一本 , ‘Text Two’ 二本 ). It thus appears that the compiler of the prints used this unique set as a structuring principle, incorporating different copies of the same text into the 'mother set.' Another detail to note is a fragmentary folio, which has been glued to the backboard by a curator.</layout></layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc><handDesc><handNote script="dbucan"/></handDesc><decoDesc><decoNote type="emblem"><desc>There is a seal next to the first line of the colophon to the first text, <title xml:lang="bo">bcum ldan 'das ngan song thams cang yong su sbyong ba gzi brjid kyi rgyal po'i bdag bskyed shin tu rgyas pa bzhugs so</title></desc></decoNote></decoDesc><additions>
                  </additions><bindingDesc>
                     <binding>
                        
                        <decoNote type="stringhole">
                           <measure unit="stringhole"/>
                        </decoNote>
                    <p>The prints are enclosed within two wooden covers. Folio 1r contains three māntric syllables in Tibetan script: <term xml:lang="bo">oṃ āḥ hūṃ</term>. On top of the syllable 'āḥ,' the triad of syllables is rewritten in black ink. To the left of these redrafted syllables is the imperial title Guangxu 光緒年 (1875-1908), also penned in black ink. An unfinished blank-ink character that bears resemblance to the radical 礻(shi) lies juxtaposed between the Tibetan and Chinese inscriptions. The penmanship in blank ink more closely resembles a scribble than an attempt at conveying information about the text. No similar black ink handwriting is seen elsewhere in the text, suggesting that the author who used the black ink was likely not a user of the folios.</p></binding>
                  </bindingDesc></physDesc>
               <history>
                  
                  
                  
               <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="gregorian">It was perhaps produced during the Guangxu 光緒 reign (1875-1908), for this reign title is indicated on the folio 1r. However, the penmanship of the reign title more closely resembles a scribble than an attempt at conveying information about the text, so it is not a guaranteed indicator of the texts' dates. </origDate>
                     
                  </origin></history>
               <additional>
                  <listBibl>
                     
                  <bibl>Filliozat, Jean. 1936. <title xml:lang="fr"><ref target="gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b525101308">Catalogue sommaire du Fonds Tibétain.</ref></title>. See pp. <ref target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b525101308/f97.item">81f</ref>.</bibl></listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc><p>Wylie transliteration</p></encodingDesc>
      
   <revisionDesc/></teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
   <graphic url="https://didomena.ehess.fr/concern/data_sets/0z709554j/manifest?manifest=https://didomena.ehess.fr/concern/data_sets/0z709554j/manifest/manifest.json" facs="2"/></facsimile>
</TEI>