<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tei-to-html.xsl" ?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sūtra of 42 Chapters <title xml:lang="bo-Tibt">འཕགས་པ་དུམ་བུ་ཤེས་གཉིས་པ་ཞེས</title> 佛說四十二章經 <title xml:lang="mnc">Fucihi nomulaha Dehi juwe fiyelen nomun</title> <title xml:lang="mn">Qutuγtu Döčin qoyar kesig-tü kemegdekü sudār-a</title></title>
            
         <editor><persName>Weiyu Lin</persName><orgName>University of California, Berkeley</orgName></editor><editor><persName>Jason Cannon-Silber</persName><orgName>Universität Hamburg</orgName></editor></titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TST Project</publisher>
            <date>2024</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>
                     <orgName>Bibliothèque nationale de France. Département des Manuscrits</orgName>
                  </repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Mandchou 226</idno>
                  <idno type="alternate"><idno>Tibétain 465</idno><idno>Ancien Tibétain-Mongol 126</idno></idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#STM">
                  <summary>Mandchou 226 (formerly Tibétain 465) features the Sūtra of 42 Chapters, which is printed in four scripts: Tibetan (Uchen), Manchurian, Mongolian, and Chinese. The manuscript includes a colophon from 74v to 82r. 

According to the colophon, the Sūtra of 42 Chapters was initially translated from Chinese into Manchurian during the xinchou 辛丑 year of Qianlong's 乾隆 reign (1781). Subsequently, it was translated from Chinese into Tibetan by Khenpo (Gabo 嘎卜) Chu Suba Gashi Li Yadu Za 嘎卜楚蘇巴嘎室利牙都雜 and Khenpo Chudie Nali Sidan Biesa 楚碟那禮斯贍別薩, and into Mongolian by Lan Zhanba Poluo Jueda Ya Biesa 藍占巴波羅覺達牙別薩繙.

The colophon further reveals that this particular copy was commissioned through the contribution of one hundred taels of silver by lay Buddhist donors. It states, 'devotees continually joyously spread the dharma with the donation of one hundred taels of white gold' 信士恆臨樂施法，資白金百兩. The only other known copy of the Sūtra of 42 Chapters written in four scripts is preserved in the Toyo Bunko 东洋文库 in Japan which appears to be identical to Tibétain 465, as it contains the exact same colophon as the latter (see Zhuang, 1990)

This four-script copy is referred to in the colophon as 'four scripts combined' (siti hebi 四體合璧)

</summary>
                  
               <msItem defective="false"><title xml:lang="bo"><term xml:lang="bo-Tibt">འཕགས་པ་དུམ་བུ་ཤེས་གཉིས་པ་ཞེས</term> <term xml:lang="zh">佛說四十二章經</term> <term xml:lang="mnc">Fucihi nomulaha Dehi juwe fiyelen nomun</term> <term xml:lang="mn">Qutuγtu Döčin qoyar kesig-tü kemegdekü sudār-a</term> <term xml:lang="en">Sūtra of 42 Chapters</term></title><textLang mainLang="bod" otherLangs="zho"/><colophon xml:lang="bo">載籍佛法周昭王二十四年甲寅歲四月八日，有光自西南來照殿前。王問群臣，對曰：西南方當有大聖人出，後一千年，教流此土，至穆王五十三年庚申歲二月十五日時，佛涅槃一千一十三年。至漢明帝永平七年正月十五日，帝夜夢金人，身長丈餘，紫磨金色，赫奕如日，來詣殿前曰：我教流傳此土。帝旦集群臣，傅毅奏帝，周書異記，階下所夢將必是乎！帝覽周書異記所載大悅，遂遣王遵等一十八人西訪佛法，至月氏國，遇天竺迦葉種摩騰伽尊者班志達、法蘭二人，白馬上載釋迦佛畫像、四十二章經及大小乘經，並佛舍利一蹲同還洛陽，時永平十年十二月三十日，後復六年，二尊者摧伏異道，踊身虛空，為王說偈曰：狐非獅子類，燈非日月明，池無巨海納，丘無嵩岳榮，法雲垂世界，法雨潤群萌，顯通希有事，處處化群山，偈已以神通復歸天竺而去，斯如是語，勘校詳明，實非謬傳。至乾隆辛丑歲，欽命繙譯清文，未譯西番、蒙古文字，嘎卜楚蘇巴嘎室利牙都雜，並嘎卜楚碟那禮斯贍別薩，體滿漢謹譯番文，藍占巴波羅覺達牙別薩繙譯蒙文，兼有信士恒臨樂施法，資白金百兩，誠刻四體合璧四十二章尊經，竭資刷印，送施福德諸人，依此善力，願我佛教熾盛恒常暨諸人眾身無災惱，飢饉關亂，悲皆消除，復願一切眾生速證無上菩從正果者也。 </colophon></msItem></msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  
                  
                  
                  
                  
               <objectDesc form="pothi" rend="xylography">
                     <supportDesc material="paper">
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        
                     <support>
                           
                        </support><extent>
                           <measure unit="folio" quantity="82"/>
                           <dimensions type="object" unit="mm">
                              
                              
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <width quantity="465"/>
                              <height quantity="150"/>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <width quantity="430"/>
                              <height quantity="110"/>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent><condition>Good condition</condition></supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        
                     <layout>The title page consists of a petite pothi leaf adjoined to the page, with the sūtra's title indicated in four distinct scripts. 
The reverse of the title page is designated as folio 1, which features an illustration of a Buddha on both sides. 
Centrally positioned between these images, the title is replicated in four scripts. The sutra initiates on recto 2. Tibetan and Chinese page numbers are found in the left and right margins, respectively. As an example, recto 2 bears the Tibetan notation ཀཉིས གོད and the Chinese notation 上二; verso 2 is གཉིས	 འོག	下二
Scripts in Tibetan and Chinese are respectively placed at the top and the bottom of the page, with Manchu and Mongolian scripts sandwiched in between.
</layout></layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc><handDesc/><typeDesc><typeNote scope="sole" script="dbucan" medium="ink black"/></typeDesc><additions>
                  </additions><bindingDesc>
                     <binding>
                        
                        <decoNote type="stringhole">
                           <measure unit="stringhole"/>
                        </decoNote>
                    </binding>
                  </bindingDesc></physDesc>
               <history>
                  
                  
                  
               <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="gregorian" notBefore="1781">This sūtra was not translated to Manchurian until 1781</origDate>
                     <origPlace>China</origPlace>
                  </origin></history>
               <additional>
                  <listBibl>
                     
                  <bibl>Filliozat, Jean. 1936. <title xml:lang="fr"><ref target="gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b525101308">Catalogue sommaire du Fonds Tibétain.</ref></title>. See p. <ref target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b525101308/f70.item">54</ref>.</bibl><bibl>[Zhuang Jifa] 庄吉发. 1990. <title type="article">[Guoli Gugong bowuyuan diancang Dazang jing Manwen yiben yanjiu] <term xml:lang="zh">国立故宫博物院典藏《大藏经》满文译本研究</term> [The Manchurian Buddhist Canon Preserved in the National Palace Museum]</title>. <title>[Dongfang zongjiao yanjiu] <term xml:lang="zh">东方宗教研究</term> [Eastern Religion Research]</title> 2: 255-319.</bibl><bibl>P. G. von Möllendorf. 1890. <title type="article">Essay on Manchu Literature</title>. <title>Journal of the North China Branch of Royal Asiatic Society</title> 45, XXIV, no. 1: 122.</bibl><bibl>B. Laufer. 1907. <title type="article" xml:lang="de">Skizze der Mongolischen Literatur/</title>. <title xml:lang="hu">Keleti Szemle</title> 8: 221.</bibl><bibl>W. Heissig. 1954. <title type="article" xml:lang="de">Die Pekinger Lamaistischen Blockdrucke in mongolischer Sprache</title>. <title xml:lang="de">Göttinger
Asiatische Forschungen</title> 2, no. 149.</bibl><bibl>W. Heissig. 1961. <title type="article" xml:lang="de">Mongolische Handschriften, Blockdrucke, Landkarten</title>. <title xml:lang="de">Verzeichnis der orientalischen Handschriften in Deutschland</title> 1, no. 205.</bibl><bibl>N. Poppe, L. Hurvitz, and H. Okada. 1964. <title>Catalogue of the Manchu-Mongol Section of the Tōyō Bunko</title>, no. 43.</bibl></listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc><p>Tibetan script.</p></encodingDesc>
      
   <revisionDesc/></teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
   <graphic url="https://gallica.bnf.fr/iiif/ark:/12148/btv1b9002803x/manifest.json" facs="23"/></facsimile>
</TEI>