<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tei-to-html.xsl" ?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><title xml:lang="bo-Tibt">མ་ཎི་བཀའ་འབུམ</title>    六字真言經 </title>
            
         <editor><persName>Weiyu Lin</persName><orgName>University of California, Berkeley</orgName></editor><editor><persName>Jason Cannon-Silber</persName><orgName>Universität Hamburg</orgName></editor></titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TST Project</publisher>
            <date>2024</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>
                     <orgName>Bibliothèque nationale de France. Département des Manuscrits</orgName>
                  </repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Tibétain 515</idno>
                  <idno type="alternate"/>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#STM">
                  <summary> This sizable woodblock print of Mani Kabum (Tibetan: <title xml:lang="bo-Tibt">མ་ཎི་བཀའ་འབུམ</title>; Chinese: 六字真言經 [lit. ‘Sūtra of Six-Syllable Mantra’]) was crafted for the event of Emperor Kangxi's (1654-1722) birthday in the year 1717, as indicated in the colophon which states, 'On the 15th day of the first month during the 56th year of Kangxi's reign in the Great Qing Dynasty' (大清康熙五十六年正月十五日).  Its creation was orchestrated by the Seal-Holder Lama (Ch. Zhangyin Lama 掌印喇嘛), identified as Jinba Jiansu 金巴監素. A total of 64 identical copies of this print were produced and subsequently disseminated to a selection of monasteries ('64 copies of the “Six-Syllable Great-Qing Sūtra” were crafted using woodblock printing techniques and disseminated to various monasteries' 刻板印造六字大清真經六十四部，散與各寺).</summary>
                  
               <msItem defective="false"><title xml:lang="bo"><title xml:lang="bo">ma ṇi bka' 'bum</title>    六字真言經   </title><textLang mainLang="bod" otherLangs="zho"/><incipit xml:lang="bo"><term xml:lang="en">Glued folio:</term> oṃ ma ṇi padme hūṃ | <term xml:lang="bo-Tibt">ཨོཾ་མ་ཎི་པདྨེ་ཧཱུྃ།</term>
<term xml:lang="en">2r:</term> khams gsum grags ldan dbus na nor bu ltar | <term xml:lang="bo-Tibt">ཁམས་གསུམ་གྲགས་ལྡན་དབུས་ན་ནོར་བུ་ལྟར།</term>
</incipit><explicit xml:lang="bo"><term xml:lang="en">366r:</term> bkra shis par gyur cig | dge'o || legs sho <term xml:lang="bo-Tibt">བཀྲ་ཤིས་པར་གྱུར་ཅིག།དགེའོ།།ལེགས་སྷོ།།</term></explicit><colophon xml:lang="bo">r.366: 大清康熙五十六年正月十五日，掌印喇嘛金巴監素奏聞祝延萬壽無疆，刻板印造六字大清真經六十四部，散與各寺，汞遠奉誦，功德無量矣！</colophon></msItem></msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  
                  
                  
                  
                  
               <objectDesc form="baad" rend="xylography">
                     <supportDesc material="paper">
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        
                     <support>
                           
                        </support><extent>
                           <measure unit="folio" quantity="366"/>
                           <dimensions type="object" unit="mm">
                              <width quantity="690"/>
                              <height quantity="235"/>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <width quantity="680"/>
                              <height quantity="230"/>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <width quantity="545"/>
                              <height quantity="155"/>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent><condition>Good condition. Folio 1 may be missing. </condition></supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        
                     <layout>The text begins from folio 2r, each folio containing seven lines.  The Chinese title and folio number are written in the right margin following the format 六字真言經 (Sūtra of Six-Syllable Mantra) 上二 (recto two). The left margin contans the corresponding Tibetan notations: <term xml:lang="bo">kha gnyid</term> (two), <term xml:lang="bo">god</term> (recto). The notation ཁ persistently appears on each folio. The colophon, penned solely in Chinese, is situated at the lower margin of 366r.</layout></layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc><handDesc/><additions>
                  </additions><bindingDesc>
                     <binding>
                        <p>The folios are encased by two wood board covers. The periphery of these boards, encircled by a yellow silk, creates a recessed space to frame the folio. Notably, a double-layered silk flap is stitched along the apex of this concavity, ostensibly functioning to conceal the underlying folio that is affixed to the board. Stitched to the flap is a small piece of hemp indicating the Chinese title 六字真言 with an abbreviated Tibetan title (<term xml:lang="bo">ma ṇi</term>). 

The left panel of the glued folio presents an illustration of Avalokiteśvara, while the right has one of Songtsen Gampo, recognized as a manifestation of Avalokiteśvara. In the panel between these illustrations is written a succinct version of the foundation of Tibetan Buddhism, recounting the actions of King Songtsen Gampo who, acting under Avalokiteśvara's auspices, reportedly subdued demons and the red-faced barbarians (i.e., Tibetans). 

However, the last line on the glued folio abruptly terminates and is not resumed on the subsequent extant folio, identified as folio 2. This implies either that folio 1 is lost, or that the text on the glued folio is not meant to be complete, serving only a decorative purpose. (Filiozat identifies the glued folio as folio 1). 

The backboard has a similar design, enclosing a folio that depicts three deities, including two wrathful deities who respectively hold a sword (Manjuśrī?) and flame (Avalokiteśvara?), with a central deity holding a victory banner.  </p>
                        <decoNote type="stringhole">
                           <measure unit="stringhole" quantity="0"/>
                        </decoNote>
                    </binding>
                  </bindingDesc></physDesc>
               <history>
                  
                  
                  
               <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="gregorian" when="1717"/>
                     <origPlace>China</origPlace>
                  </origin></history>
               <additional>
                  <listBibl>
                     
                  <bibl>Filliozat, Jean. 1936. <title xml:lang="fr"><ref target="gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b525101308">Catalogue sommaire du Fonds Tibétain.</ref></title>. See p. <ref target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b525101308/f99.item">83</ref>.</bibl></listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc><p>Wylie transliteration</p></encodingDesc>
      
   <revisionDesc/></teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
   <graphic url="https://didomena.ehess.fr/concern/data_sets/0z709554j/manifest?manifest=https://didomena.ehess.fr/concern/data_sets/0z709554j/manifest/manifest.json" facs="8"/></facsimile>
</TEI>