<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tei-to-html.xsl" ?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> BhojaCaritram (Bhojaprabandha)</title>
            
         <editor><persName>Anuja Ajotikar</persName><orgName>University of Hamburg</orgName></editor></titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TST Project</publisher>
            <date>2022</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>
                     <orgName>Staats- und Universitätsbibliothek Hamburg Carl von Ossietzky</orgName>
                  </repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Cod. Palmbl. III 61</idno>
                  <idno type="alternate"><idno>35-3307</idno></idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#STM">
                  <summary>The title mentioned on the Manuscript is Bhojacaritram but the text is known as Bhojaprabandha.  The present text end does not match with the published editions of Bhojaprabandha.  Manuscript ends at the Bhoja-gopakanyayoḥ  part 67 according to the edition The Bhojaprabandha by Sree Ballala (with English Translation) by     Saradaproasad Vidyabhushan, third edition Calacutta, S, C, Auddy and co., Calcutta: 1926. </summary>
                  
               <msItem xml:id="BhojaPra" defective="false"><title xml:lang="sa">Bhojaprabandha</title><author xml:lang="sa">Ballala</author><textLang mainLang="san"/><filiation><p>New Catalogus Catalogorum vol. 17, p. 275b-276a.
</p></filiation><incipit xml:lang="sa">[1v 1] śrīmatorājarājasyabhojarājasya prabandhaḥ ādau dhārārājye bandhulasaṃjñau ciraṃ prajāḥ paryapālaya [1v 2] t</incipit><explicit xml:lang="sa">57r 9 nṛpavara tvāṃ draṣṭumutkaṇṭhate rājā camatkṛtā prāha sukuṃāri tvāṃ līlā divyānumatyā svīkurmmaḥ iti dhārānaraṃ nītvā tathaiva svīkṛtavān ..</explicit><finalRubric xml:lang="sa">hariḥ oṃ</finalRubric></msItem></msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="loose-leaf">
                     <supportDesc material="palm-leaf">
                        <support>
                           <measure unit="stringhole" quantity="2"/>
                           <p>Thick processed wooden guard folio.</p>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure unit="folio" quantity="62">2 guard folio, 3 blank folio and 57 written folio</measure>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <width quantity="331" min="320"/>
                              <height quantity="38" min="30"/>
                           </dimensions>
                        <dimensions type="object" unit="mm"/><dimensions type="written" unit="mm"><width quantity="282"/><height quantity="28"/></dimensions></extent>
                        <collation/>
                        
                        
                     <foliation>Tamil numerals are used to number  folio. Folio 57 is not numbered. </foliation><condition>Some worm eaten parts on the blank folio. black patches are seen. Many folio are damaged at the edges but does not affect the written area. </condition></supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="8 9" streams="1"/>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc><handNote script="grantha" medium="incised"><desc>Well written. Clean and big letters.</desc></handNote></handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <additions>
                  <desc type="foliation" subtype="marginal">Tamil numerals are used for folioation in the left margin. 1v to 56v are numbered and 57 is not numbered. </desc><desc type="title" subtype="front guard-folio">Front guard folio with title Bo[ja]carittam and shelf mark stickers with printed number 68 and 35-3307. Also number 68 is written in pink pencil. Back side has some traces of worms and half thin layer of wood is removed.
</desc><desc type="title" subtype="beginning">The blank folio after the from guard has title  in the centre 
Bojacaritaṃ . 
</desc><desc type="blessing" subtype="marginal">śrīmate hayagrīvāya namaḥ hariḥ oṃ śrīrastu in the left margin of the frist folio.</desc><desc type="title" subtype="beginning marginal">bhojacaritraṃ in the left margin of the first folio. </desc></additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding/>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="gregorian"/>
                     
                  </origin>
                  <provenance/>
                  <acquisition/>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <listBibl>
                     
                  <bibl>The Bhojaprabandha by Tree Ballala (with English Translation) by Saradaproasad Vidyabhushan, third edition Calacutta, S, C, Auddy and co., Calcutta: 1926
</bibl></listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         
      <p>Square bracket used to supply missing letter such as the ttile on the guard folio  Bho[ja]carita.
For correction bracket is used to show the reading before and the square bracket to show the corrrected reading.  </p></encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
   </facsimile>
<text corresp="#BhojaPra" xml:lang="sa">[1v 1] śrīmatorājarājasyabhojarājasya prabandhaḥ ādau dhārārājye bandhulasaṃjñau ciraṃ prajāḥ paryapālaya [1v 2] t . āsya ca vṛddhatve bhojarāja iti putrassamajani . sa yadā pañcavārṣikastadātmano jarāṃ jñātvā mukhyāmātyānāhū [1v 3] ya anujaṃ muñjamāha(ba)[bā]lamālokya putraṃ ca bālaṃ vīkṣya vīcārayāmasa 

[57r 8] bhojanivallabhanṃeghaṃ cātakamaṇḍalīva madhupaśreṇīvapuṣpaśrīyaṃ mākandāpikasundarīva ramaṇīvātmeśvaraṃ proṣite cetovṛttiriyam sadā 
[57r 9] nṛpavara tvāṃ draṣṭumutkaṇṭhate rājā camatkṛtā prāha sukuṃāri tvāṃ līlā divyānumatyā svīkurmmaḥ iti dhārānaraṃ nītvā tathaiva svīkṛtavān hariḥ oṃ
 
</text></TEI>