<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tei-to-html.xsl" ?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Chāndogya Upaniṣad</title>
            
         <editor><persName>Anuja Ajotikar</persName><orgName>University of Hamburg</orgName></editor></titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TST Project</publisher>
            <date>2021</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>
                     <orgName>Staats- und Universitätsbibliothek Hamburg Carl von Ossietzky</orgName>
                  </repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Cod. Palmbl. III 4</idno>
                  <idno type="alternate"><idno>35-3250</idno></idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#STM">
                  <summary>Chāndogya upaniṣad, a text belongs to the Chāndogya brāhmaṇa of the Sāmaveda. 
One Sanskrit verse in Granth scrip is written on the 61v.  
(61v 1)dadāti pratigṛṇāti kāryyamākhyāti pṛcchati pra? hi sajajano prabhūte tacca sarvaṃ (2) ? di sthitam</summary>
                  
               <msItem xml:id="chandogya" defective="false"><title xml:lang="sa">chandogya</title><textLang mainLang="san"/><filiation><p>New Catalogus Catalogorum Vol. 7.113</p></filiation><incipit xml:lang="sa">(1v 1)o[m] thamupāsītomiti hyudgāyāti tasyopavyākhñānam |</incipit><explicit xml:lang="sa">([61r 8]) ni nirate ya upaniṣatsu dharmmāste mayi santu te mayi santu .. 2103 ..</explicit><finalRubric xml:lang="sa">([61r 8]) aṣṭamodhyāyaḥ iti chāndogyopaniṣat samāptam</finalRubric></msItem></msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="pothi">
                     <supportDesc material="palm-leaf">
                        <support>
                           <measure unit="stringhole" quantity="2"/>
                           <p>Broken cover of thick Palm leaf. Both guard folios are supported by inserting a thin palm leaf to cover the damage.  </p>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure unit="folio" quantity="65">2 guard folio, 2 blank folio and 61 numbered folios.</measure>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <width quantity="400" min="380" max="400"/>
                              <height quantity="44" min="42" max="44"/>
                           </dimensions>
                        <dimensions type="object" unit="mm"/><dimensions type="written" unit="mm"><width quantity="360"/><height quantity="40"/></dimensions></extent>
                        <collation/>
                        
                        
                     <foliation>Granth numerals in the left margin. Last two folios are not numbered.</foliation><condition> Beginning of the text is lost due to cracked folio. Many folios are craked at the corners. </condition></supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        
                     <layout streams="1" writtenLines="7 8"/></layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc><handNote><desc>Neatly written.  m is written mostly for the anusvāra at the end.
Sometimes the anusvāra  after the syllable is found.</desc></handNote></handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <additions>
                  <desc type="blessing" subtype="marginal">(1v left margin) [ha]riḥ om.</desc><desc type="shelfmark" subtype="cover">32 written in pencil.   </desc><desc type="heading" subtype="cover">aparaṃ gṛhyapariśiṣṭaṃ is scratched out.</desc></additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding><p>Guard folios are broken. thin Palm leaves are used to cover the damage and support the guard folio. First guard folio is supported by inserting  two thin palm leaves in the thick guard cover for support.</p></binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="gregorian"/>
                     
                  </origin>
                  <provenance/>
                  <acquisition/>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <listBibl>
                     
                  <bibl>The Chāndogyopaniṣad with the commentary of Śaṅkara bt Dr. Sir Ganganath Jha, Poona, Oriental Book Agency, 1942.

Chāndogyopanishat Ānandagirikṛtaṭīkāsaḿva-litaṣāṅkarabhāshyasametā [Chandogya-upanishad, with the bhashya of Sankara Acharya and the tika of Anandagiri] 
Kasinatha Bala Sastri Agase, Anandasrama Sanskrit series, v. 14. Puṇyākhyapattanē,  1890.
Upaniṣads- 	Patrick Olivelle, Oxford ; New York : Oxford University Press, 1996.

</bibl></listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         
      <p>folio number for the last folio is supplied.  Occasionally spaces are added to seperate vesres. 
Syllables which are unreadable but can be guessed are added in the square brackets. Dots are used to show the gap of the syllables due to broken folio. Daṇḍa is used to mark the end of the verse or prose.  Last folio number is supplied as the folio is not numbered.</p></encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
   </facsimile>
<text corresp="#chandogya" xml:lang="sa">(1v 1) o[m] thamupāsītomiti hyudgāyāti tasyopavyākhñānam | eṣāṃ bhūtā[nām] pṛ[thivī] rasaḥ pṛ[thi] (2) vyā [a].. saḥ apāmoṣadhayo rasaḥ oṣadhīnām puruṣo rasaḥ puruṣasya 
vāgrasaḥ vāca ṛgrasaḥ (3) ṛcassāmarasaḥ sāmna udgītho rasaḥ | sa eṣa rasānāṃ rasatamaḥ pramaḥ parārdhyoṣṭamo ya udgīthaḥ | katamā

([61 r])  bhavāmi brāhmaṇānāṃ yaśo rājñāṃ ya?śoviśāṃ yaśohamanuprāpatsi sa hāhaṃ yaśāsāṃ yaśa śyaitamadat (2) madatkam śyaitam lindumābhigāṃ lindumābhigāṃ .. 14 ..
taddhaitatbrahmā prajāpataya uvāca prajāpatirmmana (3) ve manuḥ prajābhyaḥ ācāryakulādvedamadhītya yathāvidhānaṃ guroḥ karmmātiśeṣeṇābhisamāvṛtya kuṭuṃbe śu (4) cau deśe svādhyāyamadhīyāno dhārmikānvidadhadātmani sarvendriyāṇi saṃpratiṣṭhāpyāhi san sa (5) rvabhūtānyatratīrthebhyassa khalvevaṃ vartayanyāvadāyuṣam brahmalokamabhisaṃpadyate na ca punarāvarta (6) te ca punarāvartate .. 15 .. 
apyāyayantu mamāṃgāni vākprāṇaḥ cakṣuśrotramatho balamindriyāṇi ca sarvā (7) ṇi 
sarvaṃ brahmopaniṣadam māham brahmanirākuryyāma mamāk brahmanirākarodanirākaraṇam astvanirākaraṇam me astu tadātma (8) ni nirate ya upaniṣatsu dharmmāste mayi santu te mayi santu 2103 aṣṭamodhyāyaḥ iti chāndogyopaniṣat samāptam
 

</text></TEI>