<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tei-to-html.xsl" ?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Raghuvaṃśavyākhyā, cantos 8,9</title>
            
         <editor><persName>Anuja Ajotikar</persName><orgName>University of Hamburg</orgName></editor></titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TST Project</publisher>
            <date>2023</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>
                     <orgName>Staats- und Universitätsbibliothek Hamburg Carl von Ossietzky</orgName>
                  </repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">PBS 12</idno>
                  <idno type="alternate"/>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#STM">
                  <summary>Manuscript is of commentary on Raghuvaṃśa. It is an incomplete manuscript but there is a note on the paper which identifies the manuscript as Raghuvaṃśavyākhyā, cantos 8,9. It is mentioned in the same note that commenatary by Mallinātha. 

Manuscript has thick wooden guard folio as cover. The condition is delicate. Some folio are broken into half. It needs more attention to check the content of the manuscript. </summary>
                  
               <msItem xml:id="Raghuvyakhya" defective="true"><title xml:lang="sa">Raghuvaṃśavyākhyā   </title><textLang mainLang="san"/><filiation><p>New Catalogus Catalogorum Vol 22 pp 233-252</p></filiation><incipit xml:lang="sa">[1v 1] da lokake . kādi[varjjam]? valokaḥ brāhmemuhūrte kila tasya deviku (gap due to broken folio)
[1v 2] tā bhrahmaṇahava?na….</incipit><explicit xml:lang="sa">[77 r] 4 prājāpatyeti nṛpo daśarathaḥ prājāpatyena prajāpatisaṃbandhitāpuruṣeṇa upanitaṃ na tu śi?ṣṭhena [pra?]</explicit></msItem></msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  
                  
                  
                  
                  
               <objectDesc form="loose-leaf" rend="manuscript">
                     <supportDesc material="palm-leaf">
                        
                        <extent>
                           <measure unit="folio" quantity="81">2 guard folio 2 blank folio and 77 written folio.</measure>
                           <dimensions type="object" unit="mm">
                              
                              
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <width quantity="380" min="200" max="380"/>
                              <height quantity="32" min="30" max="32"/>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <width quantity="330" min="200" max="330"/>
                              <height quantity="21" min="15" max="21"/>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        
                        
                        
                     <support>
                           <p>Thick wooden guard folio.</p>
                        </support><foliation>Tamil letter numerals in the left margin of the recto side of the folio.  Folio numbers are lost due to damage. 77r is unnumbered.
[1]--[77]</foliation><condition>Delicate condition. Some folio are broken into half.
</condition></supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="4 5" streams="1"/>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc><handDesc><handNote scope="sole" script="grantha" medium="ink black incised"><desc>Neat writing but due to damaged folio and ink it is difficult to read. </desc></handNote></handDesc><additions>
                  <desc type="user-related-note" subtype="detached front">Title of the manuscript and some related information is written in English on the white paper.   The note mentions: Raghuvaṃśavyākhyā, Sargas 8,9  By Mallinātha, Granth, 140 — 4-5  
</desc></additions><bindingDesc>
                     <binding>
                        <p>twine string  is used to wrap folio.</p>
                        <decoNote type="stringhole">
                           <measure unit="stringhole" quantity="2"/>
                        </decoNote>
                    </binding>
                  </bindingDesc></physDesc>
               <history>
                  
                  
                  
               <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="gregorian"/>
                     
                  </origin></history>
               <additional>
                  <listBibl>
                     
                  <bibl>The Raghuvamśa of Kālidāsa with the Commentary of Mallinātha
Edited with a literal English translation, with copious notes in English intermixed with full extracts, illucidating the text, from the commentaries of Bhaṭṭa Hemādri, Chāritravardhana, Vallabha, Dinakaramiśra, Sumativijaya, Vijayagaṇi, Vijayānandasūri's Varacharaṇasevaka, and Dharmameru, with various readings Edited with a literal English translation, with copious notes in English intermixed with full extracts, illucidating the text, from the commentaries of Bhaṭṭa Hemādri, Chāritravardhana, Vallabha, Dinakaramiśra, Sumativijaya, Vijayagaṇi, Vijayānandasūri's Varacharaṇasevaka, and Dharmameru, with various readings c., c. edi. Nandargikar, Gopal Raghunath, Publisher: Motilal Banarsidass, Delhi: Fourth edi, 1971
Source: Archaeological Survey of India, New Delhi (E-Book)

</bibl></listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc><p>Square brackets are used to show inferred reading. Question marks are used to show doubt. </p></encodingDesc>
      
   <revisionDesc/></teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
   </facsimile>
<text corresp="#Raghuvyakhya" xml:lang="sa">[1v 1] da lokake . kādi[varjjam]? valokaḥ brāhmemuhūrte kila tasya deviku (gap due to broken folio)
[1v 2] tā bhrahmaṇahava?na….

[77 r] 4 prājāpatyeti nṛpo daśarathaḥ prājāpatyena prajāpatisaṃbandhitāpuruṣeṇa upanitaṃ na tu śi?ṣṭhena [pra?]</text></TEI>