<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tei-to-html.xsl" ?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Manusmṛti</title>
            
         <editor><persName>Anuja Ajotikar</persName><orgName>University of Hamburg</orgName></editor></titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TST Project</publisher>
            <date>2023</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>
                     <orgName>Staats- und Universitätsbibliothek Hamburg Carl von Ossietzky</orgName>
                  </repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">PBS 15</idno>
                  <idno type="alternate"/>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#STM">
                  <summary>Although the foliation appears to be continuing, the verses in the manuscript are arranged very differently from those in the printed versions. Either the lines are skipped, or it is a selection of verses.  Additionally, it's possible that the manuscript folios are disorganized due to their fragile condition. The manuscript requires careful attention because it is severely damaged.
 On folio 52 verses 238, 244 from 8th chapter are identified. The last line of the folio is of the verse 251 from the 8th chapter. On folio [53?]  verses 219 220 from the 8th chapter are spotted. On folio 82 verses 261, 262 from chapter 9 are found. [86v?] has verses 203-205 from the 11th chapter are identified.   </summary>
                  
               <msItem xml:id="Manusmirti" defective="true"><title xml:lang="sa"> Manusmṛti</title><author xml:lang="sa">Manu</author><textLang mainLang="san"/><filiation><p>New Catalogus Catalogorum vol 18 pp:182-186
</p></filiation><incipit xml:lang="sa">1v1 (gap of approximately 18 syllables due to damaged folio.) abhigamya maharṣayaḥ / pratipūjya yathānyāyam idaṃ vacanam abruvan // bhagavan sarvavarṇānāṃ [gap of 5 syllables due to damaged folio.] nupūrvaśaḥ /
[antaraprabhavānāṃ ca dha] [gap of 6 syllables due to damaged folio.]
</incipit><explicit xml:lang="sa">[67r] 8 (gap due to damaged folio) vaṃ sañcintya manasā pretty karmmaphaloda (gap due to damaged folio).</explicit></msItem></msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  
                  
                  
                  
                  
               <objectDesc form="loose-leaf" rend="manuscript">
                     <supportDesc material="palm-leaf">
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        
                     <support>
                           <p>Thick wooden guard covers. Looks newer than the original manuscript.  Originally thin palm leaf is used as a cover but it is damaged so new wooden covers are used to conserve the mansucript.</p>
                        </support><extent>
                           <measure unit="folio" quantity="70">2 new and 2 old guard covers, 86 written folio</measure>
                           <dimensions type="object" unit="mm">
                              
                              
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <width quantity="400" min="100"/>
                              <height quantity="33" min="20"/>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <width quantity="385" min="100"/>
                              <height quantity="30" min="18"/>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent><foliation>Tamil numerals in the left margin. Mostly margin is damaged hence nuemrarion is lost.</foliation><condition>Delicate. </condition></supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="6 7" streams="1"/>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc><handDesc><handNote script="grantha" medium="ink incised"><desc>Well written.</desc></handNote></handDesc><additions>
                  </additions><bindingDesc>
                     <binding>
                        
                        <decoNote type="stringhole">
                           <measure unit="stringhole" quantity="2"/>
                        </decoNote>
                    </binding>
                  </bindingDesc></physDesc>
               <history>
                  
                  
                  
               <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="gregorian"/>
                     
                  </origin></history>
               <additional>
                  <listBibl>
                     
                  <bibl>Manu's Code Of Law A Critical Edition And Translation Of The Mānava Dharmaśāstra Patrick Olivelle with editorial assistance of Suman Olivelle.  (South Asia Research)
</bibl></listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc><p>sapce is added to separate words. </p></encodingDesc>
      
   <revisionDesc/></teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
   </facsimile>
<text corresp="#Manusmirti" xml:lang="sa">1v1 (gap of approximately 18 syllables due to damaged folio.) abhigamya maharṣayaḥ pratipūjya yathānyāyam idaṃ vacanam abruvan bhagavan sarvavarṇānāṃ [gap of 5 syllables due to damaged folio.] nupūrvaśaḥ 
[antaraprabhavānāṃ ca dha] [gap of 6 syllables due to damaged folio.]

1v 2 marhasi . jayāyujāṇḍajānāñca tathā yaṃ saṃsveda[jodbhidām] . bhūtagrāmasya (sarvasya (interliner addition)) utpattipralayaṃ tathā . ācārāṇāṃ ca sarveṣāṃ tathā kāryā [gap of 4 syllables due to broken folio]. yathākālaṃ yathāyogaṃ vaktumarhasyeśa [gap of 3 or 4 syllables due to damaged folio.]

1v 3 tvam eko hy asya sarvasya vidhānasya svayaṃbhuvaḥ acintyasyāprameyasya kāryatattvārthavit prabho

[67r] (folio is badly damaged.) 
[67r] 7 (gap due to damaged folio) pakṛnmucyate pāpāttathā dānena cāpadi (gap due to damaged folio). (According to  Manu's Code of Law, the critical edition of Manusmriti, by Prof Patrick Olivelle this verse is from chapter 11.228)

[67r] 8 (gap due to damaged folio) vaṃ sañcintya manasā pretty karmmaphaloda (gap due to damaged folio). (According to  Manu's Code of Law, the critical edition of Manusmriti, by Prof Patrick Olivelle this verse is from chapter 11.232)</text></TEI>