<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tei-to-html.xsl" ?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Alaṃkāranikaṣa</title>
            
         <editor><persName>Anuja Ajotikar</persName><orgName>University of Hamburg</orgName></editor></titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TST Project</publisher>
            <date>2023</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>
                     <orgName>Staats- und Universitätsbibliothek Hamburg Carl von Ossietzky</orgName>
                  </repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">PBS 49</idno>
                  <idno type="alternate"/>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#STM">
                  <summary>This  is  a text book of rhetoric. It seems to be rare book as very few manuscripts are noted in  New Catalogus Catalogorum and Aufrecht Catalogus.  Front documentation note in Grantha Script -  Alaṃkāranikaṣa Sudhīndrayogīviracita  Third word is unclear.  Due to severe damage to the last folio, the text has been lost. 
Before folio 1v some thing is scribbled in Granth script and numer 2 in Tamil written in the left margin. This folio's unclear content doesn't appear to be connected to the text Alaṃkāranikaṣa.</summary>
                  
               <msItem xml:id="alankaranikash" defective="true"><title xml:lang="sa"> Alaṃkāranikaṣa   </title><author xml:lang="sa">Sudhīndrayogī</author><textLang mainLang="san"/><filiation><p>New Catalogus Catalogorum vol 01 pp: 294
 Aufrecht Catalogus vol-1:p-032.</p></filiation><incipit xml:lang="sa">1v1 [gap of 1 syllable due to wormhole]yādyaḥ premakopāvaharacibhramarāt saṃbhramāntamumauleścuḍācandromuḍāni caraṇanakhadakhāpuritārdhaḥ purāreḥ yasyālokena rākā rajanikarapari [gap of 2 syllables due to broken folio.]
</incipit><explicit xml:lang="sa">80v 12 [tvā]t vi (gap of approximately 13 syllables due to broken folio.)  saṃsānu tanmate smṛtiparyyavasa (gap of approximately 5 syllables due to broken folio.)  dukta sādṛśyanibandhanātpraprastutapraśaṃsāviśeṣa aiva aprastutapraśaṃsā syādaprakāṇḍe tathāspatiḥ sukhañjivati [nariṇā?]

81r 1 vane (gap of almost of half of the line as folio is damaged.)  nta? sulabhairjaladaṃ ? ārā

81r 2 vasādhī (gap of almost of half of the line as folio is damaged.) ṇa (gap of a syllable due to injured folio.) ca tena darśitatvāt sukhañjīvatītyeta(cca) (gap of almost of half of the line as folio is damaged.) ṇṇena manasvinītyinmati? garja? (gap of a few syllables due to broken folio.) prastutapraśaṃsanasāmānyalakṣaṇasya stutiparyā</explicit></msItem></msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  
                  
                  
                  
                  
               <objectDesc form="loose-leaf" rend="manuscript">
                     <supportDesc material="palm-leaf">
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        
                     <support>
                           <p>Thin plam leaf as guard folio. </p>
                        </support><extent>
                           <measure unit="folio" quantity="83">2 guard folio and 81 written</measure>
                           <dimensions type="object" unit="mm">
                              
                              
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <width quantity="450"/>
                              <height quantity="33"/>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="written" unit="mm">
                              <width quantity="420"/>
                              <height quantity="25"/>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent><foliation>Tamil Letter numerals in the left margin of the verso.</foliation><condition>Despite the corners of the folio being damaged, it is in good condition of preservation.</condition></supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="8" streams="1"/>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc><handDesc><handNote script="grantha" medium="ink incised"><desc>Readable.</desc></handNote></handDesc><additions>
                  <desc type="blessing" subtype="beginning marginal">On 1v hariḥ oṃ is written in the left margin. 
</desc></additions><bindingDesc>
                     <binding>
                        
                        <decoNote type="stringhole">
                           <measure unit="stringhole" quantity="2"/>
                        </decoNote>
                    </binding>
                  </bindingDesc></physDesc>
               <history>
                  
                  
                  
               <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="gregorian"/>
                     
                  </origin></history>
               <additional>
                  <listBibl>
                     
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc><p>Question mark is used to show doubtful reading. Spaces are added to separate words at some places.</p></encodingDesc>
      
   <revisionDesc/></teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
   </facsimile>
</TEI>